<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vncasing of heresie, or, The anatomie of protestancie. Written and composed by O.A..</title>
            <author>Almond, Oliver.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121925</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857082</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857082</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 817:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vncasing of heresie, or, The anatomie of protestancie. Written and composed by O.A..</title>
                  <author>Almond, Oliver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 208 [i.e. 110] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Pierre Auroi] Cum licentia superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Douai :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno DC.XXIII. [sic, 1623].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>O.A. = Oliver Almond.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 104-201 skipped in numbering, numerous other errors.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNCASING OF HERESIE, <hi>OR,</hi> THE ANATOMIE OF <hi>PROTESTANCIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written and Compoſed by <hi>O. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Licentia Superiorum.</hi> ANNO DC.XXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough the diuell in no age euer wanted his emiſſaries, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt agents, who buſilie laboureth in ſowing <hi>tares</hi> &amp; <hi>death-bringing-darnel</hi> in the pureſt corne-fields of Gods Church, &amp; like cunning <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebankes,</hi> left no wily inuention vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tried, which they ſuppoſed might any way ſerue to vent their <hi>adulterate theriaca</hi> &amp; <hi>baſtardly balſamum;</hi> yet he had neuer ſuch hopes to ſtore the vaſt caues of his infernal manſion with Chriſtian ſoules, as in this age of ours, in which whole ſwarmes of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and deceiuing Miniſters, are crept into the Church, introducing (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles propheſie, ſundrie ſects of perdition, by ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broach,
<pb facs="tcp:22753:3"/>
the infectious, peſtilent, and long-ſince condemned dregges of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, brewed by <hi>Simon Magus, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus, Cerdon, Manichaeus, Aerius, Euſtachius, Vigilantius,</hi> and other ſuch ſubiects of <hi>Abaddon,</hi> and after barrelled vp by Belzebub, and carefully reſerued in his chiefe ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; where though with long ſtanding they were growne muſtie and ſtinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet by powring in the <hi>barme of libertie,</hi> they haue made them flower againe, and by hanging forth the Iui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bush of <hi>Noueltie</hi> (ſet out and garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with Rhetoricall flowers) haue drawne more cuſtomers then hells wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt counſellor durſt euer hope for.</p>
            <p>For the better diſcouerie of all which infectious potions, and vtter diſmantling of ſuch lewde Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bankes, which like Egiptian locuſts co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the face of this ſome-time Angelike
<pb facs="tcp:22753:3"/>
Ile, depopulating her once florishing vineyeardes, and ſweete-ſenting gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, I preſent thee with this enſuing Treatiſe, in which thou shalt find plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated, That <hi>Luther, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Zwinglius,</hi> and other Prime-doctors of Proteſtancie, were (by their owne confeſsions) baptized and brought vp in the now Roman Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and only by their apoſtacie gaue life and being to Proteſtancie, and that the Proteſtant Martirologies, Callen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, and genialogical tables, conſiſt either of confeſſed Papiſts, knowne Schiſmatikes, deteſted heretikes, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Atheiſts, accurſed Magitians, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious thieues, or notorious Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</p>
            <p>That all the chiefe doctrines, and principles of Proteſtancie, are old con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned hereſies; and that the moſt damned hereſies rhat euer were hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:22753:4"/>
in any age, haue bene foſtered, cherished, and defended by the chief: doctors in the Proteſtant Church.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That no Proteſtant, eſpecially of the Caluinean ſect (vvhich are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knovvne by the names of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants here in <hi>England,</hi> of Puritants in <hi>Scotland,</hi> of Caluiniſts in <hi>Sauoy;</hi> of Sacramentaries in <hi>Heluetia;</hi> of Hugonettes in <hi>France,</hi> of Picardes in <hi>Bohemiah,</hi> and of Gomoriſts, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians, Remonſtrants, Contraremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants in <hi>Holland,</hi> and other partes of Germanie) can be ſaid (if he follow the doctrines of his chiefe doctors) to beleeue aright any one Article of the Apoſtles Creede.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> That the God of the Proteſtants (according to their chiefe doctrines, &amp; the famous confeſsions of ſome of the the ſame fraternitie) is no other but a diuell of hell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22753:4"/>The due conſideration of either of which heades or chapters, vvill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly fuffice to perſwade anie man that is carefull of his ſaluation, and hath not made a couenant with death &amp; hel, to fly the fellovvship of this heretical fraternitie, &amp; haſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the rock of that true Roman Catholike Church, from vvhole top, <hi>Luther, Caluin,</hi> &amp; other their Cymiſts (by the incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the flesh, the vvorld, and the diuell) caſting them ſelues head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, fell into the ſea of hereſies in vvhich to be by death drenched, is to eternally loſt, and certainely ſwallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved vp in the <hi>Charibdis of hells</hi> bottomleſſe abiſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:5"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE CONTENCE</hi> of the firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>THAT <hi>Luther, Caluin, Zwinglius, Bucer, Oſiander,</hi> and all other prime Doctors of Proteſtancie vvere by their ovvne Confeſsions, borne, baptized, and bred in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholike Church, and by their falſe beganne Proteſtancie; that the ſaid Luther, (by his ovvne and moſt other chiefe Proteſtants aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vvas the firſt knovvne Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, a ſonne, vvith out a father, and a ſcholler vvithout a maſter.</p>
               <p>That neither <hi>Illiricus, Fulke,</hi> FOXE, or <hi>White,</hi> in their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded bedrowe of Proteſtant vvitneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, haue produced one true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; but haue shamefully ſtuffed their Catalogues vvith many knovve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and confeſſed Roman Catholikes, infinite ſtore of deſperate heretikes and a multitude of infamous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:22753:5"/>
               <head>The contents of the ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <p>THat the chiefe doctrines &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Proteſtant Religion <hi>viz.</hi> That vve may be ſaued by faith onely; that there is no free vvill to good; that children may be ſaued vvithout baptiſme; that Chriſtians enioy not the veritie of the olde fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures; that the Sacraments doe not conferre grace; that the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes are impoſsible to be kept; that Chriſtians are not tyed in conſcience to performe the Lavvs of the church, or com mon vveale; that all thinges happen by ineuitable neceſsitie; that Chriſts and S. Iohns baptiſme vvere all one; that the Church may be for ſome time inuiſible; that Altars, holy oyle, and the like are to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that approoued generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels may erre; that the dead are not to be prayed for; that Images are not to be ſet vp and vvorshipped; that Matrimonie is of equall merit vvith Virginitie; that Chriſt is not Realie
<pb facs="tcp:22753:6"/>
in the Euchariſt; that the Saints can nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther heare our prayers nor helpe vs; that the Sea of Rome is the ſeate of peſtilence; that Indulgences are of no vvorth, &amp;c. are old condemned hereſies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The contence of the third Chapter.</head>
               <p>THat the chiefe Doctors of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancie, teach a pluralitie of gods; cannot vvell brooke the vvord Trinitie; deny that Chriſt is God of God; or that the Eſſence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvas communicated to him; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that Chriſt vvas inferour to his Father, as touching his diuinitie; maintaine that Chriſt is his Fathers vicar, or vicegerent as he is God; that he had tvvo perſons; that he vvas ſubiect to ignorance and vicious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; that he is not omnipotent, nor able to doe many things; that he cannot be adored vvith out Idolatry, becauſe his humanity is ioyned to his Godhead; that the bleſſed virgin remained not a Virgin in, &amp; after her
<pb facs="tcp:22753:6"/>
child-birth; that she vvas ſubiect to the infirmities of other vvomen in child-bearing; that Chriſts natiuitie and incarnation vvere no vvay meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious; that Chriſts diuine nature vvas crucified, ſuffered and dead to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vvith his humaine; that his corporall death vvas nothing auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, &amp;c. that Chriſt died not for all men, but for ſome fevv; that Chriſt deſcended not at all into hell; that his ſoule lay together vvith his body in the graue; that he freed not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes and Prophets in his deſcent; that he could not raiſe himſelfe from the death by his ovvne povver; that his Reſurrection &amp; Aſcention vvere no vvay miraculous, &amp;c. that men neede not feare that their vvorkes shall come into iudgement; that the holy ghoſt hath a diſtinct Eſſence from the Father and the Sonne; that he is vnequal to the Father and the Sonne, &amp;c. that the church may erre in fundamentall points; that it vvas inuiſible for a 1000. years together at leſt, &amp;c. that mens ſins are neuer truly
<pb facs="tcp:22753:7"/>
remitted; no not in baptiſme, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The contence of the fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THat God (according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtants expreſſe doctrines) doth not onely permit, but force men to ſinne; that ſome men by naked decree of God, vvithout any deſert of their ovvne, are Predeſtinated to eternall damnation; that hovvſoeuer God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that he vvould haue all men ſaued, yet he neuer meant ſo; that the moſt vvicked perſons that euer vvere, vvere of God appointed to be vvicked euen as they vvere; that the diuel is but Gods agent or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth but vvhat God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth him, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:7"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Doctors: to the <hi>Worshipfull Maiſters: and to the</hi> worthie Students of the Vniuerſitie of Oxford.</head>
            <p>BEing admonished by a deare friend of myne, that this Treatiſe was defectiue, in that it wanted an Epiſtle Dedicatorie. I conſidered with my ſelfe, and reſolued to recommend it vnto the Vniuerſitie of Oxford, in reſpect that it was penned by a Scholler, and ſometime a ſtudent of the ſaid Vniuerſitie. And I my ſelfe in my youth ſucked the breaſts of that Nurſe. Often admiring the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple robes and decorum of the Doctors: accounting of them, as of the Senators and Sages of England. But yet euer deteſting ſchiſme and hereſie in my hart, being by Gods prouidence and goodnes euen <hi>acunabulis</hi> from my cradle inclyned to Catholike faith and Religion. Whereupon I left my natiue ſoyle, and trauelled into forrayne Countries, where often reflecting with aſtoniſhment, that men of that outward grauitie, eloquence and learning ſhould be ſo ouer-shaddowed with ſo darke a cloude of error, ſchiſme, and hereſie, and of ſo weake a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to thinke all the world to be ecclipſed. and that the light of the Goſpel could ſhine onely from <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martir,</hi> two Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata Fryers, or any ſuch rabble. Returning into my Countrie, eſpecially ſince his Maieſties happie raigne ouer Great Britaine. I ioyed much to ſee, as it were at our time, the prime places of Prelacie oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed
<pb facs="tcp:22753:8"/>
by Oxford men: as Canterburie by D. <hi>Abbot</hi> Yorke by D.<note place="margin">The prime place of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> 
               <hi>Tobie Matthew,</hi> Wincheſter by D. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Durrham by D <hi>Iames<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Rocheſter by D. <hi>Puke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig,</hi> London by D. <hi>King,</hi> an Eloquent Pulpit man, who was vexed long vvith a grieuous painefull ſickeneſſe of the ſtone. Oftentimes <hi>afflictio dat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectum</hi> There vvas a conſtant report, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a Prieſt before his death, and to die a member of the Catholike-Roman Church; If the report were true, a memorable note of Gods grace and goodnes; If not true, the vvorſt to himſelfe: wherefore my innated affection towardes your perſons, and the place, vrgeth mee to dedicate this Treatiſe vnto you, hoping that it may vvorke ſome good effect among you.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Novv hauing named the vvorthie men of Oxford for their prime place for Prelacie. I muſt not omitte the more vvorthie men for good life &amp; learning, vvho left all vvorldly preferment, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned baniſhment, vndertooke voluntarie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, and forſooke all delights and pleaſures of this land for their Religion, and for the profeſſion of the Catholike Roman faith,<note place="margin">The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors who left Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> and for the ſaluation of their ſoules. And firſt I name <hi>VVilliam Allen,</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, profeſſor and reader of the Diuinitie lectur in the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Doway,</hi> the firſt Founder and Preſident of the Engliſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge at <hi>Doway,</hi> vvho vvent vp to Rome and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned of Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 13. the foundation of that Seminarie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cardinall</hi> ALLEN.</note> and exhibition for a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Schollers there to be maintained Aftervvard in Pope <hi>Syxtus quintus</hi> time, he vvas called to <hi>Rome</hi> againe, and there created Cardinal. the 7. of Auguſt, anno Dom. 1587. vvhen hee receaued his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals Hatte. the Pope pronounced theſe vvords. <hi>Ego creoto Ducem, principem, ſocium regum, Cardinalem Angliae, &amp; fratrem meum.</hi> A worthie title for ſo vvorthie a man. Secondly, I name D. <hi>Audoeu,</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:22753:8"/>
               <hi>Owen Lewes</hi> an Oxford man,<note place="margin">D. <hi>LEWES</hi> Archbis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppe of Caſſana.</note> vvho vvas Reader of the Lavv lecture in the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Doway</hi> for ſome yeares, after ſent for by the Metropolitan of Cambray, and by him ſent to Rome, to negotiat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant buſineſſe of his, vvhich happely being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, he remained there, and vvas made Ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie to the Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 13. and Vicar general vnder the Ar h-biſhop of Millan, <hi>Carollus Boro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus</hi> the Sainct: after elected and conſecrated Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Caſſana, and viſitor general in Rome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. and in election to haue bene Cardinall. if he had not bene preuented by death. What should I name D. <hi>Harding,</hi> D. <hi>Sanders,</hi> D.<note place="margin">D. <hi>HAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DING</hi> and others.</note> 
               <hi>Briſtow, D. Stapleton,</hi> vvith other Oxford men all moſt famous for learning as their vvorkes written againſt the hereſies of this age, now extant doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. <hi>Gregorie Martine, William Reonals, M. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall, M. Marshial,</hi> Licentiat in Diuinitie, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie others for breuities ſake I doe ommitte worthie members of the Vniuerſitie of Oxford. Among the Fathers of the Societie. <hi>Edmund Campion, Robert Parſons,</hi> a famous writer, with others. Reuerend Prieſtes, I thinke I may ſay deſcending from the ſame Nurcerie, aboue a hundred. D. <hi>Barret,</hi> D. <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thington,</hi> both Oxford men, and Preſidents ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely in the Colledge of Rhemes and Dowaye. And now ſpeaking of the gouernours of Colledges, I cannot omitte to letaine and number in this rancke the now preſent Preſident, D.<note place="margin">The Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Doway.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kelliſon</hi> (although not an Oxford man, yet I know a well-willer to that Vniuerſitie) a mylde <hi>Moyſies</hi> for his gouernment, readie to giue content to all men, a louer of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a premoter of pietie, a great writer. Shall I omitte D. <hi>Cicile,</hi> who was Almner and Confeſſor vnto the ſyſter of <hi>Henrie</hi> the third K. of France,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> CICEL</note> and wife and Queene to <hi>Henrie</hi> the 4, D. <hi>Bagshow.</hi> D. <hi>Bishoppe.</hi> I cannot but admire and praiſe the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and goodneſſe of Almightie God in this time
<pb facs="tcp:22753:9"/>
of perſecutions, to conſider men who haue left their countrie, accepted of banishment, content with pouertie, abrogated the world, without al hope of preferment, yet aduanced aboue all expectation. Therefore looke at this preſent, and caſt your eyes vppon D.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. GIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORD</hi> Peere of France.</note> 
               <hi>Gifford,</hi> in his youth a ſcholler of Oxford, if I miſtake not, went ouer the ſeaes, was <hi>a lumnus</hi> of the Colledge of Rome, after became Reader of Diuinitie in the Engliſh Colledge of Rhemes, and now promoted by <hi>Lewes</hi> the 13. King of France, to be Arch-biſhop of Rhemes, Metropolitan, and Peere of France, for his learning, for his pietie, for his eazle againſt the Hugonettes of France, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Pulpit man, who Preached before the King at Paris, a whole Lent. In Germanie we had D. <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rner,</hi> an Oxford man, in the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Ingolſtad,</hi> heighlie eſteemed for his learning, eloquence and Oratorie. D. <hi>Spetheri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> vvas Theologus to Cardinal <hi>Paleat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. ELIE.</note> Archbiſhop of Bolonia. D <hi>Elie</hi> was reader in the Vniuerſitie of Moſſapoat in Lorayne manie yeares for his learning in the Law, cannon &amp; ciuil, famous, his elder brother ſometime was Preſident of the colledge of Iohns in Oxford, he was a Prieſt in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, and dyed in the latter time of Queene Elizabeth, a priſoner in the Citie of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford. If I should vndertake to capitulate or reakon all our renowned Confeſſors and Prieſts, now la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring in England, or detayned in priſon, or dead, I should be ouer-long.</p>
            <p>O Oxford, Oxford, thou that haſt had ſo manie worthie men that haue fledde from the ſeate of Peſtilence, and nurſe of ſchiſme and hereſie into forraine nations and countries, and haue for their learning, pietie and deuotion, bene heighly aduanced abroad. Conſider alſo how many Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs haue dyed, how manie Confeſſors, how many Prieſts haue bene and are impriſoned at home, for profeſſion of Catholike Faith and Religion. And
<pb facs="tcp:22753:9"/>
thou vvhich ſhould be the lanterne of the Land, the Pillar of light, the ſchoole of learning, the mother of peace, the nurſe of pietie; art now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the darke cloud of hereſie, the foggie miſt of Aegypt, the mayntaine of ſchiſme, the ſtrength of Puritaniſme, and miſtriſſe of ignorance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherefore this liitle Treatiſe is addreſſed vnto you, Maiſters and ſtudents of Oxford, and you who are in purple robes, as Senators and Sages of the land, that you may vncaſe your ſelues, caſt off your viſeards, expel the rauening Wolfes. And know your ſelues, and acknowledge your errours, ſchiſme, and hereſie, and returne to your mother Church, <hi>benigna mater eſt,</hi> ſhe is a louing mother, to receaue you. Hell gates cannot preuaile againſt her, ſhe hath the holy Ghoſt to aſſiſt and direct her in all truth of doctrine and maners, and good life.</p>
            <p>You know the Arch-biſhop of Spalata, a learned Prelate, as you all confeſſe,<note place="margin">Archbishop of Spalato.</note> he conuerſed vvith your prime Prelate, viſited your Vniuerſities, enformed himſelfe of your doctrine, wayed your Church, &amp; Congregation, in his prudentiall ballence, and found you <hi>minus habens,</hi> to want wayt, to be ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall: he retyred himſelfe with deſire to returne home againe, not for that he miſlyked his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynement; for he was highly eſteemed of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, much honoured of your Prime Prelate, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed by the Nobilitie, he had large maintenance 800. or a thouſand pounde reuenew <hi>per annum,</hi> whereby hee might commaunde all the delicates, delites and pleaſures that the land could yeeld, yet not ſatisfied in conſcience, nor content in minde, labored to get licence of his Maieſtie, to returne, which he obtained,<note place="margin">His depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> or elſe was commanded by him to depart the Realme. Why did he thus? but reflecting vpon his eſtate, being aged, to prouide for death, to forſake ſchiſme, to ſaue his ſoule. I am credible imformed, being vrged to declare his
<pb facs="tcp:22753:10"/>
minde,<note place="margin">His cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Church of England.</note> &amp; what he thought concerning the Church of England; he clearely anſwered, that it was but a ſchiſmatical Church, a part diuided from the bodie myſticall of Chriſt, a congregation that had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the mother Church of the world. Conſider and ruminate well (you worthie ſtudents) the ſentence and cenſure of this learned Prelate Out of all doubt, there is no ſaluation, but in the true Church.</p>
            <p>There is not the meaneſt among you, if he doe but read the Annales of <hi>M. Iohn Stowe,</hi> but he ſhall clearly vnderſtand, how, &amp; when the ſchiſme began in K <hi>Henrie</hi> 8.<note place="margin">Schiſme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon by K. <hi>HENRIE</hi> the 8.</note> his time, vvho after he had raigned 20 yeares in peace with the Church of Rome ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a diuorce from his lawfull wife Q. <hi>Katherine,</hi> which the mother Church of the world neither could nor would graunt, or permit, the King being much diſcontented, &amp; deſirous to obtayne his purpoſe, beganne his ſchiſme, made himſelfe head of the Church of England, and by acte of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnited the title to his Emperiall Crowne, a thing <hi>in auditum,</hi> and neuer by any Chriſtian Prince practiſed before, vnleſſe <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted it. After hee had thus diuided himſelfe from the Church of Rome, and eſtabliſhed his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of headſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pp, he preſently quarrelled with the Cardinal, Biſhops, and Cleargie, and conuicted them of a preminire;<note place="margin">He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted the Cardinal, &amp; Cleargie of premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire.</note> ſo that they were forced to compounde with him, for a hunder thouſand pounds, which ſome they payde euerie pennie, and not content with this, but by Parlament alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated all the landes and goodes of the religious in his Kingdome; and ſo like a wilde bore, depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated and deſtroyed the Vineyard of our Lord. and ouerthrew ten thouſand Churches and Chappels,<note place="margin">Ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed all the Religious houſes.</note> which were erected, buylded, and maintained by his Predeceſſors, and aunceſtors, and by the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Nobilitie, and pietie of the people of this land. And within ſome yeares after, he ſpoyled
<pb facs="tcp:22753:10"/>
the ſepulchers and ſhrines of the Saints, and what was gold and ſiluer, and pretious ſtone,<note place="margin">Spoyled the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Saints.</note> either by oblations, offerings, or other waies not fearing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge a whitte, he tooke without ſcruple. And from one Chapple of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> of Canterburie, were nine or ten waynes loaden awaie with the wealth of that one place.<note place="margin">Put downe al Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</note> He alſo put downe and robbed all the holy places of pilgrimages, frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vſed by deuout people in former ages in this land.</p>
            <p>And to omitte other of his good vvorkes, in the 38 and laſt yeare of his raigne (a thing vvorth the noting) hauing had warres vvith France, and peace being concluded, it vvas proclaimed by Harralds, vvith ſound of trumpet the 13. of Iune, being Whit ſonday, and the ſame day a general Proceſſion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. in vvhich vvere borne all the richeſt ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Croſſes in London, of euerie Pariſh one, and the Prieſtes in their richeſt Coapes. This Preceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion came from Paules Church through Cheape and Cornehill, vp to Leaden Hall, and ſo vvent backe to Pauls againe. This vvas the laſt shevv of rich Croſſes and Coapes in London for ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all thoſe Croſſes and Coapes, vvith other the Church plate vvere commaunded, called for,<note place="margin">Robbed all Churches in <hi>Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </note> and taken by the Kinges Officers into the Kinges Treaſure and Wardrope, and neuer ſeene after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard. And ſo vvere cunningly all the Churches of London robbed on a daye. This vvas one of the laſt good vvorkes this Church-robber did. For in Ianuarie after he dyed an excommunicated perſon, vvhich excommunication vvas publiſhed by Pope Paule the 3. thus beganne the ſchiſme in England.</p>
            <p>Then ſucceeded Edward the ſixte, a childe, a boye of nine yeares of age, vvho continued the ſchiſme, he had the title of ſupreame head immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly in earth vnder God, of the Church of England and Ierland. He had two Vnckles, the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imers</hi> by the
<pb facs="tcp:22753:11"/>
mothers ſide, the one L. Protector, the other L. Admiral of England,<note place="margin">K. <hi>ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARD</hi> eſtablished the ſchiſme</note> both infected in German he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. Preſently the firſt yeare they beganne to alter the face of Catholike Religion, which K. Henrie his Father left, commanding the Rood, the Crucifixe, and all Images of Saints, in Churches to be pulled downe, forbidding beades, holy vvater, and other ceremonies, repelling the ſtatute of the ſixe articles made by <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, alſo commanded by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, the Communion to be miniſtred vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both kindes vnto the people, and ſeruice to be in the Engliſh tongue, Altars of ſtone to be taken dovvne, and communion Tables of vvood to be ſet in their roome. The new booke of common prayer vvas published by <hi>D. Ridlie,</hi> at Pauls Croſſe, &amp;c. Pride vvould not ſuffer theſe tvvo brothers peaceably to raigne together.<note place="margin">Pride of two Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, vvas condemned of heigh treaſon, and behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at Tovver hill. 3. yeare of Edvvard the ſixt. Shortly after by the cunning of the Lord <hi>Dudlie,</hi> Duke of Northu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berland,<note place="margin">L. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note> vvho aymed to ſettle the Crovvne in his ovvne blood, by the mariage of his fourth Sonne, vnto the Ladie <hi>Iane,</hi> daughter of the Ducheſſe of Suffolke, vvhich indeed vvas by him attempted, but be fayled in his purpoſe; <hi>Edward</hi> Duke of Sommerſet, L. Protector, vvas commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Tovver of London the 14. of October, the foorth yeere of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt. But deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out againe the ſit of Februarie for that time. But the firſt of December follovving, vvas arraigned at Weſtminſter, of fellonie and treaſon, and tryed by his Peeres,<note place="margin">L. Prete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note> and acquitted of treaſon, but ſound guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of fellonie, and the 22. of Ianuarie, beheaded at Tovver Hill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the fifth yeere of King <hi>Edward.</hi> Thus the ſchiſme beganne to be ſetled by the two Vncles (but GOD ſhewed his Iudgement of them) and had thought to haue bene continued by the Duke of Northumberland (although he died a
<pb facs="tcp:22753:11"/>
Catholike) for K. <hi>Edward</hi> being ſicke of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, the Duke married his fourth ſonne, the Lord <hi>Gifford,</hi> vnto the Ladie <hi>Iane,</hi> eldeſt daughter to the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> her mother was called <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> the ſecond daughter of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth and ſiſter to <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> being dead, the Ladie <hi>Iane</hi> by the Duke vvas proclaimed Queene. But God being for the vvoman, Queene <hi>Marie</hi> obtayned her right, had the Crowne,<note place="margin">Q. <hi>MARIE</hi> renounced the ſchiſme.</note> and raigned after her brother <hi>Edward,</hi> ſhe reſtored Catholike religion, reunited her ſelfe to the Sea Apoſtolike, returned to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church of Rome, diſanulled the title of the head of the Church, cauſed this Realme to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued from the cenſure of ſchiſme, and ſo mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned it during her life.</p>
            <p>After her deceaſe, Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſucceeded, and ſhe altered all againe, and tooke to her ſelfe,<note place="margin">Q. <hi>ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored the ſchiſme.</note> being a vvoman, to be head of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, reſtored the ſciſme vvhich vvas ſet vppe in K. <hi>Edwards</hi> time, by his two Vncles, ſhe ſetled Proteſtant religion, depriued the Catholike Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whether ſhe did this vppon zeale of Proteſtant Religion, to be the true vvay to ſaluation: It is doubfull, becauſe she profeſſed her ſelfe a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like all Queene Maries time, and vvas ſo brought vp in her fathers dayes.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is thought ſhe being a vvoman, did it vpon policie feare and reaſon of ſtate.<note place="margin">The reaſon to reſtore ſchiſme.</note> In pollicie ſhe knovv her next ſucceſſor in all right to be a Ladie as vviſe, and valiant as her ſelfe, vvhich was the L. <hi>Marie,</hi> Queene of Scotland, &amp; vvife to <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> K. of France, vvith all to be a conſtant proſef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for of the Catholike Religion. Therefore to make her ſubiects ſure vnto her, thought it in policie fit to winne them to a religion contrarie to hers. She al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies feared (as shee might indeede, knovving
<pb facs="tcp:22753:12"/>
her ovvne eſtate) to ſubiect her ſelfe to the Church of Rome, vvhich vvould neuer giue conſent to graunt that the diuorce of Queene <hi>Catherine</hi> vvas lawfull; but contrarie approoued her marriage to be good, neither vvould allow that her Father King <hi>Henrie</hi> ſhould haue tvvo vviues at once, and ſo conſequently, diſapprooued and annulled the Marriage of Queene <hi>Anne</hi> her mother, as illigiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate. By vvhat motiues, or reaſon ſoeuer ſhe vvas mooued, I knovv not, but it is certaine ſhe reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished and continued the ſchiſme from the Mother Church, the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>And King <hi>IAMES</hi> our Soueraigne, vvho novv by all right of ſucceſſion raigneth, came into this Kingdome, not with ſword, nor yet vvith gard of men;<note place="margin">K. <hi>IAMES</hi> maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſchiſme.</note> but vvith a ryding rodde in his hande, in all peace, vvelcomed of all, receaued of al, and being a Proteſtant, ſo brought vppe from his Cradle, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to maintaine the Religion hee here found, which he hath and doth performe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, you may vnderſtand, the ingreſſe and progreſſe of the ſchiſme of England, and vvhat vvill be the egreſſe vvee leaue to the preſcience and protection of Almightie God, <hi>Qui omnia nouit &amp; ſuauiter diſponit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus to returne vnto you the purple Sages, &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of Oxford, Vncaſe your ſelues, put off your Maskes and Viſardes, repent this ſchiſme, diſſolue the darke cloud of hereſie,<note place="margin">Church.</note> vvhich doth daſel your eyes, and be not vvilfully blinde, but beholde, the citie ſeated vpon an hill, and the candle light ſet vpon a candleſticke;<note place="margin">Roman faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed.</note> retyre vnto your Mother Church, from vvhich by ſchiſme you haue ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your ſelues: <hi>Domus Dei eſt firmiter aedificata ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra firmam patram,</hi> she is the houſe of God ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly built vpon the firme rocke. You cannot deny but S.<note place="margin">Rom. 1. v. 8. &amp; 13.</note> PAVLE prayſed, recommended, prayed for, and prophecied, that the Roman faith was, and is to be
<pb facs="tcp:22753:12"/>
renowned through the vvhole vvorld. You cannot denie, but this Iland receaued her firſt faith and Chriſtian Religion and Inſtruction from Rome. Among the Britaines, King <hi>Lucius,</hi> ſent vnto Pope <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> to be directed in Chriſtian faith:<note place="margin">Our firſt faith from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> and among the Saxons, <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, and firſt Pope of that name, called the Apoſtle of England by S. <hi>Bede,</hi> ſent S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and twelue Monkes to <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> King of Kent, vvho entred vvith the Croſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt.</hi> BED</note> and diſplayed banners vvith the Picture of Chriſt, and after builded Churches for M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe and Martins, and ſet vp in them the Crucifixe the bagge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, adorned them with Pictures of Saints, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected Altars of ſtone; all vvhich you haue exiled and abolished, and brought in place of them the Pictures of Lyons and Dragons, and Armes of Kings, vvith a vvoodden table for your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Alſo you cannot denie, but that the Nations and Countries, and people in this part of the world,<note place="margin">All nations in Europe, faith from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> receaued their Chriſtian faith from Rome, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her to be their Mother Church, as well as vvee. Why then doe you depart from her, why do you make this diuiſion &amp; ſchiſme in the world?</p>
            <p>It is true ſaye you, that the Roman faith vvas the true Chriſtian faith, and firſt eſtablished by S <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and after confirmed by S <hi>Paule,</hi> and therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelie called the Apoſtolicall Sea, &amp; Mother Church of the vvorld. But now there hath many errors crept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the Church; and it is an <hi>Axiome</hi> and <hi>maximam</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Proteſtant profeſſion, that the viſible Church conſiſting of men, hath erred &amp; may erre, <hi>quia hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum eſt errore,</hi> for that man is ſubiect to error.</p>
            <p>O dangerous &amp; damnable oppoſition, which doth ſeeke to deſtroy Catholike faith,<note place="margin">Sor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> no leſſe then the Arrian hereſie to deſtroy Chriſt and Chriſtian faith. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or it is as manifeſt in Scripture, that the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annot erre, againſt the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as it is true that Chriſt is God againſt the Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For its proued out
<pb facs="tcp:22753:13"/>
Scripture, that Chriſt vvas true God conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and coequal vvith his Father and no vvaye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior as God, but as man only: ſo it is as manifeſt in ſcripture, that Chriſt promiſed to be vvith his Church vnto the end of the vvorld, and that hee vvould ſend the holy Ghoſt to his Apoſtles, and conſequently to their ſucceſſors, and that this Church should inſtruct and teach the people all truth, both in doctrine, maners, and in good life: And that S. Paule doth aſſure vs, that the Church is <hi>columna &amp; firmamentum veritatis,</hi> the Pillar and foundation of truth, and from her vve haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſcripture, and the true meaning and ſence thereof infalliblie vvithout errour. Wherefore as the Arrian hereſie ſought to deſtroye Chriſt, and Chriſtian religion, in denying the Godhead of Chriſt; ſo Proteſtaniſme, in ſeeking to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throvv the infaillabilitie of the Church, indeauour to diſable Catholike faith and religion. And as the Arrians labored might and maine to infect the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, and to make a Pope of their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet fayled in the purpoſe. For Pope <hi>Foelix</hi> whom they promoted and preferred to the Papacie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned them as heretikes, &amp; defined againſt them, and dyed a Martyr. O prouidence of God: yea they ſo afflicted the Church, that the moſt part of the vvorld vvas ouer-clouded and darkned vvith this filthie cloud of Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereſie: yet <hi>praeualebit veritas,</hi> truth preuaileth, inſomuch that novv in the hartes of Chriſtian, &amp; Catholike people, nothing is more odious then this hereſie of the Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants condemned to the pit of hel. So the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants haue labored <hi>omnibus vijs &amp; modis</hi> (but not able to make a Proteſtant Pope) yet to ſovv this ſeede of Cockel and Darnel, that the Church of Rome may erre, that they haue infected and cauſed a great reuoult in theſe partes of Chriſtendome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that almoſt all Almanie, and a great part of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
<pb facs="tcp:22753:13"/>
is ouercome vvith this ſeede of infection: all England and Scotland gone:<note place="margin">A great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoult in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> Ireland ſtrongly aſſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: all Holland reuolted from God, Church and Prince: Braband and the Lovv Countries made to ſtagger: but God be thanked, they haue ouercome: A great part of France in tumultuous rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King, although he vvould giue them libertie of their conſcience, yet they vvill not yeeld him devv Temporall gouernement and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection. The Swiſſards euen to the confines of Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſtand ſtubborne in their obedience to the church of Rome, <hi>ſed praeualebit veritas,</hi> truth vvil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, and this hereſie of Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that the Church may erre, vvill be as odious in future ages, as Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme is novv.</p>
            <p>If vve argue vvith the Proteſtants,<note place="margin">Proteſtant flye from antiquitie, traditions, and prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church</note> to free the Church of Rome of imputation of error (as manie great Schollers haue vvritten many learned Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, concerning this poynt) and doe prooue by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, by practiſe of the Primatiue Church, by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions from the Apoſtles, concerning thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Religion, controuerted betvvne the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and the Catholikes, they flye off and ſaye they are not demonſtratiue arguments, to conuince in matters of doctrine, but only probable proofes.</p>
            <p>If vve vrge them vvith the decrees of Popes,<note place="margin">From de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes.</note> they care not for them; if vvith the doctrine of the Fathers, and Saincts of the Primatiue Church, as for example; if vve alleadge S. Auguſtine, that hee prayed for the ſoule of his Mother Monica, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Sacrifice of the Altar, Prayers, Almes,<note place="margin">From Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. <hi>S. Ave.</hi>
               </note> Oblations of the liuing, may profite the dead, that he vvrit a vvhole booke, <hi>De cura pro mortuis augen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> of the care to be had of the dead, and that the vvhole Church did ſupplicat and pray for the ſoules departed; they vvill anſvvere he vvas a particular man, it vvas his errour, and the errour of that time. Aerius vvas condemned for an Heretike, in appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:22753:14"/>
againſt the Church,<note place="margin">Epipha. haer. <hi>65.</hi> Aug. hae. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> in the 4. age concerning Prayer and Sacrifice to be offered for the ſoules departed, <hi>Caluins</hi> anſwere is. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>inſt. c.</hi> 5. §, 10. that the auncient Fathers, were deſtitute of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from God, to authorize prayer for the dead. Alleadge S.<note place="margin">S. Hillar.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> againſt <hi>Vigilantius</hi> a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Heretike, for inuocation, and veneration of Saints, for reuerencing of holy Relickes; for viſiting and celebrating the memories of their ſepulchers, and burning of waxe tapers, for obſeruing the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting dayes and vigils, determined by the Church, and Eccleſiaſticall authoritie, for profeſſion of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie and chaſtitie among Clergie men: they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ambroſe lib. <hi>4.</hi> de ſacr. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> it vvas his errour. Bring Saint Ambroſe for the Real preſence of Chriſts bodie in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſaying, that before Conſecration it vvas bread, but after Conſecration his verie true bodie and blood: it vvas his errour, If vvee allow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of S.<note place="margin">S. Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>Baſil</hi> and S. <hi>Benedictus</hi> for monaſticall life; they vvill vvith the <hi>Sabellia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> heretikes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne it for a crime, and reprooue it for a meere impietie, and ſay it vvas their errours, and ſo of the reſt of the ancient Fathers, they were men and might erre.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Generall Councels.</note>Proceede vvith them to generall Counſels, which doth repreſent the bodie of the Church, and alleadge the foure firſt, vvhich all the vvorld re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, and S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> highlie commended, and the mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Proteſtants doe not dare to denie; yet vvill the Puritans refuſe them, and the Proteſtants accept of them no farther then in their imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they shall agree vvith them, or ſerue their turnes. And as for the foure laſt generall Counſels (I vvill name the laſt firſt) the venerable Councell of Trent, the Councell of Florence, of Conſtance, and Lateran, the Proteſtants abſolutely auerce, that they haue gone awrye, and were deceaued in the principles of faith and Religion,<note place="margin">A newe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſe.</note> and vvhy? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue particularly cenſured and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:22753:14"/>
them, and defined their poſitions as hereticall. So did the Arrians in like maner inſtance againſt the Counſell of Nyce, for the ſame cauſe, becauſe it defined againſt them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore in this Treatiſe vvee haue excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and thought vpon another courſe,<note place="margin">Only Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> to Vncaſe the Proteſtants, to laye open their contradictions, to alleadge their ovvne authorities and writers; to expreſſe the abſurdities of their inferences and conſequences, to ſee vvhither they vvill runne then.</p>
            <p>No doubt they vvill crye out, The Scriptures, the ſcriptures onely ſhall be our guyde, our Iudge, our gouernour, our vvarrant, in matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie. Although vvee know that ſome contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies cannot be decided by expreſſe ſcripture, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vvritten vvord, but vvee muſt haue our varrant from Tradition and the Church (which vve call the vnvvritten wordes) as for example the true number of the vvritten ſcriptures, are theſe and no more: the Baptiſme of Children, &amp;c. Yet vve accept of this condition of tryall, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the true ſcripture to be the vvord of God, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie it ſelfe, wherein no falſhood can be hidden, the true tuchſtone of trueth, dedicated by the Holie Ghoſt, vvritten by the Prophets, Euangeliſts and Apoſtles of Chriſt: therefore vvith all reuerence vvee reade it; and <hi>S. Charles Boromeus</hi> did ſo reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently eſteeme of the ſacred ſcriptures, that vvhen he did ſeriouſly read them, he did alvvaies read them vpon his knees, and bare-headed: a rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of pietie.</p>
            <p>Let vs vvillingly enter into the liſte of this combate vvith Proteſtants or Puritants? We know vvhat vvill be the ende of this, for demanding of them before hand, vvhether they vvill be tryed by the bare letter of the word, or the true ſence &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word? they wil anſwere by both. If vvee
<pb facs="tcp:22753:15"/>
aske hovv ſhall vvee knovv that vvee haue the true ſence and meaning of the vvord: they vvill an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere, that they vvill make this plaine, by confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of place vvith place, and that the ſpirit vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, doth tell them, this is the Trueth, and true ſence and meaning. If vvee replie, vvee haue the ſpirit as vvell as you, vee conferre place vvith place as vvell as you: vvhere then vvill be the end of this controuerſie? We muſt beleeue them vpon the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of their ſpirit, and the conference of places made by them, or elſe no end; ſo that their priuate ſpirite muſt end it, or no end at all.</p>
            <p>But to make an end at this time, I vvould aduiſe the young ſtudents to take this <hi>notandum</hi> and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat from me; not to be credulous to the allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their doctors and Sages, but to read dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the authentike Authors, leaſt that be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in you. <hi>Si coecus coecum ducat in foeueam cadent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus vviſhing no vvorſe vnto you Right vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Doctors, Maiſters, and vvorthie ſtudents, then to mine ovvne ſoule, that is vnited in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, peace in conſcience and ſaluation in IESVS CHSIST, I take my leaue, from my chamber at <hi>Doway</hi> 17. of Ianuarie. M.DC.XXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22753:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> VNCASING OF HERESIE. <hi>OR</hi> THE ANATOMIE OF PROTESTANCIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I. That <hi>Luther, Caluin, Zuinglius,</hi> and all other prime-doctors of Proteſtaniſme, were (by their owne confeſsions baptized and brought vp, in the now Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and onely by their apoſtacies, gaue life and being to Proteſtancie. And that Proteſtant Martyrologies, Callendars, and genealogicall tables, conſiſt either of confeſſed Papiſts, knowne ſchiſmatikes, deteſted heretikes, wicked Atheiſts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Magitians, ſacrilegious thieues, or notorious traitours.</head>
               <p>SCIAT <hi>lector me fuiſſe aliquando mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum, &amp; papiſtam inſaniſsimum, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luther praefat. tom. 1. &amp; tom. 3. in pſal. 45.</note> Let the Reader know, that I was ſometimes a Monke, and a moſt madde Papiſt, when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22753:16"/>
I began this buſines,<note place="margin">&amp; tom. 5. in 1. Galath. fol. 291.</note> ſo drunke and drowned in Popish opinions, that I was moſt ready to kill and ſlay all ſuch as any way with-ſtood the ſame, &amp;c. I purely adored the Pope. So <hi>Luther.</hi> And againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Idem in 1. Gal. pag. 25. tom. 4. Ien. Lat. &amp; p. 26. &amp; tom. 6. in cap. 11. Gene. fol. 129. &amp; tom. 4. in cap. 43. Iſay. fol. 179.</note>I certainely, if any other before the light of the Goſpel, had a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, and was very zealous for Popish lawes, and the Traditions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and in good earneſt I vrged and defended them as neceſſarie to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Laſtly, I endeuored with all diligence to performe them, macerating my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with faſting, watching, prayer, and other exerciſes. I while I was a Monke daily crucified Chriſt, and with my falſe truſt, continually blaſphemed him. We haue bene holie Apoſtates, for wee haue fallen from Antichriſt, and the Church of Sathan, &amp;c. There was none of vs but were bloody fellowes: if not in act, yet in heart, we haue blaſphemed God, Chriſt, the Sacraments, the goſpel, faith, all good men, the true worship of God, and we haue taught quite contrarie. We are iudged heretikes by the Pope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue diuided our ſelues from that Church, in which we were borne and bredde. Hetherto <hi>Luther,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe, and the reſt of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22753:16"/>
                  <hi>Danaeus</hi> in like maner doth boaſt,<note place="margin">Danaeus reſp. ad Leonic. edita. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1518. Zwingl. tom. 1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tres. f. 341 Melanct. tom. 1. in cap. 7. Mat. f. 407 &amp; tom. 2. ad Swenk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feld. f. 200 Oecola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p. reſp. ad Perkeym. p. 108 &amp; apud Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpin. part. 2. fol. 35. Brentius in apol. pro conf. Wittenb. c. de eccl. fol. 873. Caluin in confeſſ. fidei. fol. 111.</note> that his friend <hi>Oſiander,</hi> was a moſt <hi>wicked Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcan</hi> Monke. Neither doe <hi>Zwinglius, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton,</hi> or <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> ſeeme to take ſmal pride in ſuch like confeſsions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pelican</hi> was a Minor, and <hi>Bucer</hi> a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican (ſaith <hi>Hoſpinian</hi>) yea, we were all of vs (ſaith <hi>Brentius</hi>) ſeduced fooles, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and ſeruants of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>We do not denie (ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi>) but that we were once of that number<note n="(e)" place="margin">Idem l. 4. confeſ. c. 15. n. 16.</note> bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Papall kingdome<note n="(f)" place="margin">ibid. c. 6 n. 1. See alſo the Bishop of Elie reſp. ad Bellar. c. 1. Bulling. tom. 1. decad. 5. ſer. 2. fol. 285. Muſcul. in locis communibus, ca. de ſchiſmate. Mourney l de eccleſia. cap. 11. Perkins in cap. 4. ad Galath. v. 26. Hooker lib. 4. of Eccleſiaſt. pollic. p. 181. Powel l. 1. de antichr. c. 21. Morton. 2. part of his apol. l. 2. c. 10. Luther tom 7. in ſer. quid ſit hom. Chriſt. praeſtand. fol. 274.</note> but we haue now departed from the Roman Church. So <hi>Caluin.</hi> And the ſame is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by <hi>Bullinger, Muſculus, Pleſsie Mourney, Perkins, Hooker, Powel, Morto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> &amp; the reſt.</p>
               <p>I was the firſt to whom God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to reueile thoſe doctrines, which are now preached,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in 1. Cor. 1.15. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>34. &amp; col. menſ. fol. 488.</note> this praiſe they cannot take from vs; that we were the firſt that brought light to the world. Without our helpe, no man had euer learned one word of the Goſpel. So the fore mentioned <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22753:17"/>
                  <note place="margin">Wotton in exam. Iuris cler. Rom. pag. 392.</note>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> might well ſaye, that he was the firſt, who in theſe times preached Chriſt, eſpecially in the principal points of the Goſpell, which is Iuſtification by faith in Chriſt, and in this reſpect, it is an honour to <hi>Luther,</hi> that he was a ſonne without a father, and a ſcholler without a maiſter. So <hi>Wotton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Morgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. tract. de eccleſ p. 145.</note>It is ridiculous (ſaith <hi>Morgenſterne</hi>) to thinke that anie before <hi>Luthers</hi> time held the true doctrine, or that <hi>Luther</hi> receiued his doctrine from others, and not others from him, ſince all Chriſtians know, that all Churches before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, were ouerwhelmed with more then Egyptian darkneſſe, and that <hi>Luther</hi> was ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue to reſtore the true light.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Luther</hi> had had any predeceſſors im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bued with the true faith and religion, there had bene no neede of a Lutheran reformation,<note place="margin">Milius in explicat. Auguſt. Confeſ. art. 7. See the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie. tract. 2. c. 2. ſect. 11.</note> &amp;c. So <hi>Milius.</hi> And the like is affirmed by <hi>Hoſpinia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. Coelius Secundus Curio, Bucanus, Fulke, Downham,</hi> and infinite other Proteſtants, as shall be shewed in the next chapter.</p>
               <p>And although other Proteſtants blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing at this ingenious confeſsion of their fellowes (which they finde apt to conuince them of hereſie, becauſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſo deepely of noueltie) haue taken no ſmall paines, to make their pedegree
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22753:17"/>
ſmell of ſome more antiquitie; and haue for this purpoſe compoſed very volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and large Catologues, in which they haue moſt shamfully thruſt in, not only all ſuch noble profeſſors of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, who any way reprehended the vices of thoſe times they liued in, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſlike of the religion; but alſo omitted no ſorte of ſchiſmatikes, lewde heretikes, atheiſts, ſorcerers, witches, thieues, or traitors, who either conſent with them, or diſſent from vs in any one point, yet ſuch is their hard happe, that among all this GALLAMAFRY, there is not one true Proteſtant to be found, as by examining their Catalogues, and bed-roles of witneſſes, I will here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate vnto you.</p>
               <p>Firſt then,<note place="margin">Entituled a looking glaſſe for Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> to beginne with the ſixt age (leauing * the examination of the firſt fiue to an other Treatiſe) from the yeare 600. to 700.<note n="(b)" place="margin">S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie the great, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the year 590, is here rai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed by M. White, after the yeare 600. to plead for Proteſtancie. See White in his way to the Church. §. 50. pag. 387. Humf. in Ieſuitiſmo part. 2. rat. 5. p. 5. &amp; 627. Bale actis Ro. Pont. an. 1558. p. 44. 45. 46. &amp;c. Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 6. cap. 10. col. 743. 382.</note> they produce S. GREGORIE the great: who beſides that he was Pope of Rome, was ſo farre from being a Proteſtant, that Doctor <hi>Humfries, Bale, Oſiander,</hi> and the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riators confeſſe of him, that he helde Purgatorie, relikes, tranſubſtantiation,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22753:18"/>
prayer for the dead, indulgences, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of Images, Maſſe, Holie oyle, Monkerie, Holy-water, Auricular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, &amp; al other our doctrins, yea, <hi>quod ſibi vendicauerit &amp; exercuerit primatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuper omnes Eccleſias.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Centur. Magdeb. cent. 6. c. 10. col. 425. &amp;c. And the like is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Fulke in confut. of Purgato. p. 310. &amp; Martir. in cap 8. Iud. &amp; Carion in Croni. l. 4. p. 368. and Oſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 6. p. 242.</note> That he challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vnto himſelf, &amp; exerciſed the <hi>Supremecie</hi> ouer all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: which is the only poynt for which M. <hi>White</hi> maketh him one of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtanticall progenitors.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they produce the ſixt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councell, in which the Fathers were ſo farre from being Proteſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally affected, that they decreed as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.<note n="d" place="margin">Conci. 6. general. can. 4.</note> That what Cleargie perſon ſoeuer did lie with a Nunne (whom they ſtyle Chriſts ſpouſe) should be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.<note n="e" place="margin">can. 44.</note> That if any Monke married a wife, he should be punished as a forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator.<note n="f" place="margin">can. 48.</note> That none should be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated a Bishop, till his wife (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) being ſeuered from him, were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in a Monaſterie, farre from his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.<note n="g" place="margin">can. 73.</note> That the Croſſe ought to be worshipped.<note n="h" place="margin">can. 56.</note> That in Lent (no not on Sundaies) men might not eate Egges, Cheeſe, Butter, nor Flesh.<note n="i" place="margin">can. 6.</note> That no Subdeacon, Deacon, or Prieſt, might marrie after Orders taken, &amp;c. Yea, in that verie Canon, for which they are made Proteſtants, it is only ſaid, that it may be lawfull for ſome ſelected mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22753:18"/>
perſons, to be admitted to the order of Prieſt-hood; which was ſometimes permitted to the Greeke Church, and alſo in the beginning of the Goſpell, when Prieſts were more ſcant, among the Lattins: you shall heare what Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius will ſay touching this poynt.</p>
               <p>The Holy Preaching of God recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not after Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epiph. hae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſ. 59. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra Catha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ros. See S. Hierom co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant. c. 1. &amp; cap. 8. &amp; S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine de a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dulter. coniug. l. 2. c. 20. &amp; Euſeb. li. 1. Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. demonſt. c. 9. &amp; alij paſsim.</note> them that marrie againe after their wiues departure, by reaſon of their great dignitie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Prieſthood, and this the holy Church of God obſerueth with all ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; yea she doth not receaue the once married perſon, that yet vſeth his wife, &amp;c. eſpecially where the holy Canons be ſincerely kept. But thou wilt ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that in certaine places, Deacons, Subdeacons, and Prieſts, doe yet beget children; but that is not done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Order and Rule, but according to mans minde, which by time ſlaketh, and for the great multitude, when there were not found ſufficient for the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie. This and much more S. <hi>Epiphanius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly they alleadge in this age, the third<note n="*" place="margin">Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carence 3. extat tom. 3. concil. ſee in that council. c. 3. 4. &amp;</note> Portugal Councel, which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it commendeth vnto vs hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Veſſels, forbiddeth all Cleargie men priuatly to keepe companie with any woman, ſaue their mother. And decreeth, what ornaments are to be vſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22753:19"/>
both in priuate and publike Maſſes) hath nothing at all againſt vs, no not in the place by them alleadged; for it only ſaith, that in the<note n="h" place="margin">Maiſt. White to make this councell ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, vſeth as blacke dealing as may be. For where the Councel ſpeaketh of the Sacrifice, he applieth it to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſaying, that the Councel appointed the Cuppe to be adminiſtred to the people in the Sacrament. And to this he taileth an other egregious Lie, in intimating, that our vſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we gaue the Sacrament in one kinde only) was to dippe the bread in wine.</note> ſacrifice of the Maſſe, wine mingled with water, and bread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, should be vſed, and not wine only, nor bread dipped in water, which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, our Church well alloweth of, and conſtantly teacheth and practiſeth.</p>
               <p>IN the ſeuenth age, viz. from 700 to 800. they<note n="*" place="margin">White in his way to the Church §. 50. pag. 388.</note> name <hi>Clement, Scotus,</hi> and <hi>Adelbertus.</hi> Both which (beſides that they helde more points with vs, then with them, and conſequently, could not be true Proteſtants) were confeſſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.<note n="b" place="margin">See Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius an. 745 n. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> helde that a Chriſtian might lawfully marrie, with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife; th at when Chriſt deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell,<note n="c" place="margin">See the ſame Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cod. n. 21 24. &amp; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene verbo I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claſtae.</note> he deliuered thence, not only the faithful, but alſo the Infidels, and the worshippers of Idols, and the like. And as for <hi>Adelbertus,</hi> he gaue out that he had certaine relickes, by which he could obtaine, what he liſted of God; was well content, that Churches and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22753:19"/>
Chappels, should be dedicated to his proper worshippe and honour; gaue his owne haire, &amp; parings of his nailes, to be worshipped of his followers, as ſacred relikes; bragged that he knew the ſecrets of mens hearts, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly,<note place="margin">White vt ſupra. ſee Baron. an. 704. n. 17. &amp; Dama. vt ſupra. See Conc. Conſtant. pol. ſub Iſaurico &amp; Copron. c 15. 17. 18 &amp; Magd. cent. 8. c. 9. &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. tricae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. 2. act. 6.</note> gaue them abſolution without hearing their confeſsions, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They further produce the two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitan councels, vnder <hi>Leo Iſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> and <hi>Copronimus,</hi> which councels, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that they were condemned and reiected by diuers following Councels, as ſchiſmaticall and hereticall) decreed as followeth; that whoſoeuer denyed that the B. Virgin, was to be inuocated; or that the Saints were not to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped; or that eternal life was not giuen for the merit of good workes, &amp;c. should be ANATHEMA, or accurſed of God: either of which doctrines, will conuince, that neither of theſe councels did much fauour Proteſtancie.</p>
               <p>They further<note n="*" place="margin">White vt ſupra.</note> produce in this age, (as an other Proteſtant witneſſe) the Councel of Frankford<note n="b" place="margin">What is to be thought of the Councel, ſee the notes on the third tome of councels an. 1618. p. p. 126. See alſo Bellarm. tom. 7. operu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> f. 566. lib. cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> titul. confutat. libelli de cultu Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. qui falſo, &amp;c.</note> as alſo two bookes one pretended, to be compoſed by CHARLES the great, and the other by LODOWICK his ſonne, containing the Acts of that Counſell.</p>
               <p>To which wee anſwere, that if the Councel of Frankford, had bene ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22753:20"/>
Councell, and thoſe two books (bearing the names of CHARLES and LODOWIKE) there true borne, and not hereticall Imps, <hi>(c)</hi> iniuriouſly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened on thoſe two worthy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Princes; yet ſeeing together with the reiection of Images, they teach That the Pope <hi>is ſupreame head,</hi> in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies belonging to faith, That the Pope hath his ſupremacie immediatly from God, That prayer is to be made for the dead, That Saints are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocated, That relickes are to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped, That in the Euchariſt, Chriſts bodie is truly preſent, and there to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored, &amp;c.<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Charles the great, did not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like edicts that the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, rits, and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Church of Rome, and other decrees, pleaſurs, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppe, should be obſerued through all his Empire; but he himſelfe alſo did compell the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this, by impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; ſundrie punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſaith Hoſpinian in epiſt. dedic. hiſt. vide etiam Oſiand. in epit. ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 8. p. 101. and Cooper in Cronico. f. 173. and Criſpin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l. de ſtat. Eccleſiae pag. 221. 226.</note> The Proteſtants haue ſmall reaſon to claime this Councel, as a good witneſſe of their religion.</p>
               <p>Beſides the<note n="d" place="margin">Cent. 8. c. 9. col. 570. ex Paulo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milio. l. 2. hiſt. Fran.</note> Magdeburgians, out of <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> confeſſe that CHARLES the great, ſent twelue of his moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prelates, to the Roman Councell, vnder Pope ADRIAN, in which the worship of Images was eſtablished. He wrot alſo the Epitaph of Pope ADRIAN as followeth:
<q>
                     <l>Hic Pater Eccleſiae, Romae decus, inclytus author</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ADRIANVS</hi> requiem Papa beatus habet.</l>
                     <l>Vir cui vita decus; pietas, lex; gloria, Chriſtus;</l>
                     <l>Paſtor Apoſtolicus, promptus ad omne bonum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
Which euidently shew, that CHARLES the great, held not Image-worshippers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22753:20"/>
Idolaters, but rather the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as may appeare by what hath bene alreadie ſaid, as alſo by the teſtimonie of <hi>Ionas Aurelienſis,</hi> who as an eye-witneſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that in the raigne of CHARLES the great, <hi>Claudius</hi> bishop of Towers (the chiefe oppugner of Images) durſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where shew his head. And as for LODO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VICK his ſonne, ſurnamed the <hi>godly, Carion</hi> writeth as followeth. LODO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VICKE the only ſuruiuing ſonne of CHARLES, was for his religious ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, ſurnamed the <hi>godly,</hi> for he increaſed the feaſts, and the Idolatrous worshipping of Saints, and the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious obſeruation of Monaſtical orders, &amp;c. So farre was LODOVICK from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proteſtantically minded.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Ionas Aureli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſ. l. 1. de cultu I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mag Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rionin cronico l. 4. p. 96. edit. 2. volum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</note> they produce venerable <hi>Bede, Iohn Damaſcene,</hi> and diuers other knowne Catholikes. For as touching S. <hi>Bede, Oſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> acknowledgeth, that he held in all poynts with the Pope, &amp; as for <hi>(c)</hi> S. <hi>Iohn Damaſcene,</hi> he was one of the principall reſiſters of <hi>Leo Iſauricus,</hi> in his hereſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the worship of Images, neither did he differ from vs, in any poynt of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22753:21"/>
doctrine for ought I can finde.<note n="*" place="margin">Illiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogo teſtium veritatis. Oſiander in epit. cent. 8. l. 2. c. 3. c. ſee Baron. an. 727. 7 n. 18. 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>IN the eight age<note n="l" place="margin">White vt ſupra pag. 388.</note> they name <hi>Iohn Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Bertram,</hi> &amp; <hi>Claudius</hi> bishop of Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the laſt of which three, holding that baptiſme was not good, which was not adminiſtred with the ſigne of the Croſſe, and profeſsing Neſtoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme: the Proteſtants muſt needes confeſſe him to be an heretike. And as touching <hi>Scotus</hi> and<note n="(n)" place="margin">Beſides that, the Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (cent. 9. c. 4. col 212.) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that in Bertrams booke, tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is taught: tis thought that Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made not that booke, becauſe Pantalion, who was diligent in reckoning vp all Bertrams bookes, maketh no mention of this booke, for which he is only made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. See Pantalion in Cronologia. an. 65.</note> 
                  <hi>Bertram</hi> (if thoſe bookes in which the Real preſence ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be impugned, were made by them) being in all other points, beſides that of the Real preſence, knowne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; what reaſon the Proteſtants haue to produce them, as their progenitors, let the readet iudge.</p>
               <p>They likewiſe name in this age <hi>Lotha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">White vt ſupra.</note> who (ſaith <hi>White</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Pope to the obedience of the Empyre, ſending for that cauſe, three Archbishops, twentie Bishops, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers noble men to Rome, who diſputed againſt him, and confuted him.</p>
               <p>Which to be one of the blackeſt and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22753:21"/>
moſt impudent lyes, that euer was coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the very author by him cited, will abundantly witneſſe; for he plainly ſaith, that<note n="*" place="margin">Diuina gratia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirante, nec ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones ipſius al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificis, nec pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiam ſuperare valueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. tantaque ei ſuperna aderat virtus, vt nullo ſermone eum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludere &amp; conſtringere potuerunt, &amp;c. See Anaſtaſius (cited by White) in vitis Pontificum, in Sergio. 2. an. 162.</note> Gods grace ſo inſpired the Pope, that thoſe (Lotharian) Bishops were not able to ouercome, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent him by their ſpeeches, but being themſelues ouercome and confounded, with shame, were forced to leaue him, and goe their wayes.</p>
               <p>They further alleadge in this age<note n="b" place="margin">The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael, chiefely shewed himſelfe to be a Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a vowed Nunne, in impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Nicene Councel, &amp; in banishing good Catholikes.</note> 
                  <hi>Michael</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Photius</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke of Conſtantinople, two worthy Progenitors of Proteſtaniſme. The firſt of them (according to all<note n="(c)" place="margin">See Zonaras and Cedri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus apud Bellarm. tom 7. de cultu Imagin. ca. 6.</note> Greeke au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors) being a moſt wicked man, farre more addicted to Iudaiſme, then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie; holding fornication to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and denying the reſurrection, &amp;c. And the ſecond, maintaining among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereſies, that the Holy Ghoſt, did not proceede from the Father, and the Sonne, but from the Father only; that neither the good should enioy happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor the ill receaue punishment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of Iudgement, that to hurt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22753:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22753:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22753:23"/>
&amp; circumuent his enimie,<note n="d" place="margin">See Gualter in Crono graph. ſaec. 8. in collat. c. 4.</note> a man might lye, and for-ſweare him ſelfe; that it was in each mans power when he liſted to diſſolue Matrimonie; that Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes might not marrie againe; that ſimple fornication and vſurie were no ſinnes; that a man was not bound to make reſtitution of ſtolne goods; that men were to abſtaine from blood, and all meates prohibited in the Old law; that the Euchariſt was to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to children, immediatly after bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the like.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they<note n="g" place="margin">Powel in praefat. l. de an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſto.</note> produce as a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant witneſſe of this age, <hi>Alphred</hi> king of the weſt Saxons, &amp; ſome others whom <note n="h" place="margin">See Stow in his Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle edi. an. 1614. pag. 80.</note> all the world knowes, to haue bene in all poynts true Roman Catholikes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">White as aboue § 50. pag. 389.</note>IN the ninth age (quoth M. <hi>White) Otho</hi> the great, depoſed IOHN the Pope, &amp; aſſumed into his hands the nominating and making of Popes euer after. Which was a manifeſt reſiſtance made againſt the grouth of the ſupremacie. So <hi>White.</hi> and citeth for his Author, <hi>Sigonius.</hi> In which,<note place="margin">Sigonius regni Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lici. l. 7. an. 963.</note> after ſearch made, finding the contrarie, I could not but ſtand amazed at the frontleſſe impudence of this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, &amp; his Cymiſts. For both <hi>Sigonius</hi> &amp; <hi>Luitprandus</hi> declare, that <hi>Otho</hi> went to Rome, with an intent to aid Pope IOHN againſt <hi>Berengarius</hi> and <hi>Albertus.</hi> And after
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22753:23"/>
comming thither, though he was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Bishops, of this Popes ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, yet he wrote vnto him a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Luitpran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dus l. 6. c. 6. &amp; 7.</note> in which he ſtiled him, <hi>The chiefe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, and vniuerſall Pope;</hi> called the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, Bishops, and Prieſts, his ſonnes, &amp; him ſelfe his Protectour, earneſtly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his FATHERHOOD, to make his appearance and anſwere before the Councel of Bishops (for that purpoſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled) to ſuch crimes, as were obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt him. And after, when he appeared not, and the Bishops were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to haue him depoſed, he only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared (as <hi>Sigonius</hi> writeth) <hi>Quando ergo haec praeſtare ſtatuitis, &amp;c.</hi> Since then you are determined to depoſe him, chooſe yee another in his roome,<note place="margin">Illiricus ex Luit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prando. cent. 10. c. 9. col. 433. &amp; ſequent.</note> who may be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of this ſeate, &amp;c. not daring (as <hi>Illiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> confeſſeth out of <hi>Luitprandus</hi>) to make him ſelfe iudge of him, that was his Iudge. So farre was this good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, from preſuming on his owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, in the depoſition of Popes, or arrogating vnto himſelfe the making of Popes, as this lying heretical Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter affirmeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnulphus</hi> a learned Catholike Bishop, is alſo<note n="*" place="margin">White as aboue. pag. 23.</note> produced for a Proteſtant wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this age: but the only reaſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged (which is, that he held the Pope to be Antichriſt) proouing to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22753:24"/>
be a<note n="b" place="margin">See Baron. an. 992. per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſlanderous lie; the Proteſtants cauſe, is but little aduantaged by this witneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Illiricus in cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium. &amp; White as aboue.</note>IN the tenth age, they name <hi>Glaber, Rodolphus, Leuthericus, Anſelmus, Lanfranke</hi> and others, who are all well knowne Roman Catholikes, and notable op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of Proteſtancie.</p>
               <p>They name likewiſe<note n="c" place="margin">White as aboue.</note> 
                  <hi>Berengarius,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">See Gualter in cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia. ſaec. 1000. in coll. c. 1.</note> who yet abiured as hereticall, that very poynt, for which only he is made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and dyed reconciled to the Church of Rome.</p>
               <p>They<note n="e" place="margin">White as aboue. Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſtadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis in epiſt. ad Wolfan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat apud Dodechi num in additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianum Scotum. an. 1090.</note> name alſo <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, Emperour of Germanie, &amp; other of his Bishops &amp; nobles. The worth of which witneſſe, you shall heare from the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtographers of that time. <hi>Omnis qui digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates ſpirituales vendit, haereticus eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Euerie one that ſelleth ſpiritual dignities, is an heretike; but <hi>Henrie</hi> whom they call king, doth ſell Bishoprikes, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botships; for he hath ſold for money, the Bishoprikes of Conſtance, Bam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg and Mintz, the Bishoprikes of Reipurth, Ausburg, and Strasburge for a ſword; the Abbotship of Fulden for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultrie; the bishoprike of Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience for Sodomie, &amp;c. So <hi>Stephanus Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſtadienſis</hi> while this <hi>Henry</hi> was yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
               <p>The Catholike men who liued in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22753:24"/>
that time (ſaith <hi>Maerianus</hi>) hearing and ſeeing theſe abhominations,<note place="margin">Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, in Cron. an. 1075.</note> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of wickednes of <hi>Henry,</hi> directed Meſſengers with letters to ALEXAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER Bishop of the Sea Poſtolike, in which they declared theſe, and manie other things which were done &amp; ſaid, by the mad Simoniacal heretikes, vnder King <hi>Henry</hi> their Author and patron.</p>
               <p>If you deſire to know (ſaith <hi>Krantzius</hi>) the praiſes of <hi>Henry;</hi> he was noble,<note place="margin">Krantzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us l. 5. Saxon. c. 24.</note> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſtrong, tall, and of a Kingly Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; but on the other ſide, the heynous offences which he committed, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible to be ſpoken, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auentine</hi> alſo ſaith,<note place="margin">Auentine l. 5. anal. Boron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. pag. 563.</note> that his very freinds cannot deny, but that <hi>Henry</hi> was infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for rauishments, adultries, &amp;c. He was held by all Catholikes (ſaith <hi>Vſpergenſis</hi>) for an arch-pirate, an apoſtata,<note place="margin">Vſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis in crônic. an. 1068. Caluin l. 4. inſt. c. 11. n. 3. ſee Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine l. 1. de tranſlat. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perij. c. 9. tom. 7.</note> arch-heretike, and a greater perſecutor of mens ſoules, then of their bodies, &amp;c. So all the writers of that time, to which you may adde the teſtimonie of <hi>Caluin,</hi> who plainly confeſſeth, that this <hi>Henry</hi> was a man, light, rash, and of no iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of wounderful diſſoluteneſſe of life, Who had in his Hall, all the bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rikes of Germany, partly to be ſould, and partly to be expoſed for a pray.</p>
               <p>To this you may<note n="*" place="margin">Note that this Henrie the 3. or as ſome call him the fourth, in the time he ſtroue with the Pope for the inueſtiing of Bishops by Ring and Staffe, was depoſed by his owne ſonne, and impriſoned, whence eſcaping after a ſecond defeat, was brought to ſuch miſerie, that he ſued to be a Sexton in a Church, but not admitted to that office, he fell to begge of Lay men, crying in lamentable maner, <hi>Haue mercie vpon me,</hi> at leaſt you my friendes, for the hand of the Lord hath touched me, and ſo full of miſerie, and repentant ſorrow, he pyned to death, to the great reioycing of al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. See Sigonius. de reg. Italico. l. 9. in Hen. 4.</note> adde, that he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſubmitted him ſelfe to Rome, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22753:25"/>
acknowledged the Popes ſupremacie, as BELLARMINE proueth at large.</p>
               <p>IN the eleuenth age, they name <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, Emperour of that name, who in the beginning of his raigne, inſiſted in the ſteps of his father before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">See Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas Vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis in cron. an. 1110. &amp;</note> but ſeeing (as it is well knowne) he afterward recanted, and was reconciled to the Sea Apoſtolike; he ceaſed to be a Proteſtant witneſſe.</p>
               <p>They produce in like maner, an other of their Granſires in this age;<note place="margin">White as aboue.</note> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Fredertcke,</hi> named <hi>Ahembardus:</hi> but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what grounds thinke you? he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed appeales to Rome, ſay they, which I finde to be true indeed, but yet this will not make him a Proteſtant, vnleſſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancie, proceede only of ſpleene, and the heate of contention. For that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that the Pope was Chriſts true Vicegerent vpon earth, and the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal and higheſt Bishop, as both his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22753:25"/>
wordes and deedes declare ſufficiently.<note place="margin">See Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clerum vol. 2. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat. 93. p. 844. edit. 1614 &amp; p. 856. See alſo Radeniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de rebus Frederick primi. c. 16. 17. &amp; 56. and Krant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zius l. 6. c. 16.</note> For to let paſſe his proſtrating him ſelfe before <hi>Victor</hi> the Antipope, which yet was an euident ſigne, that he had the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall dignitie, in the heigheſt eſteeme) he ſtyled Pope ALEXANDER the 3. (whom he ſo much hated) head of the Catholike Church. And when he was willed to humble him ſelf at this ALEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANDERS feet, he did ſo, pronouncing theſe wordes, <hi>Non tibi, ſed Petro, cuius ſucceſſor es, Pareo:</hi> I doe obeyſance not to thee, but to S. PETER, whoſe ſucceſſor thou art.</p>
               <p>Much more shamfully S. BERNARD is by them produced, as a Proteſtant witnes of this age,<note place="margin">White as before, &amp;c Illiricus.</note> who yet in all points was a Roman Catholike, as al his books doe euidently declare, and ſome Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants proteſt, ſaying<note n="(b)" place="margin">Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. cent. 12. col. 1637.</note> 
                  <hi>He worshipped the God Maozim, to the laſt minute of his life;</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">ibid. col 1638.</note> he was an earneſt propugner of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſeat;<note n="(d)" place="margin">White taker ad Rationet Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niani. rat. 7. p. 105.</note> he was the only godly man your Roman Church had for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares.</p>
               <p>Againe, they alleadge the<note n="(e)" place="margin">White as aboue, Illiricus in Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium. &amp; Beza in vita Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uini, &amp; in Icon. an. 158. v. Wald. Fulke de ſucceſſ. contra. Stap. pag. 332. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hil pag. 57. &amp; Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarius de Eccleſia fratrum ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. p. 7. 9. &amp; 11. See the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie, tract. 2. c. 2. ſect. 3 cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſibus fraterna coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio ad extremu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenda eſt. So Caluin in Epiſt. 201. ad Polonos.</note> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes <hi>(f)</hi> and Albigenſes, as Proteſtant witneſſes of this age, who held indeede manie Proteſtanticall opinions, but with all, * that no obedience was due to any Prelate; that it was lawful for all men although they were forbidden by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22753:26"/>
their ſuperiours) to Preach that Laye perſons, if they were iuſt, might Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate; that no perfect perſon might vſe any manuall labour; that men were to vſe no other forme of prayer, but the <hi>Pater noſter;</hi> that Prieſts and ciuill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, being once guiltie of Mortall ſinne, did immediatly looſe their digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and were not after to be reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; that Eccleſiaſticall perſons might poſſeſſe neither money nor lands; that the Apoſtles Creed was to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that no Iudge had power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne any man to death; that all carnal copulation is lawful, if our luſt prouoke vs thereunto; that Churches enuironed with walls, are to be eſteemed as barnes; that thoſe married folke, who lye toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without a deſire to get children, doe ſinne mortally; that men might lawfully diſſemble their faith; that there were two beginnings, to wit, God and the diuel; that God created mens ſoules, and the diuel their bodies; that mens ſoules paſſed out of one bodie, into an other; that our bodies should neuer riſe againe; that there was neither Hell nor
<note n="(m)" place="margin">* See Gualterus in his Cronographie ſaec. 12. cap. 25. &amp; 16. and Illiricus in Catalogo; and Oſiander cent. 9. 10. 11. &amp; Fox. acts. &amp; Symon voyen. in catalogo doctor. Eccleſ. p. 134.</note>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:22753:26"/>
Purgatorie; that the new teſtament was made by a kinde God, and the old by a ſpiteful God, and therefore the one to be reiected, and the other admitted; that the Author of the old Teſtament, was a lyar and a murtherer; that all the Fathers of the olde Teſtament, were damned; that Iohn Baptiſt, was one of the greater diuels; that Marie Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene was Chriſts concubine, and the ſelfe-ſame woman, which the Goſpel affirmeth to haue bene taken in adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; that there were two Chriſts, one good, who was borne and crucified, and the other bad, who was viſibly borne at Bethelem, and crucified at Ieruſalem; that God had two wiues, <hi>Collant</hi> and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libant,</hi> on whom he begat many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; that good Chriſt neuer eate, nor drunke, nor was euer viſible but in Paules bodie; That to lie with ons mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was no greater ſinne, then with any other woman, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Which horred opinions, howſoeuer <hi>White, Abbots, Illiricus, Beza, Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Foxe,</hi> can diſgeſt, and place theſe miſcreant Albigenſes, and Waldenſes, in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of their moſt noble Proteſtant progenitors,<note place="margin">Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius de fratrum ortho. Eccleſia pag. 273.</note> becauſe in ſome poynts they agree with them; yet ſome other Proteſtants reiect them as heretikes: the Waldenſes (ſaith <hi>Camerarius</hi>) neuer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22753:27"/>
agreede with our Churches,<note place="margin">Iewel in defence of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie. p. 48. Oſiander cent. 13. p. 329. See the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Apologie tract. 2. c. 2.</note> nor wee with theirs. The Albigenſes are none of ours, ſaith Iewel; they were Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, ſaith <hi>Oſiander;</hi> with whom conſent, <hi>Cooper (in dict.)</hi> the Magdeburgians (<hi>cent.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. Marbeke (<hi>in locis communibus.</hi> 22.) and diuers others.</p>
               <p>They place moreouer in this age, in their Catalogue of Proteſtant proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Illiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologo teſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter de Brucis,</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. pag. 142.</note> 
                  <hi>Abaillardus,</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Lib. epiſt. zwing. &amp; Oecola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padij pag. 710. &amp; 716. &amp; centur. 12. col. 848.</note> 
                  <hi>(d) Arnoldus,</hi> and other like, who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in deed, as the Proteſtants now doe; that men had no Free-will; that there is no Reall preſence; that the Maſſe was to be abrogated; that Croſſes were to be broken downe, &amp; the like, yet ſeeing they alſo held; that no Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ought to be builded, and that ſuch as were built, ought to be plucked downe; that almes-deedes and prayers, were not to be regarded; that God was not a ſimple eſſence; that God was not the author of all good; that the Angels created ſome things; that Chriſt tooke not on him humaine flesh to free vs; that Chriſt had in him no feare of God; that God could not haue made things otherwiſe then they are; that all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels temptations came by touching certaine herbes and ſtones; that the bleſſed should neuer ſee God, and the like; the Proteſtants haue no great
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22753:27"/>
reaſon to glorie in them.<note place="margin">Illiricus in Cato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo teſt. Powel in praefat. l. de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto pag. 14. 15. 16. White as before p. 392. and Powel in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat. of Popish reaſons. pag. 53. Naper in Apocal. cap. 20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the twelft age, they name S. <hi>Thomas</hi> of Aquine, <hi>Bonauenture, Durand, Lira, Duns Scotus, Roger Bacon</hi> and others ſo Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely addicted, and ſo diametrically oppoſite to Proteſtancie, that none but impudence it ſelfe, would produce them for Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>They name alſo <hi>Peter Blois,</hi> and <hi>Guliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus de Sancto Amore;</hi> the firſt of which two (beſides theſe two hereticall opinions; that Monkes liuing by almes, could not be ſaued, and that actual pouertie, was not lawfull) was in all points (for ought I finde) a Roman Catholike; and the other, by their owne<note n="*" place="margin">Oſiand. in Epit. cent. 12. pag. 281.</note> confeſsions, only reprehended our maners, and not our doctrine.</p>
               <p>They further<note n="a" place="margin">Whire vt ſupra.</note> name in this age, <hi>Frederike</hi> the ſecond, Emperour of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, and <hi>Almoricus</hi> with others of like ſorte; the firſt of which we eaſily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to haue bene at emnitie with the Pope a long time. But yet, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he after<note n="(b)" place="margin">See Vſperge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis in Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico, &amp; Whimx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telingus in epit. rerum Corman cap. 15.</note> hartely repented the ſame, and humbly craued abſolution at the Popes handes, and was in Religion a Roman Catholike; the Proteſtants do him great wrong, in producing him for one of their progenitors: and as touching <hi>Almoricus,</hi> ſince together with the denyal of the Real preſence, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22753:28"/>
inuocation of Saints;<note place="margin">See Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier in Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph. faec. 1200. in collat. c. 1.</note> he alſo taught theſe following (<hi>viz.</hi> that if Adam had not offended, there should not haue bene anie diſtinction of Sexes, nor anie procreation of Children; that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed should neuer ſee God, but in his Creatures only; that there should be no reſurrection of bodies; that there was neither heauen nor hell, and the like) this will proue but an hereticall witneſſe.<note place="margin">White in his way as before p. 392 &amp; Powel in prefatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne l. de antich. White in his way as aboue pag, 393. Fox actes &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Powel in praefat. l. de anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto.</note>
               </p>
               <p>IN the thirteenth age they name, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farus, Pelagius, S. Katherine</hi> of Sienna, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Wickham, William Occham,</hi> and ſome others: the three firſt of which were in all points for ought I can finde, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Roman Catholikes, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the other did hold erroniouſly in ſome points, yet it is moſt certaine that they were very farre from being in all, Proteſtantically affected.</p>
               <p>They further produce in this age, <hi>Lollard walter,</hi> and <hi>Iohn witclffe,</hi> as two emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent martirs, and moſt renowned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant progenitors; and yet the firſt of theſe was burnt for theſe and ſuch like opinions.<note n="*" place="margin">See Gualtier in Crono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphia. ſaec. 13. c. 7. in col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> That Lucifer and his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotiates, were vniuſtly thruſt out of heauen; that Michael and the other bleſſed Angels, should be damned; that the Virgin MARY remained not a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22753:28"/>
that God wil punish no ſinnes that are committed here on earth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Wickliffe</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">See Stow and Hollin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shead in their Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles. an. 1382. and Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in his 4. cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turie. Matthew Hoe in tract. 1. de diſput. p. 27. Pantaleo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Cronol pag. 119. Vadianus Zwingl. l. 5. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtop. 168.</note> beſides that he dyed of a natural diſeaſe quietly in his bedde) <hi>Matthew Hoe, Pantaleon,</hi> and <hi>Vadianus Zwinglianus,</hi> all famous Proteſtants, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute him for an Heretike, and others for a<note n="(b)" place="margin">See Fox acts &amp; monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; Stow. See alſo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton in diſpute de iure Magiſtrat. &amp; Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 9. 10. 11. 12. art. 15. See alſo Breitly in his Proteſtant Apollogie tract. 2. §. 4. c. 2.</note> Traytour. Neither doe I ſee, how anie Proteſtant can iudge better of him, vnleſſe he happilie allow of theſe following poſitions of his viz. That no Prieſt ought to poſſeſſe any thing as proper; that no Magiſtrate had any authoritie, as long as he was in Mortall ſinne; that no Prelate ought to excommunicate any, vnleſſe he be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that the partie was before excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by God; that the people may at their pleaſure punish their Lords; that Vniuerſities, Colledges, &amp; degrees therein taken, were as commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to the common weale, as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell; that by Gods law, the brother and ſiſter might marrie together; that God muſt obey the diuel; that euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be called God; that all things happened by ineuitable neceſsitie; that to enrich the Cleargie, was againſt the law of Chriſt; that all oathes are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which are vſed to confirme bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines and contracts; that a bishop is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22753:29"/>
not aboue a Prieſt, and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Powel in praefat. lib. de Antichriſto. pag. 28. 29.</note>
                  <hi>Powel</hi> addeth to the former Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Confeſſors of this age, <hi>Nicolas Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Petrus Patishal,</hi> and <hi>Richard White;</hi> but in acknowledging them to haue bene true Witcliffes, we may iuſtly conclud them to haue bene notorious heretikes.</p>
               <p>IN the fourteenth age; they place <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Fox in Acts &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; Powel vt ſupra, and Bale, ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 6. c. 78. and Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let in ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſi. Stow in annal. edit. 1614. fol. 344. ſee alſo Holin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shead an. 1414. See the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Foxes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender in the 3. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion.</note> 
                  <hi>Ashton,</hi> for one of their rubicated or prime Martirs; who yet as STOW witneſſeth, was condemned for rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and treaſon, and buried vnder the Gallowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Browne (a) Richard Silbecke, Iohn Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerly,</hi> and <hi>William Swindersbie,</hi> are placed as fower other Proteſtant Martirs; and yet the firſt three <hi>(b)</hi> were condemned for treaſon and rebellion with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Robert Ashton;</hi> and as for <hi>Swindersbie,</hi> beſides that <hi>Fox</hi> confeſſeth, that he is vncertaine what became of him (only he is ſure that he eſcaped the handes of thoſe that had him in hold, and that he had no harme, during the time of RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD the ſecond, viz. in the yeare 1401. in which yeare. he is made a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir) The opinions for which he was queſtioned were theſe: That no man can impriſon an other for debt; that euerie Prieſt taking an yearly penſion, committeth ſymmonie; that Prieſts Conſecrating in Mortal ſinne, commit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22753:29"/>
Idolatrie, &amp;c. which euidently shew,<note place="margin">White as aboue, Powel in praefat. lib. de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſto. p. 33. 34. Fox acts &amp; mon. Stow and Hollinsh. an. 5. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r. 5. Walſing, an. 1417. p. 448.</note> that <hi>Swinderbie</hi> was an heretike.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thorpe, Iohn Purney,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Old Caſtle,</hi> are three other Proteſtant Martirs of this age; and yet the two firſt are confeſſed by <hi>Powell,</hi> to haue bene <hi>Weckliffites,</hi> and conſequently heretikes, as before shewed; and as concerning <hi>Old-caſtle,</hi> (whom <hi>Fox</hi> ſtileth Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir) <hi>Stow</hi> and <hi>Hollanshead</hi> confeſſe, that he was conuicted and condemned for treaſon and open rebellion, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly executed. an. 134. 17. December 14. an. 3. Henrici. 5. And as touching his doctrine,<note place="margin">Fox &amp; Powel vt ſupra. This <hi>Only</hi> or <hi>Bulling<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brooke,</hi> is named by Fox in his firſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knight and in the ſecond Prieſt.</note> he was ſo madly minded (ſaith <hi>Walſingham</hi>) that he thought hee should riſe againe the third day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roger Only,</hi> alias <hi>Bullingbrooke, Elenor Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Rainold Peacocke,</hi> are produced as three other Proteſtant progenitors in this age; the two laſt for confeſſors, and the firſt for a rubricated Martir, who yet was executed for no other cauſe, but for that he had ſought the kings death, by art Magicke; and as for <hi>Elenor</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eleonor Colham, is ſtyled by Powel <hi>pijſſima duciſſa.</hi> a moſt pious Dutches.</note> 
                  <hi>Cobham,</hi> she was conuicted to haue bene a principal agent in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie with <hi>Only;</hi> and after conuiction was committed to the ward of Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Standly,</hi> where she remained during her life, in the Caſtle of Cheſter, whoſe pride, falshood, couetous, and lecherie
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22753:30"/>
(ſaith <hi>Stow</hi>) were cauſe of her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion.<note place="margin">Stow an. 20 Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly concerning <hi>Peacoke,</hi> the ſame <note n="(a)" place="margin">Stow an 36. Henr. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Stow</hi> will tell you, that he was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for denying certaine Articles of the Apoſtles Creede, which he after at Paules Croſſe, abiured, reuoked, and renounced; requiring all men, in the name of God, and as they tendred their ſaluations, not to giue credite to his pernicious doctrines, errours, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies (which by preſuming on his owne naturall witt, and preferring his owne iudgement in reading the Scripturs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement of his Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church, hee had conceiued and written) but that all ſuch bookes and writings, should be deliuered to the Archbishop, or his Commiſſaries, to be burnt, as well deſeruing the ſame.</p>
               <p>They further name in this age, <hi>Iohn Hus, Richard Turmin,</hi> and <hi>Machiauil.</hi> The firſt of which three,<note place="margin">White vt ſupra. Fox in Acts and Monum. Illiricus l. 19. teſt. p. 1916. an. 1608. edit. <hi>Matthew Hoe</hi> in tract. duobus. tract. 1. de diſp. pag. 27.</note> maintained all <hi>Wickliffes</hi> opinions, and is iuſtly ranked by <hi>Mathew Hoe,</hi> in the Catalogue of Heretikes, and his opinions, ſtyled MONSTROVS MONSTERS. Secondly concerning <note n="*" place="margin">Of this Proteſtant Martir, <hi>Fox</hi> confeſſeth, that he not onely eſcaped burning, but had neuer ſo much as any ſentence of death pronounced againſt him.</note> 
                  <hi>Turmin,</hi> he was in the conſpiracie with Sir <hi>Iohn Oldcaſtle.</hi> &amp; as touching <hi>Machiauill</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:22753:30"/>
al men know that he was a true Atheiſt.</p>
               <p>And thus hauing exactly viewed the Catalogue of the Proteſtants pretended <hi>Ancaſtrie,</hi> and found them to be no other, then either confeſſed Papiſts, knowne Schiſmatikes, deteſted Heretikes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſts, Magitians, Thieues and Traitors, I will conclude this chapter with this dilemma.</p>
               <p>Either <hi>Luther</hi> and his cope-mates, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Zwinglius</hi> and the reſt, had knowne, viſible, and eminent predeceſſors, who profeſſed the doctrines they now teach in all former ages, or they had no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors. If they had no predeceſſors (as <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe, and moſt learned Proteſtants confeſſed in the beginning of this chapter) it muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low (to ſay nothing of the calling of Proteſtant Miniſters, which muſt needs befro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diuel, becauſe it was neither<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie that is, from men of lawfull authority it could not be, for neither at that time, nor long before, there had bene any knowne or viſible Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Miniſter or Magiſtrate, as they themſelues confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the beginning of this chapter, and as for Papiſts, who then were onely viſible, as moſt Proteſtants acknowledge, they neuer ſent them to Preach thoſe new doctrines, neither will any Proteſtant indure to deriue any ſmall authoritie from them. We (ſaith <hi>Fulke</hi> in his Retentiue (p. 67.) and in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the falſe Catholike (pag. 50.) deteſt, abhorre, abiure, and ſpit at your Antichriſtian and filthie Orders; you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, if you thinke that we hold our offices of Deacons, Prieſts, or Bishops, for any other then meerely laicall; The Papiſticall ordinations ſaith <hi>Powell</hi> (in his conſideration of the Papiſts reaſons pag. 71. &amp; 70.) are meere Prophanations, neither is there in the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie any Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling So he, and the like is affirmed by Beza, <hi>apud Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauium in defenſ. tract. p. es</hi> Bucanus <hi>in locis commun. loco.</hi> 42.</note>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:22753:31"/>
ordinarie, nor<note n="(b)" place="margin">Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their own confeſſions, and this for two reaſons: Firſt, becauſe extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie calling hath not bene in vſe ſince the Apoſtles time, nor muſt euer be expected, till the end of the world, as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in tom. 5. Witt. in cap. 1. ad Galath. p. 376. <hi>Muſculus</hi> (in locis commun. p. 304.) <hi>Lobecke</hi> (in diſput. Theolog. p. 358.) and <hi>Sarania</hi> (in defenſ. tract. contra defenſ. <hi>Beza.</hi> p. 73. &amp; 35. 36. 37.) contend. Secondly becauſe extraodinarie vocation was euer accompanied with miracles, as the ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> (in locis communib. claſſe 4. cap. 20. &amp; Epiſt. ad Senatum Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſ. apud Sleydan. l. 3. an. 25.) Piſcator (in volum. Theolog. Theſ. 1. loco. 23.) Polanus (lib. 1. part Theolog. pag. 358.) and other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme; Now that no Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant euer wrought any mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in it ſelfe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will any of them chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lenge ſo much; we neither work mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther doe we hold, that the doctrine of truth is to be confirmed by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles. So <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> in examin. <hi>Keliſ.</hi> p. 8. and the like is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Fulke</hi> (contra Remiſt. teſt. fol. 478.) <hi>Eraſmus</hi> (apud <hi>Fitz Siomn</hi> in Britanniar. Miniſtr) and others.</note> extraordinary, that is neither immediatly from God, nor me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatly by men of lawful authoritie: If (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay) they had no predeceſſors, it muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> needes follow, that the doctrines, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which the Proteſtant Church is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, were heretical and Antichriſtian, and they them ſelues Nouellizers, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and Sathanicall Miniſters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the true<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay. cap. 2. verſ. 2. &amp; cap. 60. 61. &amp; 62. per totum. And Pſal. 91. v. 4. Epheſians 4.11.12. Mat. 18. v. 15. &amp; cap. 24. v. 25.26. And Daniel 2. v. 44. And Oſee cap. 2. v. 19 Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius in Orat. de Chriſti. Chryſoſtom. ſerm. 26. de Pentecoſt. Auguſtine epiſt. 170. &amp; in Concione. 2. in pſal. 5. See alſo the Proteſtants Apologie, tract. 2. c. 2. ſect. 8.</note> Church of Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to expreſſe Scriptures, conſent of Catholike writers, and confeſsions of beſt learned Proteſtants, muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies as a Cittie ſeated on the toppe of a hill, knowne, eminent and gloriouſly viſible, whoſe Sunne muſt neuer ſet, nor her Moone lie hid, whoſe gates muſt euer ſtand open and the like, hauing in her Paſtors and Miniſters Preaching the word, and adminiſtring the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and reſiſting all nouelties and falſe doctrines.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:22753:31"/>But if (as <hi>Illiricus, Fulke,</hi> and D. <hi>White</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end) <hi>Luther</hi> and his cymiſts, had any Predeceſſors, the chiefe of which were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe formerly mentioned, to witte, Schiſmatikes, Heretikes, Athieſts, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitians, Thieues, and Traitours (for as touching Papiſts, they vtterly diſclayme them, neither will any Proteſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to deriue his Pedegree or Miſsion from them of all others) it cannot be denyed, but that Proteſtants are infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and deteſtable heretikes, in being deſcended, from ſuch accurſed, infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, diuellish, and deteſtable progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:22753:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER II.</hi> That all the chiefe doctrines and principles of Proteſtancie, are old condemned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; and that the moſt damned hereſies that euer were hatched in any age, haue bene cherished, foſtered, and defended by the chiefe Doctors in the Proteſtant Church.</head>
               <p>THat all the doctrines which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants at this day ſo eagerly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine againſt Roman Catholikes, are old condemned Hereſies; and that the chiefe Apoſtles and Doctors of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, haue reuiued and defended all the moſt deteſtable hereſies that euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny former age begotte.<note place="margin">Iacobus Gualtier in lib. cui titulus <hi>Tabula Cronogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phica</hi> Eccleſiae catholicae à Chriſto nato vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad an. 1614. edit. an. 1616. Clement. 3. recog. Irenaeus l. 1. c. 20.</note> IAMES GVAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIER in his learned and elaborate Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nographicall tables (out of the ſeuerall Catalogues of Hereſies, compoſed by S. <hi>Eiphanius, Auſtine, Philaſtrius, Alphonſus</hi> a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro Prateolus,</hi> and other auncient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne writers) hath proued at large. Out of whom I will here inſtance in ſome few which ſeeme to be as the Marrow, Eſſence, and life of Proteſtaniſme. Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe the age in which theſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies were firſt begot; the Fathers and Councells, who oppoſed and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22753:32"/>
them; and the Proteſtant Doctors by whom they are reuiued and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. I will begin with the firſt age.</p>
               <p>In the firſt age, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> one of the firſt deteſted heretikes, was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of hereſie by S. CLEMENT and IRENEVS, for teaching; that men are not ſaued by good workes, but by faith only; and that man had no free will: both which aſſertions, are now gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally maintained by all ſorts of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, as two principal and eſſential Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of their religion.</p>
               <p>That<note n="b" place="margin">Luther in artic. 36.</note> it is not in mans power to thinke either good or euill, but that all things doe happen by abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, is one of our chiefe Articles, ſaith <hi>Martin Luther;</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Idem tom. 5. Ger. Ien. in admonit. ad Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. fol 288. &amp; tom. 7. Ger. Wit. fol. 478.</note> and as for Iuſtification by faith only; (for<note n="d" place="margin">Idem tom. 1. Ger. Wit in 2. ad Galat. fol 47. &amp; 91. &amp; tom. 1. Latt. Ien. fol. 488.</note> faith only Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, and not that faith which includeth Charitie) it is an Article which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without, becauſe that failing, our Church falleth;<note n="e" place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 5. in c. 3. ad Gal.</note> it is our onely ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, without which, both we and all other ſectaries, had vndoubtedly peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed;<note n="f" place="margin">Idem tom. 2. lib. de abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione Miſſae. fol. 390.</note> it is the ſumme of our Goſpel. So Luther.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond age <hi>Cerinthus</hi> ſtands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted of hereſie, by<note n="g" place="margin">Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haereſ. 8</note> S. <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> for teaching that children might be ſaued without Baptiſme; which is now a plauſible doctrine, among all the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22753:33"/>
Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Baptiſme is but a ſeale of the promiſe, and neither hindereth nor furthereth in the way of ſaluation; neither doth the ſaluation of children depende on baptiſme, but on the promiſe which God made to ABRAHAM Gen. 27.7; therefore all the children of beleeuing parents, are ſanctified in their mothers wombe, and are by faith the heires of the kingdome of heauen, ſo<note n="a" place="margin">Caluin l. 4. Inſt. c. 16. n. 24. &amp; 17. &amp; 26. &amp; cap 15. n. 10. &amp; 20. &amp; in ad. tid concil Trident ſeſſ 5. Rogers in his booke entituled the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> doctrine of the Church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. art. 25. Willet in Synopſ. contr. 11. q. 3. Babington Coment. in Geneſ. 17.7. Zanch. in Miſcel. l. 3. art. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluin;</hi> and the like is affirmed by <hi>Rogers, VVillet, Babington, Zanchie,</hi> and all other pure Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>In the ſame age, <hi>Ebion</hi> ſtands condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of hereſie,<note place="margin">Epiphan. haereſ. 30.</note> by the foreſaid <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> for denying <hi>that Chriſtians enioyed the veritie of the old Figures;</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Caluin l. 4. Inſtit. c. 17. &amp; 19. <hi>per to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum</hi> Et c. 14. n. 20. &amp; l. 2. c. 10. n 5. &amp; Willet in Synop. controu. 15. q. 3. &amp; controu. 11. q. 7. &amp; Powel l. 2. de An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſto cap. 21.</note> which is alſo a currant doctrine, among the Caluinian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: For they generallie teach; that the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, is but a figure of Chriſts bodie; That S. IOHN Baptiſts baptiſme, was all one with ours; that our Baptiſme exceedeth not in prerogatiue the Iewes circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that the ſchoolemens diſtinction (teaching that the Sacraments of the Old law did onely adumbrate or shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Sacraments of the new
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22753:33"/>
conferred grace) was to be hiſſed at; and that the Iewes in their ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts had the ſame ſubſtance of Chriſt that we haue.</p>
               <p>Againe, the ſame <hi>Ebion</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the foreſaid<note n="*" place="margin">Epipha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. haere. 30.</note> Father, <hi>For impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a neceſsitie on mariage,</hi> which is a doctrine much vrged &amp; defended by <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> the Proteſtants Apoſtle &amp; Euangeliſt. As it is not in my power (ſaith he) not to be a man,<note place="margin">Luther in Sermon. de Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio 1522. fo. 5. latt. Witt. See alſo Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin l. 4. Inſtit. c. 13. n. 3. &amp; Harmon. in Mat. 19.12.</note> ſo it is not in me to liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a woman, &amp;c. For our Election or Councel is not free, but a thing natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally neceſſarie, that a man be ioyned to a woman, and a woman to a man; for this word which God ſpake, <hi>increaſe and multiplie,</hi> is not a precept, but more then a precept, to wit, Gods worke which is not in our power to hinder or omit, but it is as neceſſarie as to be a man, &amp; more neceſſare then to eate, drinke, purge, ſleepe or wake, &amp;c. So <hi>Luther.</hi> And in an other place, exempting but three kinds of men from the neceſsitie of marriage, viz. Gelded men, Eunuches borne, and ſuch as haue made themſelues Eunukes, he addeth ſaying; whoſoeuer doth not finde himſelfe in the number of one of theſe, muſte in any caſe thinke of a wife, and haſten marriage, yea though he haue made ten vowes, oathes, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and adamantine obligations to the contrarie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:22753:34"/>
                  <note place="margin">Epiphan. haer. 27. &amp; Auguſt haer. 7.</note>Againe in this ſame age, <hi>Capronimus</hi> ſtandes condemned of hereſie, both by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and S. <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> for contending that the law appertained not vnto Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men; which is one of <hi>Luthers</hi> prime doctrines: You shall heare him ſpeake; <note n="a" place="margin">Luther tom 4. Ieu. latt. argum in epiſt. ad Galath.</note> the Apoſtle ſaith, ye are not vnder the Law, but vnder grace; how not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law? according to the new man, vnto whom the Law doth nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine, for it had his limitts vnto Chriſts time, as PAVLE afterward ſaith &amp;c.<note n="b" place="margin">Ibid.</note> ô Law touch not my conſcience, for I am baptized, and by the Goſpel called to the communion of Iuſtice, and euerlaſting life, to the Kingdome of Chriſt, where there is no Law, but meere remiſsion of ſinnes, peace, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and mirth, &amp;c.<note n="c" place="margin">Ibid. in cap. 2. ad Galath. fol. 46.</note> therefore a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is free from all Lawes, and ſubiect to none, neither within nor without<note n="d" place="margin">Ibid. fol. 42.</note> The opinion of <hi>Hierome</hi> and others is to be reiected, who dreame that PAVLE ſpeaketh not here of the ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, but of the Ceremonial Law, &amp;c.<note n="e" place="margin">Ibid. fol. 89.</note> I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>do this and liue,</hi> as a certaine Ironie or ſcoffing ſpeech, &amp;c.<note n="f" place="margin">Ibid. fol. 53.</note> neither doth PAVLE ſpeake here of the Ceremonial Law, &amp;c. but of all the Law, there ſimplie all the Law, whether it be Ceremonial, or of the ten commandements is abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22753:34"/>
to a Chriſtian, &amp;c.<note n="a" place="margin">Ibid. in cap. 4. ad Gal. f. 144</note> THOMAS and other Scholemen ſpeaking about abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the Law, ſay, that the Iudiciall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Ceremoniall Law were taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way after Chriſt, but not the Moral; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe ſpeake they know not what, &amp;c. <note n="b" place="margin">Ibid. in cap. 2. fol. 62. &amp; 54.</note> What is it to me, that thou ô Law accuſeſt me as guiltie, that thou conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteſt me of many ſinnes committed? yea I commit many daily, but this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me, now I am deafe, I heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee not, pray thee trouble not my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;<note n="c" place="margin">Ibid in cap. 2. fol. 55.</note> true it is, I haue ſinned, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God will punish &amp; condemne me! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o; yea but the Law of God ſaith ſo. I haue nothing to doe with this Law; why? becauſe I haue an other Law,<note place="margin">See alſo Caluin 4. Inſt. c. 10. n. 5. &amp; l. 3. c. 19. n. 2. &amp; 4.</note> which compelleth this Law to be mute, to witt, <hi>Libertie;</hi> what <hi>Libertie?</hi> of Chriſt, for by Chriſt I am freed from the Law; ſo a faithfull man by only faith may lift vp himſelfe, and conceaue ſure hope and firme conſolation, that he may not waxe pale at the view of ſinne, but may ſay, <hi>Sir diuel,</hi> thy threats and terrours mooue me nothing, becauſe there is one which is called IESVS CHRIST, in whom I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, he hath abrogated the Law, &amp; is thy <hi>Sathan</hi> ô <hi>Sathan;</hi> ô Law if thou canſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me, binde me, terrifie me, I wil place ouer thee an other Law, that is to ſay, an other tyrant &amp; tormentor, who shall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22753:35"/>
in like maner accuſe, bind, &amp; oppreſſe thee,<note place="margin">v. Luther vt ſupra in cap. 3. ad Calat. fol. 115.</note> thou art in deed my <hi>Hangman,</hi> but I haue an other <hi>Hangman</hi> Chriſt, who shal tortour thee, by him I am free. If the diuell beate me, I haue a ſtronger diuel, who shal in like maner whip him; Chriſt is my diuel;<note n="a" place="margin">Ibid. in cap. 4. ad Galath. fol. 118.</note> therefore a conſcience beleeuing in Chriſt, ought to be ſo ſure, that the law with his terrours &amp; threats is abrogated, that he muſt altogether be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whether MOYSES, the Law, or a Iew euer were; <hi>(b)</hi> the Law certainly is no other then the ſincke of all euils, hereſies and blaſphemies, becauſe it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie augmenteth ſinne, accuſeth, terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, threatneth death, sheweth God to be an angrie Iudge, condemning ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; wherfore if thou be wiſe, banning farre off, <hi>ſtuttering and ſtammering</hi> MOYSES with his Law; neither let his terrours &amp; threats any way moue thee, but do thou ſimplie ſuſpect him as an heretike, an excommunicated perſon, a damned wretch, far worſe then the Pope &amp; the diuel himſelfe, and therefore in no caſe to be heard, &amp;c. Hetherto <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. haer. 6. ſee Alphon. a Caſtro in v. Crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tura. &amp; v. malum.</note>Againe in this ſame age, the <hi>Gnoſtikes</hi> ſtand condemned of hereſie by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> for teaching, <hi>that ſome creatures were</hi> of their owne nature ill: which is <hi>Caluins</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe doctrine. For he plainly ſaith, that the diuel was by nature euill, wicked,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22753:35"/>
malicious;<note place="margin">Caluin. l. 3. Inſt. c. 23. n. 3 &amp; l 1. c. 14. n. 15. &amp; 17. Epiphan. in ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceph. &amp; Auguſt. haer. 18.</note> and that all men (whom God hath Predeſtinated to death, are by a natural condition, guiltie of death.</p>
               <p>Againe in this ſame age, the <hi>Caini</hi> ſtand condemned of hereſie, both by S. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for teaching that Iudas fact was good in betraying his maiſter; and that he fore-ſaw the benefites which would accrew vnto vs by Chriſts Paſsion: which in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is plauſible doctrine, among all the Caluin-Proteſtants;<note place="margin">Crowly in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie. pag. 30. &amp; 46.</note> I confeſſe (ſaith <hi>Crowly</hi>) in his Treatiſe entituled, <hi>An Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie or defence of the English Writers</hi>) theſe are my wordes, that Gods Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the onely cauſe of Adams fal, but not conſequently of all ſinne, for ſuch as haue eyes to ſee,<note place="margin">See Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamcton in Rom. 8. edit. 1. &amp; Caluin l. 1. Inſtit. c. 18. n. 1. &amp; 2. &amp; l. 3. c. 23. n. 8.</note> doe ſee that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams fall was good, &amp;c. yea it is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine generally maintained by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants (as shall be shewed in the next Chapter) that <hi>Abſolons</hi> inceſtious adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, was Gods worke; that Iudas trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, was as well the worke of God, as Paules vocation; that the Iewes in abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our Sauiour, and putting him to death, did nothing but what the hand and Counſel of God had formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, and the like.</p>
               <p>Againe in this ſame age the <hi>Plotemaians</hi> ſtand condemned for heretiks by S.<note place="margin">Epiphan. haer 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> for maintaining, <hi>that God had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22753:36"/>
ſome impoſsible things.</hi> And in particular touching the inſeparable knot of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; which doctrine is generally main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by all Proteſtants; as appeareth not onely in that they (contrarie to Gods word) admit of ſo many diuorces as shall be anone shewed, but in that they maintaine<note n="*" place="margin">Caluin l. 2. Inſtit. c. 7. n. 5. &amp; in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. c. 2</note> that the Law of God, or the ten Commandements are impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be kept,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Idem comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. in Act. 14. v. 10.</note> no not though a man be neuer ſo much aſsiſted or holpen by Gods grace.</p>
               <p>Againe in the ſame age the <hi>Priſcillians, Marcites</hi> or <hi>Marcocites</hi> ſtand condemned for heretikes, both by S. <hi>Ireneus,</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and S.<note place="margin">Irenaeus l. 1. c. 9. Epiphan. haer. 49. Auguſt. haer. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> for teaching that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Preiſt-hood, appertained as well to women as to men; which doctrine is alſo maintaned by <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> the two great Euangeliſts of Proteſtaniſme.</p>
               <p>In the adminiſtration of the<note n="b" place="margin">Luther tom. 7. Witt. Lat in notis Eccleſ. fol. 150.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, it is not materiall whether the partie (adminiſtring) be male or female, young or old, neither neede we in the adminiſtration of the Word and Baptiſme be inquiſitiue touching theſe &amp;c.<note n="c" place="margin">Idem tom. 2. Ien. Lat. lib. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broganda Miſſa. fol. 442. 443. 444. 447. 448. 449. &amp; tom. 1. Ger. Ien. fol. 336. &amp; 824. apud Vtenbergium. cauſa 7. See alſo tom. 2. Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. Witt. fol. 90. &amp; lib. de miniſtris Eccleſiae pag. 36. where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coning vp all the parts of Prieſtly function, as to Preach, to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, to Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate, to giue ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, &amp;c. He conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that they are all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to women.</note> I ſay, that among Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there is no difference of perſons, no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22753:36"/>
Lay perſon, no Clarke, no Shaueling, no Annointed perſon, no Monke &amp;c. Prieſthood in the New Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and common to all Chriſtians, for we are all Prieſts in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that Chriſt was a Prieſt; this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is vnreſiſtable, that in the New Teſtament, there are no viſible Prieſts, nor can be different from lay perſons, and ſuch as be, are without the warrant of Scripture; therefore all Chriſtians, haue power and authorite to Preach though BEHEMOTH, with all his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents burſt himſelfe; when <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, it is not permitted for a woman to ſpeake in the Church, he doth not ſpeak ſimply, as if it were vtterly vnlawful for a woman to Preach, but only that it is not fitting for a woman to Preach, if a man be in preſence, that is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that office, otherwiſe it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that a woman ſpeake &amp;c. all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, both men and women,<note place="margin">See Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin l. 4. Inſt. c. 19. n 28. &amp;c 4. n. 9. Gualtier in Crono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>graphia. ſaec. 2. in Collat. c. 16.</note> young &amp; old, maiſters and ſeruants, miſtaeſſes &amp; maids, learned &amp; vnlearned are Prieſts; neither is there any difference, if their faith be alike; whoſoeuer hath crept out of baptiſme, may glorie, that he is both a Prieſt, a Bishop, and a Pope. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>Martin Luther.</hi> And the like is taught by other Proteſtants; yea <hi>Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:22753:37"/>
affirmeth,<note place="margin">See Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimundus Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus l. 7. de Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne haereſ. c. 7. n. 5. where he reciteth many ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> that in Prouince, Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brug, and infinite other places, women haue bene ordinarily ſeene to Preach; and that not many yeares ſince, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man among the Abbenacenſes, when a certaine Miniſter denyed to giue her the Communion, went angerly home to her owne houſe, and there laying a Napkin vpon a ſtoole, ſet Bread and Wine thereon, and with her owne handes, miniſtred vnto her ſelfe, the Lords ſupper.</p>
               <p>Laſtly in this ſame age, <hi>Prodicus</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Adamites, ſtands condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of hereſie by the<note n="*" place="margin">See Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. anno 120. n. 37 Luther in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. tom. 2. Ien. lat. fol. 247. 173. 275. Caluin. l. 4. Inſt. c. 10 n. 1. See alſo l. 3. Inſtit. c. 19. n. 2. &amp; 4.</note> Doctors of that time, for teaching <hi>that Chriſtian people were not tyed in conſcience, to performe anie Lawe;</hi> which doctrine is likewiſe maintained by <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> and followed in practiſe by all ſorts of Proteſtants; It is certaine, that neither Men nor Angels, can impoſe any Lawes vpon Chriſtian men, vnleſſe they be willing thereunto. So <hi>Luther,</hi> and the like is affirmed of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin.</hi> Yea he dareth to ſay; that humane Lawes, how good or honeſt ſoeuer, whether they be made by Church or Magiſtrate, doe not bind in conſcience <note n="(a)" place="margin">Lib. 4. Inſtit. c. 20. n. 1.</note> and that the promiſed libertie in the Goſpel, did acknowledge neither King nor Magiſtrate among men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:22753:37"/>IN the third age,<note place="margin">Auguſtin. contra Fauſtum Manich. lib. 20. c. 5. 6. 7. &amp; haer. 40.</note> the Manichaeans ſtand condemed by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> for that they condemned <hi>Altars;</hi> which is ſo cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant a doctrine among Proteſtants, that Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> in his Sermon vpon the Lords Supper, boldly affirmeth, that the word <hi>Alter</hi> hath bene kept in the Church by the diuel, that men should beleeue the Euchariſt to be a Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſame Manichees<note n="*" place="margin">See Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teolus v. Manichaei</note> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically attributed all thinges to fate or ineuitable neceſsitie, and affirmed that ſinne could not be auoided; which is a doctrine now generally maintained by all Proteſtant doctors, eſpecially thoſe of the Caluinean ſect.<note n="b" place="margin">Caluin 1. 3. Inſtit c. 23. n. 9</note> 
                  <hi>reprobi euadere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queunt peccandi neceſsitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi> The Reprobats cannot auoid the neceſsitie of ſinning; eſpecially, when by ordinance of God, ſuch a neceſsitie of ſinning is impoſed vpon them. So Caluin. Yea there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more familiar with him and his followers, then to affirme<note n="c" place="margin">Idem li. 1. Inſt. l 18. n. 4.</note> that man being iuſtly forced by God, doth doe what is not lawful for him;<note n="d" place="margin">Ibid. n. 1.</note> that God cauſed ABSOLON to pollute by inceſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Adulterie, his fathers bed;<note n="e" place="margin">Bucer. in cap. 1. ad. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. p. 72. &amp; in cap. 9. p. 454.</note> that God doth not only permit men to fall into errour by forſaking them, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth, hardneth, deliuereth into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſence, and ſendeth a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full errour, to make men doe ſuch a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22753:38"/>
thing<note n="a" place="margin">Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. de Predeſt. pag. 105. 166. 167. cap. 1.</note> that the moſt horred offences that euer were, are done by Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; that ſinnes through the force of that decree, are altogether inauoidable.</p>
               <p>IN the fourth age the Donatiſts ſtand conuicted of hereſie by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> for contending, that the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of Chriſt and S. Iohn Baptiſt were al one.<note place="margin">Auguſt. l. 2. contra lit. Petil. c. 32. &amp; 34.</note> Which is a doctrine generally defended by all Caluinian Proteſtants;<note n="b" place="margin">Caluin. l. 4. Inſtit. c. 15. n. 8. &amp; 1. Willet in ſynop. controu. 14. q. 3. &amp; cont. 12. q, 7. Powel l. 2. de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſto. c. 21. Optatus Meliui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. lib. 2. &amp; 6. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. See Sanders haer. 91.</note> the auncient Fathers were deceiued (ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi>) when they ſaid, that the Baptiſme of IOHN, was but a preparatiue to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme of Chriſt; we (ſaith <hi>D. Willet</hi>) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Sacrament of IOHN and our Sauiour were al one; yea (ſaith <hi>Powel</hi>) we Proteſtants hold it a blaſphemie in the Papiſts, for making a differance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene IOHNS and Chriſts Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Againe, the ſame Donatiſts ſtande co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by S. <hi>optatus Miliuitan,</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning holy Oyle, and caſting it on the ground; as alſo for that they cauſed the Sacrament of the Euchariſt to be caſt to the dogges, pulled downe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, (Which he calleth the ſeates of Chriſts body) broke and ſold <hi>Chalices,</hi> rent and <hi>tore corporalls, veiles, bookes,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruments appertaining to Gods ſeruice: which was the ordinarie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of Caluin-Proteſtants in the beginning of their deformed reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22753:38"/>
and in which they ſtill perſeuer, as opportunitie offereth it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſame Donatiſts ſtande condemned by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> for teaching,<note place="margin">Aguſtine concione 2. in Pſal. 5 &amp; in Pſal. 18. &amp; in epiſt 16. ad Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſ. &amp; lib. de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. c. 11. &amp; 13. Epiphan. haer 68. &amp; 69. Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret lib. 4. haeret. fab. &amp; Auguſt. haeret. 46.</note> that the Catholike Church was peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in all the world, except in thoſe places which Donatus liued. Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is a doctrine generally taught by all ſortes of Proteſtants, as was shewed in the former chapter.</p>
               <p>Againe in the ſame age, the Arians ſtand condemned of hereſie by S. <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, S. Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, that the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, were not of one nature, ſubſtance, or eſſence, and refuſing to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or conſubſtantiall, becauſe it was not in the ſcripture: in both which, the chiefe Proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, shew themſelues to be their true diſciples and faithful followers, as shall be shewed in the next chapter.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſame Arians were<note n="*" place="margin">Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius ſer. 4. contra Arrianns &amp; Hilarie l. 9. de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, for that they taught that the Sonne of God was ignorant of many things, and that he learned as he grew in yeares, which alſo is currant doctrine with Caluin and his Cymiſts.<note n="a" place="margin">Caluin Harmon. in Mat. c. 24 v. 36. &amp; har. in Luke c. 2. v. 40.</note> It is euident, that ignorance was common to Chriſt with the Angels: ſo Caluin; yea he further ſaith, that Chriſts ſoule was as ſubiect to ignorance, as the ſoules
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22753:39"/>
of other men, and that this was the only difference betweene vs and him, that our neceſsities are of neceſsitie, his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie; and that Chriſt in particular knew not the day of Iudgement, nor what tree that was which he curſed. And the like is taught by other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctors, as shall be shewed in the next chapter.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſame <hi>Arrians</hi> are<note n="*" place="margin">See Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus à Caſtro. v. concili.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of hereſie, for maintaining that <hi>a Councel, howe lawfull ſo euer aſſembled and approued might erre:</hi> Which alſo is a high-prized doctrine in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Synagogue; you shall heare the wordes of their firſt Author and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt.<note n="a" place="margin">Luther in poſtil. concione 1. poſt dominic. Trinit. fol. 114. Witt. Lat &amp; art. 115 &amp; 500. &amp; tom. 7. Witt. Ger. fol. 262.</note> Among all the Councels, I neuer ſaw any in which the Holie Ghoſt was found; Councels are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, neither muſt we truſt vnto them; for there was neuer any ſo incontami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, but either added or diminished from Gods word; yea the councel of the Apoſtles, albeit it was the firſt and moſt pure, had ſome what mingled with it, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Epiphan. haer. 75. &amp; in ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal. Auguſt. haer. 53. Nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 9 c. 16.</note> This abhominable opinion (that councels haue the Holie Ghoſt) is to be numbred among the greateſt euils of chriſtianitie. So this Apoſtata.</p>
               <p>Againe in the ſame age <hi>Euſtachius</hi> and <hi>Aerius</hi> ſtand condemned by S. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for maintaining that the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22753:39"/>
Faſtes of the Church, were not to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued;</hi> which is alſo a knowne cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant doctrine among all ſortes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; yea it is common with the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſort of them, to make their greateſt feaſts vpon the greateſt and ſolemneſt faſting dayes, of which none can be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſame <hi>Aerius,</hi> ſtands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the two fore ſaid Fathers,<note place="margin">Epiphan haer. 75. &amp; Auguſt haer. 53.</note> for teaching that the <hi>dead were not to bee prayed for, nor Sacrifice to be offered for them:</hi> which alſo is a Doctrine generallie taught by all Proteſtant Doctors; yea in defence therof, they dare pronounce with their maiſter <hi>Caluin;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin. l. 3. Inſtit. c. 5 n. 10.</note> that all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in praying and offering Sacrifice for the dead, were foolishly deluded by the deceipts of Sathan; that it was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of ill-conſulted ſedulitie, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate credulitie, and peruerſe emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that the cuſtome of praying for the dead, was a profanation of the inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of God, and that it was an errour yea and a groſſe &amp; ſuperſtitious errour.</p>
               <p>Againe in the ſame age, <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata ſtands<note n="*" place="margin">See So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomen l. 5. cap. 20. &amp; Euſeb. l. 7. c. 14.</note> condemned, for that he brake downe the Image of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and cauſed his owne to be ſet vp in ſteed thereof; as alſo for that he was a great enimie to the Holy Croſſe, the Crucifix, and the ſigne of the Croſſe:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22753:40"/>
and haue not the Caluinian Miniſters abundantly reuied the memorie of this accurſed Apoſtata? haue they not throwne downe the Images of our Sauiour? broaken downe Croſſes and Crucifixes? do they not hold the ſigne of the Croſſe as ſuperſtition? and in ſteed of the Images of Chriſt and our Sauiour do they not place in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate howſes the pictures of their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata <hi>deformers,</hi> or the Laſciuious Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis, Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Ganimede</hi> and ſuch like, &amp;c?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus contra Heluidiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>Againe in the ſame age <hi>Heluidius</hi> ſtands condemned by S. <hi>Hierome</hi> and the other Catholike Doctors, for equalling the merit of marriage, with the merit of virginitie,<note place="margin">Luther Sermon. pe Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio. tom. 5. Lat. Wit. &amp; tom. in Epiſt. ad Wolſang fol. 505. See Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. l. 4. Inſtit. c. 12. n. 28. &amp; Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. in Mat. 19.11.12.</note> wihch heretical doctrine all the Doctors of Proteſtancie do alſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly maintaine; yea their father <hi>Luther</hi> dareth to write; that ſingle life is farre more baſe and vild then marriage; that matrimonie is more then a precept; that who ſo determineth to liue without a woman, muſt put off the name of man, and put on the nature of an angell or ſpirit; that he muſt needs be a whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter that flyeth marriage, and that it is more neceſſarie to lie with a woman then to eate drinke or ſleepe.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſame <hi>Iouinian</hi> ſtands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for maintaining,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22753:40"/>
that theſe who were by Baptiſme rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, and receiued into grace, could not looſe that grace, nor ſinne, at leaſt to death; which verie doctrine was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued by <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luther in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon. tom. 2. Lat. Wit. fol. 78. Caluin l. 4. Inſt. c. 17. n. 2. Damman l. de Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum p. 145. &amp; Piſcator in reſp. ad duplic. Voſtij. p. 389. &amp; alij paſsim.</note> and is ſtill eagerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by all Caluinian Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Thou ſeeſt how rich a Chriſtian or Baptized man is, who though he would, cannot looſe his ſaluation, what ſinnes ſoeuer he commit, vnleſſe he will ceaſe to beleeue; So Luther. By our ſinnes (ſaith Caluin) we can no more be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then Chriſt himſelfe; we maintaine ſaith <hi>Damman,</hi> that the iuſt man muſt of neceſsitie perſeuer, and that thoſe who are truly faithful, cannot fall from grace by any ſinnes; they that are once iuſtified, remaine alway iuſtified. So the Vniuerſitie of Oxford, in their late Veſpers. 10. Iulij. nu. 1619. reſp. <hi>Baites</hi> &amp;c. Iles, and the like is affirmed by <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcator</hi> and all others.</p>
               <p>IN the fift age <hi>Vigilantius</hi> ſtands condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of hereſie by S.<note place="margin">Hieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierome</hi> for deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Catholike cuſtome in ſetting vp waxe lights at the Tombes of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs; for impugning the ſingle life of Preiſts; for teaching that it was idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, to reuerence the ſepulchers and holy relikes of Saintes, and denying that Saints were to be inuocated or worshipped. Then which <hi>Vigilantian</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22753:41"/>
no doctrines are more plauſible in the Proteſtant religion;<note place="margin">Hieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus l. 3. contra Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</note> The <hi>Pelagian</hi> in the ſame age are comdemned of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie by the foreſaid father, for boaſting that they were ſure of their iuſtice, and might ſecurely promiſe to them ſelues the kingdome of heauen; whch is the verie doctrine of the Proteſtants at this day; al the faithful ought to be certaine of their ſaluation,<note place="margin">Caluin in Antidot. concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. c. 15. 13 &amp; 10. &amp; l. 3 Inſtit. c. 2. n. 16. 38. 39. 40 &amp; l. 4. c. 17. n. 2.</note> ſaith <hi>Caluin,</hi> yea ſaith he, that man is not truly faithful, who doth not confidently glorie that he is the heire of the kingdome of heauen, ſince our ſinnes can no more hurt vs, then Chriſt him ſelfe, nor we looſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, more then he.<note n="a" place="margin">Luther tom. 4. Ien. Lat. in cap. 4. ad Galat. fol. 118. &amp; 122. &amp; in Colloq menſal. Powel. de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. l. 2. c. 19.</note> we, thankes be to God, can decree and iudge out of the word, how God is affected towards vs; we ought not to doubt that the ſpirit of God dwelleth in vs, but certainly to determine that we are the temple of the holy ghoſt; we ought firmely to beleeue that not only our office is pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, but alſo our perſon, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we ſay, do, or thinke. So Luther. To which Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> addeth, that it is blaſphemie to ſay that euery man ought not to aſſure himſelfe of his ſaluation.</p>
               <p>The Neſtorians in this ſame age ſtand<note n="*" place="margin">Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine haer. 89. Socra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes l. 7. c. 32.</note> condemned of hereſie, for tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that Ieſus Chriſt borne of the Virgin MARIE, was not God, but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22753:41"/>
meere man,<note place="margin">Sanders haer. 100.</note> and after had the diuinitie ioyned vnto him, for the merrit of his holy life, and that not perſonally nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but only by a ſpeciall prerogatiue, &amp;c. In which blaſphemous hereſie, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> &amp; <hi>Caluin</hi> far exceede him, for though they ſeeme to acknowledge that Chriſt was perfect God, and that his diuinitie was ioyned to his humanitie perſonally by an hypoſtaticall vnion, yet they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten ignorance and deſperation on him, and make him a ſinner, yea the greateſt of ſinners: You shall heare them ſpeake; <hi>Omnes Prophetae &amp;c.</hi> all the Prophets fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw this in ſpirit, that Chriſt should be the greateſt thiefe,<note place="margin">Luther in cap. 3. ad Galat. tom. 5. Lat. Wit. fol. 348. 349.</note> the greateſt adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, the greateſt man ſlayer, the moſt Sacrilegious &amp; moſt blaſphemous, &amp;c. becauſe being a ſacrifice for the ſinnes of the world, he is no innocent perſon, and without ſinne, he is not the Sonne of God, borne of the Virgin, but a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, &amp;c. We ought to acknowledge, that as Chriſt was inwrapped in our flesh &amp; blood, ſo likewiſe in our ſinnes, malediction, death and euils: but you will happily ſay, that it is abſurd to call God a ſinner and accurſed? I anſwere,<note n="c" place="margin">Idem hom. baptiſ. tom. 5 lat. W fol. 3 349.</note> that if thou wilt denie that he was a ſinner, deny alſo that he ſuffered for thee, &amp;c. <hi>(a)</hi> all the ſinnes of the world were ſo laide vpon Chriſts shoulders,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22753:42"/>
that he became the moſt grieuous and greateſt ſinner vpon earth,<note place="margin">Caluin in cap. 3. ad Galath &amp; in 1. ad Cor. c. 5.</note> &amp;c. Since then he was ſo great a ſinner, he needed baptiſme, and it was very requiſite that he should be baptiſed, for the remiſsion of his ſinnes. So Luther. Chriſt in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming mans nature, was truly a ſinner, and guiltie of the curſe of God;<note n="a" place="margin">Idem. l. 2. Inſt. c. 16. n. 10.</note> it had bene to no purpoſe, if Chriſt had onely died a corporall death<note n="b" place="margin">Ibid. n. 12. &amp; har. in Mat. 27. v. 46.</note> he indured in ſoule the torments of a damned, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperat man;<note n="c" place="margin">Ibid.</note> he was ſo vexed on all ſides, that being ouer-whelmed with deſperation, he ceaſed to call vpon God, which was to renounce his owne ſaluation. So Caluin. and further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth<note n="d" place="margin">L. 2. Inſt. c. 16. n. 12. in har. in Mar. 14. 36. &amp; Luke 2.4. &amp; in Mat. 26.39. &amp; ad Rom. c. 9. v. 3. See after in the next chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note> that Chriſt was touched with a vicious affection; that in his prayers, he held not a well proportioned courſe; that hee in a manner wauered in his vowes; that he forgot that he was ſent hether on that condition to be our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; yea that he refuſed and detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as much as in him lay, the office of a Redeemer; that he feared the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne ſoule, and the like.</p>
               <p>Laſtly in this age, <hi>Zenaias</hi> ſtands<note n="*" place="margin">Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus l. 16. c. 27. &amp; Baron. an. 485. n. 16.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of hereſie, for the denying the worship of Images; and the foreſaid <note n="e" place="margin">Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes l. 7. c. 32. &amp; Sand. haer 100.</note> Neſtorius, for proudly contemning the writings of the Fathers, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe and other his adhaerents,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22753:42"/>
before all antiquitie. The firſt of which hereſies is a principle in Proteſtancie, and as touching the ſecond, I am verily perſwaded that Neſtorius came short of the Proteſtant Doctors.</p>
               <p>I am<note n="a" place="margin">Luther contra regem Angl. to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. Witt. fol. 339. &amp; tom. 6. Ger. Witt f. 483.</note> aſſured that I haue my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from heauen, and therefore I wil not conſent that either Man or Angel be iudge of my doctrine, but by it, I meane to iudge both Men and Angels; <note n="b" place="margin">tom. 1. Ger. Ien. in praefat. &amp; lib. ad Ducen. Georgiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> no doctor ſince the Apoſtles time, hath ſo plainely prooued and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the chiefe articles of faith, out of the word of God, as I haue done;<note n="c" place="margin">L. de ſeruo arbitrio contra Eraſ. edit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. vide etiam tom. 2. Witt. fol. 486. apud Breiarlio in apol. Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. tract. 2. c. 2. ſect. 10 ſub. 9.</note> wee will admit of no other authoritie, but the Scriptures, and thoſe after our owne interpretation; what we interpret was the minde of the holy Ghoſt, but what others interpret, how many or learned ſoeuer, proceed from the diuel;<note n="d" place="margin">In cap. 1. ad Galath. tom. 5. Witt. fol. 290. &amp; tom. 7. Witt. fol. 483.</note> ſay that the Church, <hi>Auſtine,</hi> or the other Doctors, nay ſay that <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> or an Angel of heauen, teach the contrarie, yet my doctrine is of that nature, which will illuſtrate Gods glorie;<note n="(e)" place="margin">Tom 4. Ien. Lat. in 2. Galath.</note> PETER prime of the Apoſtles, did liue &amp; teach beyond the warrant of Scripture, and therefore he did erre<note n="(f)" place="margin">In colloq men. fol. 588.</note> I am <hi>Iſayas,</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22753:43"/>
and <hi>Philip, (Melancton)</hi> is <hi>Ieremias;</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Idem in colloq. menſ. fol. 932. &amp; 17. &amp; 478 &amp; tom. 2. latt. Wit. fol. 500. &amp; 505. apud. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium in theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. Caluini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica.</note> 
                  <hi>Baſil</hi> was wholly a Monke, and not worth a rush; <hi>Cyprian</hi> was a weake diuine; <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> doth nothing but prate, his bookes are a troubleſome and inordinate pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket; <hi>Athanaſius</hi> had nothing ſingular in him; <hi>Hierome</hi> ought not to be numbred among the Church doctors, for he was an heretike, a man of no iudgement nor diligence; he wrote manie things wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly, he was a very block head in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the Scriptures, obtruding Iewish blindneſſe for hiſtoricall ſence, and his owne follies for allegories. I know not among the Fathers, to whom I am ſuch an enemie, for he writeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but of faſting, difference of meats, and virginitie; but as for faith and true religion, there is not a word to be found in his writings; <hi>Gregories</hi> ſermons are not worth a farthing; in his dialogues, the diuel deceiued him, &amp;c. Hetherto Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touching himſelfe and the fathers:<note place="margin">Caluin in epiſt. 145. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bachium.</note> neither doe his followers differ from him in iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> was an excellent ſeruant of God; and a faithfull miniſter of the Church;<note n="b" place="margin">l. 1. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Pighi.</note> a ſingular Apoſtle of Chriſt, by whoſe mouth God thundered;<note n="c" place="margin">Epiſt. 109. ad fratres Monſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar.</note> from whoſe Church our Goſpel did flow; a man moſt excellently qualified, &amp;c. So Caluin. to which other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22753:43"/>
a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dde<note n="a" place="margin">Beza in lib. de paena hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. p. 94. 95. 148. apud Ka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in praefat. Catechiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minoris<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lutheri.</note> that he was the renewer of Chriſtian Religion, Gods ſingular ſeruant, in whom who ſo ſeeth not the ſpirit of God, ſeeth nothing;<note n="b" place="margin">Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Kan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fen vt ſup</note> that no age would euer produce ſuch a man; <note n="c" place="margin">Kanſen in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fata prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatione</note> that he was a bleſſed man, in whom the Holy Ghoſt shined; the Prophet of Germanie; the light bringer and light-lender to all diuines; the wonder of the world;<note n="d" place="margin">Amſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſius in praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. 1. Tom. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theri.</note> that there was neuer any ſince the Apoſtles time, who for ſpirit, wiſdome, and vnderſtanding, might be compared with him;<note n="e" place="margin">Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſted. l. 7.</note> that he excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the auntient Fathers, as much as the Sunne ſurpaſſeth the Moone; and that neither S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> nor any of the reſt, had they liued in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, would haue bene ashamed to haue bene his ſchollers, and haue carried a candle before him;<note n="f" place="margin">Iuel in Apolog. par. 2. c. 4. 2. &amp; Fox Acts &amp; Monuments.</note> that he was a man ſent from God to illuminate the world, the Chariot, and the Coachman of Iſrael; <note n="(g)" place="margin">Powel in his <hi>Animaduerſ.</hi> of the Papiſts ſupplicat. p 70.</note> a thriſe holy man;<note n="(h)" place="margin">Spanburgius l. contra Stephan. Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colum. See the Proteſtants Apologie. Tract. 2. c. 2. ſect. 10. ſub. 15. &amp; 9.</note> the next in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to Chriſt and Paule;<note n="(i)" place="margin">See in Mercurius Gallobel. Arthurus Goterdi. an. 1617. at what time a Inbile was celebrated, by the conſent of all Proteſtants, in memorie of Luther.</note> the elect veſſel and organ of God; the light of the Goſpel, &amp;c. So they touching their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22753:44"/>
maiſter <hi>Luther.</hi> But as for the auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers they will not tell<note n="a" place="margin">Caluin commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. in Ioh. c. 10 v. 6. &amp;c. 11. 13. &amp;c. 15. 20.</note> that S. <hi>Auſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was a prating diuine, variable, &amp; incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in all learning; S. <hi>Gregorie Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene,</hi> a teller of feigned fables; S. <hi>Baſil</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> erronious fellow;<note n="b" place="margin">Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in 14. ad Rom.</note> S. <hi>Irenes,</hi> a man tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neuer read the Scriptures, and one tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnderſtood not the Apoſtles Creede, a peſtilent writer;<note n="c" place="margin">Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtae in ſcuto fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei dialo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go 8. See Feuarden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius in theolog. Caluiniſt.</note> S. <hi>Clement</hi> (the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low labourer with S. <hi>Paule</hi> (Phil. 4.3. a verie knaue, and infected with a diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish contagion; S. <hi>Denis</hi> of Areopagite, an inſolent and dangerous fellow;<note n="d" place="margin">Beza in Iconibus &amp; Luther in poſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain die exultat.</note> that S. <hi>Ierome</hi> was an Idolater, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of Idolatrie; a worſe Chriſtian, then <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> and as certainly damned (vnleſſe he repented him of his hereſies) as the diuel;<note n="e" place="margin">See the Suruey pag. 337. Pomero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comment in Ionam. Socinus I de Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti natura contra volanum p. 222. See Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Apol 1. 1. ſect. 16. fol. 2.</note> that S. <hi>Anacletus</hi> and <hi>Anice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> were no better then rogues, and men branded in the forehead, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I care not for the Fathers, whether holy or not holy, they were blinded with a Montanicall ſpirit, in the Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and doctrines of diuels, ſpeaking lyes, &amp;c. we ought not to credit them, &amp;c. So <hi>Pomeran.</hi> wee doe not hold our ſelues ſubiect to the iudgement of any Fathers, how learned ſoeuer, nor to the iudgement of any Councels, though neuer ſo lawfully aſſembled, nor to the iudgement of any church how perfect or vniuerſall ſo euer. So <hi>Socinus.</hi> And
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22753:44"/>
the like might be prooued out of all the other Proteſtants,<note place="margin">Beza in epigram. an. 1597. p. 178. &amp; in Iconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; in vita Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uini.</note> touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Catholike Fathers. But as touching the doctors of their owne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, they ſpeake as you heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of <hi>Luther;</hi> no man wrote more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly then <hi>Caluin,</hi> no man more godlie; we owe the building of our Church vnto <hi>Caluin</hi> next vnto God, he was the deſtroyer of all hereſies, both new and old; he was the faithful &amp; vn-reproue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſeruant of God, a true Prophet, and the mouth of the Lord. So <hi>Beza.</hi> Againe <note n="a" place="margin">Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtae in clypio fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log 8. &amp; Beza in Iconib. See Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus in Cronog. ſec. 2. Coll. 20.</note> we acknowledge <hi>Witcliffe</hi> for a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble martir, and the true and immortall glorie of England; <hi>Hus</hi> for a true hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly gooſes <hi>Zwinglius</hi> and <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> for a noble paire of heauenly warriors; <hi>Tindal</hi> for a great Euangeliſt. And ſo of the reſt.</p>
               <p>IN the ſixt age, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> among other Hereſies,<note n="*" place="margin">Cedre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio.</note> blaſphemouſly maintained <hi>that God was the author of ſinne,</hi> ſo do the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, as shall be shewed in the next chapter.</p>
               <p>As the <hi>Armeni</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Alpho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ a Caſtro. v. baptiſ. Matrim. &amp; Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtia.</note> heretically taught that the Sacraments did not conferre grace; that Matrimonie was no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that in the Euchariſt water was not to be mingled with the wine, ſo do all ſorts of Proteſtants, eſpecially of the Caluinian ſect.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:22753:45"/>Againe, as the fore ſaid <hi>Mahomet</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Prateo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus verbo Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metes.</note> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically allowed poligamie, or a plurality of wiues, ſo doth <hi>Luther, Muſculus, Melancton,</hi> and other chiefe Proteſtant doctors;<note n="b" place="margin">Luth. in propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus de biga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia. an. 1528. propoſ. 62. 65. 66 &amp; in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit in Geneſim. an. 1525. cap. 16.</note> Poligamie is now no more abrogated then the reſt of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, but left indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, to witt, neither forbidded nor commaunded. ſo <hi>Luther.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Muſc. in expreſ. Pauli ad Coloſ. &amp; Tim. 3. Melancto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olog. p. 134. &amp; 128. an 171. Beza in creopagie fol. 80. Zanchie. in Miſcel. fol. 27. Caluin in Epiſt editis à Beza in 8. an. 76. pag. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Muſculus</hi> alſo is of opinion that Poligamie was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the time of the Apoſtles; and <hi>Philip Melancton</hi> (though he iudge the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8. from his firſt wife <hi>Catherine,</hi> as moſt vnlawfull) is confident, that king <hi>Henry</hi> might with credit and a good conſcience (if his end were to haue iſſue) haue taken an other wife &amp;c. becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>Poligamie</hi> is no vnuſuall thing, nor againſt Gods Law; ſince <hi>Abraham, Dauid</hi> and many holy men, had many wiues at once. Thus <hi>Melancton, Beza, Phinix, Zanchies</hi> moſt holy man, and <hi>Caluins</hi> true diuine.</p>
               <p>There be yet liuing can well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Doctor <hi>Lawrence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His firſt wife is yet liuing &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth at <hi>Cowly.</hi>
                  </note> publike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor in the Greeke tongue, in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of Oxford, both in the dayes of King Edward the ſixt, and Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, had two wiues at once, the one dwelling at <hi>Cowley,</hi> and the other in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22753:45"/>
which two he vſed ſucceſsiuely, the whole Vniuerſitie either willingly conniuing, or elſe approuing the ſame.</p>
               <p>It is alſo well knowne (to omit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) that D. <hi>Thorneborow,</hi> now bishop of Worceſter, had a long time two wiues at once, one of which (viz. the firſt his true lawfull wife) is lately dead; whence it is euident, that the Doctors of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, euery way equal Mahomet in the approbation of Poligamie.</p>
               <p>Furthermore as the ſame Mahomet heretically taught;<note place="margin">Prateo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus verbo Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> that any man might lawfully ſue a deuorce in theſe three ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; to wit, if his wife were barren, or peruerſly mannered; or if he could not loue her, and after foure moneths mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie another; ſo doth <hi>Luther, Caluin, Bucer,</hi> &amp; all other chiefe Proteſtant Doctors: yea and in many other caſes alſo. You shall heare them ſpeake.</p>
               <p>Somtimes wiues proue ſo froward,<note place="margin">Luther ſerm. de Matrim. &amp; vita coniugali tom. 5. lat. fol. 123.</note> that though their husbands should tentimes fall into luſt, yet ſuch would be their hardnes, that they would not regard it; here then it is meete for the husband to ſay, <hi>If thou wilt not an other will, if the miſtreſſe will not, let the maid come,</hi> diſmiſſe <hi>Vasthi,</hi> and take <hi>Heſter,</hi> after the example of King <hi>Aſſuerus.</hi> So Luther. Againe:<note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is the duty of Magiſtrates (if wiues proue ſo obſtinate) to force them, yea
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22753:46"/>
and punish them by death; but if the Magiſtrate will not doe it,<note place="margin">Ibid. Melanct. in analijs theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gieis part 1. p. 648. &amp; 550. Canones Genuenſ. an. 1560. &amp; 1562.</note> then let the husband imagine with himſelfe, that his wife is taken away by thieues and killed, and ſo let him chooſe another wife. Againe.</p>
               <p>An adulterer may (after diuorce) goe into a ſtrange countrey, and there if he cannot containe, he may take a wife. So <hi>Luther,</hi> and the like is affirmed by <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton</hi> and <hi>Pomeran.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bucer in cap. 19. Mat. Bucanus in locis commun. loco 12.</note>If a husband (ſay the Geneuean can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons) shall be abſent, let his wife cauſe him to be called by the publike cryer, &amp; if he come not within the time limmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Miniſter shall licence the wife to take an other husband.</p>
               <p>Whether a woman be put away iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly or vniuſtly, if she haue no hope to returne to her firſt husband, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to lead a godly life, and wanteth the companie of a man, he that marrieth her, shal not offend. So <hi>Bucer.</hi> with whom <hi>Bucanus</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> giue their aſſent, and farther adde;<note n="a)" place="margin">Caluin l. 4. Inſt. c 19. n. 37.</note> that in caſe two be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, without the conſent of their parents;<note n="b)" place="margin">Idem in ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenſ. p. 29. an. 1562.</note> or in caſe a man marry a whore, inſteed of a virgin;<note n="c)" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 32.</note> or in caſe any partie get any contagious diſeaſe; <note n="d)" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 40. 41.</note> or in caſe either partie be abſent by the ſpace of a yeare; <hi>(e)</hi> or in caſe the husband wil not keepe home after three
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22753:46"/>
admonitions, the mariage may lawfully be diſſolued, and other partie new mate himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> alſo aboue mentioned, well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth of all the foreſaid cauſes,<note place="margin">Luther commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in 1. Cor. c. 7. an. 1523. &amp; in lib. de cauſis matrim. an. 1530.</note> and further affirmeth, that in caſe the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band perſwade the wife, or the wife the husband to any ſinne; in caſe a rich wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man marrie a poore man, &amp; her friends diſlike the match; and in caſe the man and the wife brawle and ſcould, and cannot liue peaceably together, the marriage may be diſſolued, and either partie free to marrie againe.</p>
               <p>If after marriage conſummate either partie,<note place="margin">Bucer de regno Chriſti. &amp;c. l. 2. c, 42.</note> by meanes of ſome incurable diſeaſe cannot performe the marriage duties, the ſound or able partie, may be lawfully married to an other. So <hi>Bucer</hi> aboue mentioned. Againe.</p>
               <p>If the wife be ſo hurt in bearing chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that afteward she cannot indure the companie of her husband, it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plaine caſe, that the man may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie take a new wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in like maner may the wife ſerue the husbande, if he chance to hurt his <hi>Virgam viril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> Againe.</p>
               <p>In caſe either partie be a witch, or a murtherer, or a Church-robber,<note place="margin">Idem vt ſupra c. 37. 38. 39 &amp;c.</note> or a fauourer of thieues, or a receiuer of ſtolne goods, or a periured perſon, or in caſe either partie laye violent handes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22753:47"/>
vpon the other,<note place="margin">Ibid. cap. 26. 27. 28. 29. 30 &amp;c.</note> or in caſe the husband doe but beate his wife, the marriage may be diſſolued, and either partie be at libertie to marrie againe; yea, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cannot finde in his hart to loue his wife, and vſe her according to the rules of coniugal charitie,<note place="margin">See Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers workes entituled <hi>De regno Chriſti;</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of which you shall find theſe &amp; infinite other praiſes.</note> is ſtrictly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and enioyned by God, to put her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie and marrie an other.</p>
               <p>Hereunto <hi>Martin Bucer;</hi> whom the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Church acknowledgeth for one of her prime Apoſtles; <hi>Crinaeus</hi> for an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and ſupreminent diuine; <hi>Caluin</hi> for a moſt faithfull doctor of Chriſts Church; Sir <hi>Iohn Cheeke,</hi> for a moſt vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raleld maſter, both in humanitie and diuinitie, and the Vniuerſitie of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge for a moſt diuine man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">See Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. an. 745. n. 27</note>Againe in the ſame age, as <hi>Adelbertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> derided thoſe that went on Pilgrimage to Rome, to viſite the holy ſepulchers of the Apoſtles, &amp; other glorious mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo doe all Proteſtants; And as the Albanenſes, heretically contend that vſurie was lawful, ſo do<note n="*" place="margin">Caluin in epiſt. 345. cuius initium diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior fuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem. edit. Geneuae. an. 1575. Bucer in cap. 5. Mat. Hutter in 2. part. reſp. &amp;c. in praef. ad confratres.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluin, Bucer,</hi> &amp; other chiefe Proteſtants; yea this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine paſſed for ſuch currant diuinitie in Geneua, that two Miniſters were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished thence, for maintaining the contrarie, as <hi>Hutter</hi> a Proteſtant writer witneſſeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:22753:47"/>Laſtly, not to inſiſt any longer exactly on particulars as <hi>Godiſcaldus, Beringarius,</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes, Albanenſes, Iohn Witcliffe,</hi> and other in following ages,<note place="margin">See con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. c. 3. Concil Roman ſub Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. 7. an. 1079. Concil. 11. gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale. an. 1170. Concil. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienſe. an. 1415. Concil Florenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. an. 1431. Conciliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Trident. an. 1546.</note> heretically taught (as may appeare in the * councels and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of that time) that Chriſt was not really preſent in the Sacrament; that the Maſſe was a Sacrifice of diuels; that the Saints could not heare our prayers; that the feſtiuals of Saints, were not to be obſerued; that the Aue Maria was not to be ſaid; that Auricular Confeſsion was not to be vſed; that Indulgences were of no power; that there was no Purgatorie; that there was no merit in faſting; that the Church wrought no true miracles; that all the Eccleſiaſticall benedictions of Water, Bread, Wine, were to be reiected; that Confirmation was no Sacrament; that the Bishop of Rome was not the head of the Church; that the Church of Rome, was the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Sathan, &amp;c. So doe all ſorts of Caluinian Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Whence, if a little* <hi>leauen</hi> be ſufficient to marre the whole paſte; or as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> expoundeth theſe wordes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, if one errour may corrupt the whole maſſe of Faith, what an OLLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POTREDO or Gallimafrie, may wee iudge Proteſtancie to be, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of all the fore mentioned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereſies,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22753:48"/>
moſt of which were raked out of hels botomleſſe abiſſe, after they had bene condemned thether, for more then a thouſand yeares before, and the reſt, deuiſed in latter ages, by perſons which the Proteſtants cannot denie to haue bene deſperate heretikes. If I ſay one errour be ſufficient to corrupt the whole maſſe of Faith, as the Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth; if he that offendeth in one, is made guiltie of all,<note place="margin">Iames 1. v. 10.</note> as S. IAMES con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth; if one ſingular doctrinall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour obſtinatly defended, make an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike,<note place="margin">Luther tom. 2. de votis fol. 272. &amp; tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Witt. Lat. in c. 17. Mat. fol. 74. Schluſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg. in Theolog. Caluin. art. 1.</note> and euery heretike be certainly damned, as both <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Scluſſelberg</hi> auouch; what a monſtrous corrupt maſſe is Proteſtancie, and what guiltie and hereticall wretches are all Proteſtants, who defend not one, ten, or twentie, but many ſcores, I may ſay, many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of accurſed hereſies?</p>
               <p>If any man doth not ANATHEMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIZE <hi>Arrius, Eunomius, Marcedonius, Apollina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Neſtorius, &amp;c.</hi> with their wicked wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and all other heretikes which are condemned by the Church, and thoſe who <hi>teach as they did,</hi> and remaine in their impieties, let him be accurſed of God, ſaith the ſixt general Councel. Accurſe therefore (Chriſtian reader, accurſe (I ſay) theſe hereticall Proteſtants; theſe new ſowers of old condemned hereſies;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:22753:48"/>
theſe late reuiued <hi>Simonians, Corinthians, Nouatise, Arrians, Aerians, Euſtachians, Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius, Neſtorians</hi> &amp;c. leſſe in not accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, thou they ſelfe ſtand accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of God.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle biddeth vs in any caſe to auoid an hereticall man, after two or three admonitions, and not to ſay vnto him ſo much as <hi>Aue,</hi> or <hi>God ſaue you;</hi> now that the Proteſtants are manifoldly he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, hath bene abundantly prooued, auoid them therefore as much as may be, haue no commerſe with them, at leaſt in ſpirituall affaires, leſſe by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with them, in this life thou be forced to accompanie them in the next alſo, in the lake that burneth with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:22753:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER III.</hi> That the Proteſtants (eſpecially thoſe of the Caluinean ſect) beleeue aright, no one Article of the Apoſtles Creede: Euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie proued out of their beſt Doctors, and their owne mutual confeſsions.</head>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE I. I beleeue in God the Father Almightie, maker of Heauen and Earth.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt to beleue a right in God (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to expreſſe<note n="*" place="margin">One Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, one God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of al, &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 4.5.</note> Scripture, and the NICENE<note n="(b)" place="margin">The Father is God, the Sonne is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, and yet there are not three Gods, but one God, &amp;c. For as we are compelled by the Chriſtian veritie, to confeſſe each perſon to be God and Lord, ſo are we forbidden by the Catholike Religion, to ſay three Gods and three Lords.</note> CREED) is to teach and profeſſe that there is but one God only, and not a pluralitie of Gods; but many <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Zanchie</hi> wrote a booke which he entituled, <hi>de tribus Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him</hi> that is, of the three Gods, concerning which, ſee <hi>Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no-Turciſmum, Gulielmi Rainoldi l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5 <hi>fol</hi> 449. <hi>edit.</hi> 1603. <hi>Caluin</hi> affirmeth that God the Father is God <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> by an excellencie and exceſſe, and that Chriſt is his Fathers <hi>Vicar</hi> or <hi>Vicegerent,</hi> &amp; hath a power ſecondarie or next vnto the Father. <hi>Coment. in cap.</hi> 22. <hi>Mat. v.</hi> 44. <hi>&amp; in cap.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. <hi>&amp; in cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Marci</hi> 2. 19. <hi>&amp; in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 15. <hi>&amp; contra Gentile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Protheſi.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp; in confeſ. ca.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; lib</hi> 1. <hi>Inſt. cap.</hi> 13. <hi>u.</hi> 23. See <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uardentius</hi> in <hi>Theomach. Caluin. l</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 15. The generalitie alſo of Proteſtant Doctors, both Lutherans and Calueniſts (as shal be shewed in the ſecond Article) maintaining that Chriſts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature or Godhead is ſubiect and inferior to the Father, whence it neceſſarily followeth, that either Chriſt is not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely God, or that he is a diſtinct &amp; inferior God to God the Father, and conſequently that there are more Gods then one.</note> Proteſtant Doctors plainely teach, that there is a pluralitie of Gods; and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22753:49"/>
the beſt eſteemed and moſt Apoſtolical amongſt them, maintaine<note n="(d)" place="margin">The word of God doth plainly teach vs, that this diuine Eſſence, is truely, really, indeed, and from Eternitie diſtinct in the three perſons. <hi>Beza in Confeſſ Gallie a puncto</hi> 1 <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>Luther</hi> alſo (the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Apoſtle and Euangeliſt) &amp; <hi>Melancton (Caluins</hi> neuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended diuine) affirme that there be three diuinities, as there be three perſons. <hi>Luther apud Zwingliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. tom.</hi> 2 <hi>reſp. ad Lutheri l de ſacramento. fol.</hi> 474. <hi>&amp;</hi> Melancton <hi>in locis communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus edi. Baſil. c. de Chriſto,</hi> In like maner the confeſſion of the English Church ſaith as followeth, <hi>The diuine nature, which we call God, is diuided into three coequal perſons.</hi> In Harmo. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes. And <hi>Caluin</hi> is confident, that if God the Father did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate his Eſſence to his Sonne, that either he hath no Eſſence him ſelfe, or but halfe an Eſſence, &amp; condemneth it as an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his aduerſarie, in that he ſaid, <hi>The Father gaue to his Sonne that very ſubſtance which he had, the ſame and no other.</hi> Caluin <hi>contra Valintin Gentilum. p.</hi> 916. <hi>&amp;</hi> 917. <hi>&amp;</hi> 912 <hi>&amp; in Actis Serueti. p.</hi> 249. 250. 871. 872. and the like is affirmed by <hi>Skeggius</hi> in <hi>Genebra. p.</hi> 98 <hi>&amp;</hi> 108. See <hi>Caluino-Turciſ l.</hi> 3 <hi>c</hi> 5.</note> that in the three perſons of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, there be three <hi>Diuinities,</hi> three <hi>eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tial differences,</hi> three diſtinct <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>eſſences;</hi> which is all one (as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>George Paule, Caſſenouius,</hi> and other bewitched of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentine Gentile,</hi> doe write that the three perſons or <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> haue three <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> or Eſſences, whence they neceſſarilie teach, that there be three Gods. So Beza, <hi>lib. de vnitate eſſent. in confeſ. fidei cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. And <hi>Zwinglius</hi> in his anſwere to <hi>Luther,</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that the <hi>Diuinitie is three-fold,</hi> or of three kindes, ſaith, Hence it neceſſarily followeth, that there are three natures (in the diuinitie) and three Gods. Zwinglius <hi>vt ſupra.</hi> And the like is affirmed by <hi>Stankarus lib de trinitate apud Guliel. Rainol. in Caluino-Turciſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> confeſſe) as to teach that there be three Gods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:22753:50"/>Secondly to beleeue in God aright (according to the foreſaid NICENE CREED<note n="(f)" place="margin">The Catholike faith is this, that we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one God in Trinitie, and the Trinitie in vnitie. &amp;c.</note> is to adore one God in Trinitie, and the Trinitie in vnitie: but the chiefe Proteſtant<note n="g" place="margin">In a Synod of Caluinſts at <hi>Vilna</hi> an. 1589. May 11. It was by publike decree prohibited, for Miniſters to vſe any more the word <hi>Trinitie</hi> in their Sermons, becauſe it was not founde in the ſacred Scriptures. See <hi>Schluſſelberg in Theologia Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtica. lib</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 326. <hi>Danaus</hi> termeth this prayer (holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, one God haue mercie on vs) a foolish madde, and vnioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted prayer, euilly inuented by the Fathers, and moſt dangerous. Danaeus <hi>apud Feuardentium in theomachia.</hi> Caluin. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>errore</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 13. <hi>Ochinus</hi> calleth theſe diuine names <hi>(God infinite, God in the trinitie of perſons)</hi> monſtrous, Sathanicall, &amp; vnknowne to the Prophets and Apoſtles; <hi>Caluin</hi> wiſheth that the word <hi>(Trinitie)</hi> were buried; <hi>Muſculus</hi> plainly ſaith, that he would not confeſſe the three diuine perſons before the heathen, leſſe he might be thought to ſay, that there were three Gods. And <hi>Luther</hi> blotted out of the Roman Liturgie, the foreſaid pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (<hi>the holy Trinitie one God, &amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Feuard.</hi> as aboue, fol. 9. &amp; 10. 13. In a Synode at <hi>Petriconio</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi> an. 1565. The Caluinian Miniſters there aſſembled, reiected the decree of the Nicene councel, and affirmed that they would rather ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Arrian Synode. See <hi>Caluino-Turiciſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c</hi> 4. And <hi>Danaeus</hi> in his <hi>cenſuram magiſtrum ſentent. diſt.</hi> 12. <hi>reſp. ad Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrard. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Caluin</hi> was much offended with the word <hi>Trinitie</hi> (ſaith <hi>Petrus Carolus,</hi> one of his owne brethren <hi>in actis colloq. Lauſanenſ.</hi>) and the reſt of the Proteſtants confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently teaching<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that nothing is neceſſarily to be beleeued, that cannot expreſly be found in Scripture, cannot but ioyne with theſe formerly recited. See <hi>Caluino-Turciſ l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 116. 117. <hi>&amp;</hi> 43.</note> Doctors, both Lutherans and Caluiniſts, cannot away with the word TRINITY, and ioyntly condemne this forme of prayer <hi>(Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie one God haue mercie vppon vs)</hi> as foolish, madde, vnioynted, barbarous, moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and euilly inuented by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:22753:50"/>Thirdly to beleeue a right in God, is to teach and maintaine, according to Gods expreſſe word in holy Scripture; <note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 5 v. 5.</note> that God willeth no wickedneſſe; <note n="(i)" place="margin">Eccleſ. 15. v. 21.</note> that God commaundeth no man to doe wickedly;<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iames 1 v. 13.</note> that God tempteth no man;<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 24. v. 10. &amp; pſal. 83. v. 11</note> that all the wayes of God are mercie and truth;<note n="(m)" place="margin">Oſee 1. v. 9.</note> that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction commeth from our ſelues; <note n="(n]" place="margin">2. Pet 3. v. 9. &amp; 1. Tim. 2. v. 4.</note> that God would haue no man pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and the like.</p>
                  <p>But the Caluin-proteſtants doe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, &amp; with great confidence, teach; <note n="(o)" place="margin">Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. lib. 1. Inſtit. c. 18. n. 4.</note> that God forceth men to doe what is not lawful for them;<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ibid. n. 1.</note> that God cauſed ABSOLON to pollute by inceſt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bed;<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ibid. 7 cap. 14. n, 2. &amp; Whitaker <hi>apud Duraeum ration.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 214. 217. <hi>&amp; Bucer in Rom. c.</hi> 9.</note> that God put into the hart of DAVID, to number the people;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:22753:51"/>
that God doth not only permit men to fall into errour by forſaking them,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> but ſeduceth, hardeneth, deliuereth into a reprobate ſence, and ſendeth a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful errour to make men do ſuch a thing; <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſet forth with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge. p. 46.</note> that the moſt wicked perſons that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were, were of God appointed to be wicked, euen as they were;<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor de Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt.</hi> c. 1. p. 105. 166. 167.</note> that ſinnes through Gods decree, are vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoydable;<note n="(u)" place="margin">Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie lib. de natura Dei p. <hi>688</hi> &amp; Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceherus in catena aure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> p. <hi>36.</hi>
                     </note> that though God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his reuealed will in the Law, would haue all men ſaued, yet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods hidden and ſecreet power he would not haue all men ſaued;<note n="(x)" place="margin">Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor de pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>133. 134. 138.</hi>
                     </note> that though he commanded all men to repent, yet he would not haue them ſo to doe;<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ibid. c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>261.</hi>
                     </note> that God in promiſe offereth his grace to many, which yet he neuer meaneth to performe;<note n="[z]" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. cap.</hi> 4 <hi>p.</hi> 304. See alſo Caluin l. 3. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. c. 24. n. 13.</note> that God ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly calleth the reprobate to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and yet preciſely he would not haue them repent; that Chriſt called the Iewes to repentance, as he was man, but not as he was God, and the like: By which they make God the author of all ſinnes, an hypocrite, a deceiuer, and a moſt wicked tyrant, and conſequently are ſo farre from beleeuing a right in God, as that by their doctrines they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22753:51"/>
transforme him into a diuel, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate and worship him, as <hi>Schluſſelberg</hi> a famous Lutheran Doctor affirmeth in theſe words.</p>
                  <p>The Sacramentaries make God the author and producer of all ſinnes,<note place="margin">Schluſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg in Theologia Caluini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica. art. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>113.</hi>
                     </note> but we know not this God, but doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirme, that the diuel is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, moouer, forcer, and producer of al ſinnes and iniuſtice, therefore the god, whom the Caluiniſts adore and inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate is the diuel. So their brother <hi>Schluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelberg.</hi> And the like is affirmed by <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Nicolaus, Caſtalio,</hi> and other, as shall be shewed in the laſt chapter of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE II. And in IESVS CHRIST his only Sonne our LORD.</head>
                  <p>THe Proteſtants beleeue not aright in IESVS CHRIST the Sonne of the Eternall Father, is alſo abundantly manifeſt.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, wheras according to the NICENE<note n="*" place="margin">There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right faith is, that we beleeue and confeſſe, that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, is God and Man; God of the ſubſtance of his Father, begotten before the world, and Man of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Mother, borne in the world, perfect God, and perfect man, &amp;c. In ſymbolo Athanaſij.</note> CREED, to beleeue aright</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:22753:52"/>For firſt, where as according to the NICENE CREED, to beleeue a right in Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne, is to beleeue that he was begotten of the ſubſtance of his Father, &amp; that he <hi>is Deus de Deo,</hi> God of God. The chiefe doctors of Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie teach;<note n="[b]" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea odit</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. my ſoule hateth the word <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial,</hi> and the Arrians did verie well in exacting, that it might not be lawfull, to place that prophane and new voice among the rules of faith. So Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. tom. 2. Witt. Latt. an. 1551. fol. 252. <hi>Filius non eſt genitus de ſubſtantia patris,</hi> The Sonne is not begotten of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Father, ſaith Beza <hi>contra</hi> Heſhuſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Fathers in the Nicene Councell affirmed, that Chriſt is God of God, yet Caluin inuincibly prooueth that Chriſt is God of himſelfe; the Fathers in the Nicene Councel teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt was conſubſtantiall to his Father, ſpoyled Chriſt of his diuinitie. So Whitaker <hi>contra</hi> Campianum. pag. 153. the Papiſts blaſpheme in ſaying, that Chriſt is not <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>God of himſefe.</hi> So Powel <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Antichriſto. cap.</hi> 8. and the like is affirmed by Willet in Synopſ. pag. 610. and Danaeus <hi>contra</hi> Bellarm. parte 1. <hi>ad controuerſ.</hi> 2. c. 19. out of Caluin l. 1. Inſtit. c. 13. n. 23. and Beza <hi>contra</hi> Heſhuſium, and other prime Proteſtants. See Caluino-Turciſ. l. 3. c. 7. and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardentius in Theomach. Cal. lib. 3. f. 73. 74. and Iacob Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier in Conograph. tabula ſaec. 4. cap. 3. &amp; 12. in collat.</note> that the Eſſence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot be communicated to the Sonne, &amp; that Chriſt was <hi>God of himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, the ſaid<note n="(c)" place="margin">The diuinitie of the Father, Sonne &amp; Holie Ghoſt is equall, their Maieſtie coeternall, &amp;c.</note> Fathers affirme, that to beleeue a right in Chriſt, is to profeſſe that he was equall to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to his Diuinitie; but the Proteſtants Arrianizing teach,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:22753:52"/>
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">It is a moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, and diuiliſh thing to ſay, that Chirſt is not our Mediatour, as he is God. So Caluin. <hi>in tract. theolog. p.</hi> 941. 945. And further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding that of the firſt to the Corinthians cap. 15. v. 28. <hi>(then the Sonne shall alſo be ſubiect vnto him)</hi> He vnderſtandeth it of Chriſts diuine nature, Caluin. l. 2. Inſt. c. 14. n. 3. &amp; in his Epiſtle to the Polonians (pag. 941.) he affirmeth that it is not abſurd to graunt, that the Sonne is inferiour to the Father, &amp; that according to his diuinitie he maketh interceſsion. Whence <hi>Stankarus</hi> a brother of his, inferreth ſaying. <hi>Caluin</hi> with <hi>Arrius,</hi> and <hi>Arrius</hi> with <hi>Caluin</hi> doe very well agree, in that they both make the Sonne of God in his diuine nature, to doe the office of a Miniſter, a Biſhop, and Mediator. <hi>Stanka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus lib. de Trinitate v.</hi> 2. See <hi>Caluino-Turciſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. Againe. It is Concluded ô <hi>Caluin,</hi> that thy doctrine touching the Son of God, is plainly <hi>Arian,</hi> from which I pray you to depart aſſoone as may be. <hi>Stankarius contra miniſtros Genuenſ. &amp; Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur, fol.</hi> 123. Chriſt according to his diuine nature, was a Prieſt and offered Sacrifice. So <hi>Fulke</hi> in his Retentiue. pag. 89. and againſt the Rhemeſe teſtament. Heb. 5.6. ſect. 4. Chriſt is our Mediatour, Redeemer, King, &amp;c. not according to one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, either humaine or diuine; but according to both natures. So the Lutherans in their booke of concord. p. 736. <hi>art. de perſona Chriſts. Melancton</hi> alſo teacheth, that Chriſts diuine nature was obedient to his Father. <hi>in locis commun. an.</hi> 1558. <hi>loco de filio;</hi> The Vniuerſitie of Oxford in their late Veſpers, publickly maintained, <hi>That Chriſt was our Mediator according to both natures.</hi> See their act queſtions. 10. Iulij an. 1619. Reſp. <hi>Th. Winnefe.</hi> And the like is affirmed and taught in all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches, if <hi>Beza</hi> may be credited, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Haec (ſc. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe mediatorem ſecundum diuinam naturam diſtincte conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratam) eſt noſtrarum Eccleſiarum fides, &amp;c</hi> That Chriſt is our Mediator, according to his diuine nature diſtinctly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is the beleefe of all our Churches touching Chriſt our Mediator, which we doe not doubt to be conformablie to the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles. <hi>Beza</hi> Epiſt. 28.</note> that Chriſt was in feriour to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to his diuine nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:22753:53"/>We farther finde in the ſame Nicene <note n="*" place="margin">In like maner the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, the Sonne is omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and the holie Ghoſt is omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, &amp;c. Equall to his Father, according to his diuinitie, &amp;c.</note> Creed, that to beleeue a right in Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne, is to acknowledge that the Sonne is omnipotent, as well as the Father; that he is both God and Man; that he is but one perſon and the like: but the Caluino-proteſtants teach, <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Caluin</hi> l. 1. Inſtit. c. 13. n. 23. 24. plainly ſeuering the perſon of the Mediator from Chriſts diuine perſon, doth together with <hi>Beza (contra Pappum</hi> pag. 7.) and othar Caluiniſts main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine two perſons in Chriſt, the one humaine, and the other diuine, which is Neſtorianiſme; and the Lutherans in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating the proprieties of the diuine nature to his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, confound the two natures in Chriſt, which is Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme. Whence <hi>Beza (in praefat. contra Brentium)</hi> inferreth that the Lutherans are Eutichians, and <hi>Philippus Nicolaus (lib. cui titulus fundamentum Caluinianae ſectae cum veteribus Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorianis &amp; Arrianis, detectio)</hi> contendeth that the Caluiniſts are Neſtorians, and ſo both heretikes by their owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. See <hi>Feuardentium in Theomach. Caluin. l.</hi> 3. <hi>fol</hi> 81. 82. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra haereſ.</hi> 10. 11. <hi>&amp; Gualter in tabula cronograph. ſaec.</hi> 5 <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>in collat.</hi>
                     </note> that he had two perſons, the one hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, &amp; the other diuine;<note n="(g)" place="margin">It is euident that ignorance was common to Chriſt with the Angels, ſo Caluin. har. in Mat. c. 24. v. 36. Yea further, that Chriſts ſoule was as ſubiect to ignorance, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens, and that this was the only difference, that our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities are of neceſſitie his voluntarie. har. in Luke 2. v 40. that in particular he knew not the day of iudgement, not what that tree was which he curſed Harmon. in Mat. 24.36 &amp;c. 21. v. 18. <hi>Marlorat</hi> alſo expounding the foreſaid places of Scripture conſenteth with Caluin, and affirmeth that all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Doctors be of the ſame opinion. Marlorat. in Mat 9. &amp; Luke 2. <hi>Gallaſius (Bezas</hi> colleague in the Geneua Church) affirmeth, that Chriſt was ſo ignorant, that he needed inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as well as other men. annot in Irenaeum l. 2. c. 49. The foreſaid <hi>Caluin</hi> farther affirmeth, that Chriſt was touched with a vitious affection; that in his prayers he held not a well proportioned couſe; that his prayer in the Garden was not Meditated; that in a maner he wauered in his vowes; that hee forgot that he was ſent hether on that condition, to be our Redeemer, yea, that he refuſed and detrected as much as in him lay, the office of a Redeemer. Caluin. Harmon. in Marke 14.36. &amp; in Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. d. 4. &amp; ad Roman. c. 9. v. 3. &amp; in Mat. c. 26. v. 34. See Caluino-Turciſ l. 3. c. 13.</note> that he was ſubiect to ignorance and vicious
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22753:53"/>
affections;<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Petrus Richeus,</hi> whome <hi>Beza (in (h) Iconibus</hi> ſtileth a man of rare pietie &amp; learning, &amp; <hi>Danaeus</hi> an other famous Proteſtant Doctor, publikely taught, that Chriſt was not to be adored, becauſe his godhead was ioyned with his manhood, which [in the Caluiniſts opinion) cannot be adored without Idolatrie. Yea <hi>Richeus</hi> affirmed, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſaid that Chriſt was neceſſarily to be adored, was an heretike. He blotted out alſo in the Primers or common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er bookes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this appendix vſually added to euery Pſalme, <hi>Glorie be to the Father, the Sonne, and holy Ghoſt</hi>) And <hi>Danaeus</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him accurſed of God, that adored the flesh of Chriſt; though hypoſtatically ioyned to the Sonne of God. See Feuardentius in theomach. Caluin. lib. 3. fol. 82. 83. contra hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. 22. &amp; 13. cap. 9. &amp; <hi>Schluſſelberg.</hi> in Theolog. Caluiniſt. art. 29. p. 150. and <hi>Caluino-Turciſ</hi> l. 3. c. 9.</note> that he is not in any caſe to to be adored<note n="(i)" place="margin">See <hi>Feuardentius</hi> in Theomach. Caluiniſtica lib. 1. fol. 35. &amp; 36. and <hi>Schluſſelberg</hi> in Theolog. Cal. art. 3. pag. 12; that this doctrine againſt Chriſts omnipotencie, might be the more vniuerſally beleeued, the Caluinian Miniſters in their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme printed at Geneua an. 1563. <hi>per Franciſum Duron,</hi> and diuulged through out all France, ſuppreſſed the word <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent,</hi> and left it out of the Apoſtles Creed, as the foreſaid <hi>Feuardentius</hi> affirmeth. l. 1. p. 36. <hi>vt ſupra.</hi>
                     </note> and as touching his omnipotencie, they are ſo farre from
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22753:54"/>
beleeuing it, that they plainly affirme it as blaſphemous doctrine in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, to giue God abſolute power; that the Angel Gabriels ſpeech <hi>(no word is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible to God)</hi> is not vniuerſally to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, nor to be beleeued; that God cannot make a bodie exiſt without his dimenſions; that God cannot make a a Camel or Cable rope paſſe through the eye of a needle; that thoſe thinges are impoſsible to God which were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene, nor neuer about to be; that God can effect nothing aboue or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the order in nature by him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; and that neither God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor the Sonne, with all their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, can bring to paſſe, that Chriſts body may ſubſtantially be preſent in manie places at once, or in any other place but in heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE III. Which was conceiued by the Holy Ghoſt; borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin MARIE.</head>
                  <p>IN the third Article, which treateth of Chriſts Conception and Natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, neither Lutheran nor Caluinian Proteſtant can be ſaid to beleeue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:22753:54"/>For firſt the Lutherano-proteſtants with one conſent, teach and maintaine <note n="*" place="margin">Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rani in concordia referente Iurgieui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio in bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo quinto Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij anno <hi>1602.</hi> quar. A. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> that the humaine nature, is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where, whence it muſt needes follow (ſaith <hi>Iurgiewicius</hi>) that it could not be conceiued and borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marie alone; for if preſently after the Incarnation, it was euery where, ſurely it was in the wombes of al both men and women; neither could Chriſt in that ſence be euer ſaid to be borne of the Virgin MARIE. For to be borne of a woman, is no other then to goe out of her wombe, but he that is euery where, cannot be ſaid to goe from place to place, or euer ſo to go out of the wombe as that at the ſame inſtant he remaine not there.</p>
                  <p>Secondly the Caluino<note n="(b)" place="margin">Reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Popiſh fictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Chriſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly paſſed through the Virgins wombe, wee ſay and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that he went out and was borne naturally, the obſtacles being broken, and the places opened, and that the Virgin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſupernaturally gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with childe, was deliuered naturally. So <hi>Molinaeus in vniou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 4. <hi>Euang. part.</hi> 3. And the like is affirmed by <hi>Martin Bucer in dialogo de corpore Chriſti. fol.</hi> 94. <hi>Caluin</hi> alſo enquiring what time paſſed betweene Chriſts natiuitie and flight into Egypt, anſwereth that it ſeemed to him verie probable, that it was not preſently, but long after, and that God ſpared Marie, till ſhe had well recouered her weakneſſe in child-bearing, that ſo ſhe might the better take her iournie. <hi>Caluin. Harmon. in cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Mat. v.</hi> 13.</note> Proteſtants generally teach, that the B. Virgin MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE was not onely ſubiect to the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:22753:55"/>
of other women great with childe, but alſo that she was not a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at that inſtant when our Sauiour was borne, which is contrarie to the doctrine of the Catholike<note n="(c)" place="margin">If by Chriſts natiuitie, the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie or ſoundnes of Marie his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould haue bin corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hee could not now be ſaid to haue bin borne of a Virgin. and ſo the whole Church ſhould make a falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. <hi>Auguſtine in Euchirid cap.</hi> 34.</note> Church, and the plaine deniall of this third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</p>
                  <p>They alſo<note n="[d]" place="margin">The Monkes &amp; Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prieſts, and Popiſh Doctors, doe erre in vrging the merit of Chriſts incarnation, natiuitie, temptations, and afflictions; for theſe had profited nothing, but only the death of Chriſt, that only was acceptable for the expiation of ſinnes. So <hi>Moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus in har. Euang.</hi>
                     </note> teach that Chriſts nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie and incarnation were not merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; yea ſome Caluiniſts (as<note n="[e]" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sarcerius</hi> in concione de feſto natiuitatis.</note> 
                     <hi>Sarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> writeth) do vtterly deny that Chriſt tooke flesh of the Virgin MARY, but that he made him ſelfe a certaine body of the foure elements, &amp; paſſed through her wombe, as water through a channel, <note n="[f]" place="margin">
                        <hi>Andreas Fricius</hi> lib. de mediatore in initio.</note> And <hi>Andreas Frizius</hi> a famous Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, doubteth not to profeſſe, that for his owne part he cannot ſee (if the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the three perſons be all one) how the Father should not be incarnate as well as the Sonne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE IIII. He ſuffered vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified dead &amp; buried.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:22753:55"/>COncerning Chriſts death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">Luther in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iori de coena do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, &amp; de concil parte. 2. fol. 276. &amp; fo. 554 tom. 3. Ger Ien. apud Zwingl. tom. 2. in reſp. ad Luther. fol. 458.</note> which is taught in the fourth Article, the Apoſtle of Proteſtancie ſaith as followeth; if in Chriſt the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature had only ſuffered for me, that Chriſt had bene a baſe and low-prized Sauiour, yea he had needed an other Sauiour to ſaue him ſelfe. So <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therani in lib. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae. art. de Chriſti perſona. an 1580. Caluin lib. 2. Inſt c. 16 n. 10 &amp; 11.</note> the Lutheria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s alſo in their booke of Concord, teach the ſame doctrine, ſaying; Chriſts whole perſon ſuffered for vs, was crucified, died, and deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell, is our Mediator, Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, King, &amp;c. not according to one nature, either humaine or diuine, but according to both natures; <hi>Caluin</hi> in like maner plainly affirmeth, that it had bene to no purpoſe, if Chriſt had only dyed a corporall death; that he indured in ſoule the torments of a damned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate man;<note n="(c)" place="margin">Idem harmon in Mat. c. 27. v. 49. &amp; 46. &amp; cap. 26. v. 39. &amp; Harmon. in Marke c. 14. v. 36.</note> that he was ſo vexed on all ſides, and ſo ouer-whelmed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation, that he ceaſed to call vpon God; that in his Paſsion, he ſpake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideratly and without Meditation; that he refuſed as much as in him laye, the office of a Redeemer;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Lib. 2. Inſt. ca. 17. num. 1.</note> and that if Chriſt had bene ſimplie and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe oppoſed to Gods iuſtice, there had bene no place of meriting, becauſe there
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22753:56"/>
could not be found in the man (Chriſt) any ſuch dignitie as might merit Gods fauour. So <hi>Caluin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeum. p. 24. 126. Simide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius theſi. 136. Seluece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futatione accuſatio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>num. fol. 192.</note>
                     <hi>Gerlachius</hi> auoucheth, that theſe are true propoſitions, <hi>The diuinitie is borne, crucified and dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Smidelinus</hi> alſo affirmeth, that both to <hi>ſuffer</hi> and to <hi>die,</hi> doe appertaine to diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
                  <p>Albeit (ſaith <hi>Selueccerus</hi>) that neuer to be indured phraſe <hi>(That Chriſt as he was God was not ſubiect to paſsion or ſuffering)</hi> doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten occurre in <hi>Theodoret,</hi> yet none of vs (Proteſtants) either may or ought to ſay that God did not ſuffer or die. So he. And<note n="*" place="margin">Teſte Czeca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio lib. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptis moribus pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum &amp; euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> art. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Muſculus</hi> an other great Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant publikely maintained againſt <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karus</hi> at Frankford, that Chriſts diuine nature or Godhead, both ſuffered and dyed together, with his body on the Croſſe, and cauſed <hi>Stankarus</hi> by a publike decree to be banished for holding the contrarie.</p>
                  <p>Now to ſay that Chriſts diuine nature ſuffered and died together with his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,<note place="margin">Zwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius tom 2. in reſp. ad Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theri co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. fol. 498.</note> or which is all one, to hold that God can ſuffer or die, what is it but to denie God? what more blaſphemous thing can be ſpoken (ſaith <hi>Zwinglius</hi>) then to ſay that God can ſuffer; why the verie Philoſophers themſelues held, that God was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> immortal, how then can
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:22753:56"/>
Chriſts diuine nature is paſsible (much more that it can die) is Arrianiſme,<note place="margin">Stanka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus l. de Trinitate &amp;c. quart d. 5. &amp; B. 1.</note> blaſphemie, atheiſme, &amp; the direct way to throw downe Chriſt, and the Holie Trinitie, from the throne of Maieſtie.</p>
                  <p>Againe to maintaine with <hi>Caluin</hi> that Chriſt died more then a corporal death and the like before mentioned, what <note n="*" place="margin">See Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino-Turciſ. l. 3. c. 13. p. 580. 581.</note> is it but to place him among accurſed ſinners, and deſperate wretches?</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, it is a receaued doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Caluine-proteſtants, <hi>That Chriſt died not for all men,</hi> and that by his death and Paſsion, he ſatisfied not for the ſinnes of the whole world, which the<note n="[c]" place="margin">Schluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelberg. in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſt. l. 1. art. 6.</note> Lutheran Proteſtants truly auow to be a moſt blaſphemous doctrine, and farther adde, that the maintainers there of, are worthy to be adiudged to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall flames.</p>
                  <p>Whence it abundantly followeth, that the Proteſtant Doctors, euen by their owne confeſsions teach moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly concerning Chriſts death and Paſsion, and therefore are very far from beleeuing a right, the fourth Article of the Apoſtles Creed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE V. He deſcended into hell, the third day he roſe againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:22753:57"/>COncerning the fift Article, which treateth of Chriſts deſcent into hell, and riſing againe from the dead whereas it is expreſly ſaid in the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, <hi>that he deſcended into hell after he was dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and buried:</hi> the Caluino-proteſtants ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally<note n="*" place="margin">Zwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius l. epiſt. 3. Oecola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius lib. 1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. p 4. Bucerus in c. 27. Mat. Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger coment. ſuper E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri. Hidel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bergenſ. Theologi in cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmo an. 36. 69 Caluin. l. 2. inſtit. c. 16. n. 8. 10. 11.</note> teach, that by his deſcent into hell, is meant that he ſuffered extreame torments on the Croſſe, and ſo either vtterly denie this Article, or confound it with the former.</p>
                  <p>Againe, whereas the Scripture plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith, <hi>Thou shalt not leaue my ſoule in hell;</hi> and, <hi>Thou haſt brought my ſoule out of hell,</hi> &amp;c. whence it may be euidently collected (as<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rogers in his Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacis of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles agreed vpon an. 1562. and 1609. art. 3. Bezas teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment printed an. 1556. 1558. &amp; 1598.</note> ſome chiefe Proteſtants acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) that his ſoule went downe into Hell; <hi>Beza</hi> in the tranſlation of the text readeth, <hi>Thou shalt not leaue my carcaſſe in the graue;</hi> and after<note n="(c)" place="margin">See t. 1. operum Bez. an. 1582. pag. 461.</note> giueth the reaſon of this wicked tranſlation to haue bene, becauſe <hi>the Papiſts wreſt this place to eſtablish their Limbus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreouer whereas all the<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Irenaeus</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>39.</hi> &amp; Euſaebius in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat. euang. <hi>l. 10.</hi> c <hi>8.</hi> &amp; Gregor, Nazianzene in oratione <hi>2</hi> in paſcha. &amp; Epiphanius haer. <hi>46.</hi> &amp; Ambroſe de Myſter. Paſchae c. <hi>4.</hi> Chryſoſtome hom. <hi>5.</hi> in demonſtrat. quod ſit Deus. Hierom in <hi>9.</hi> Zachariae &amp; epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> epitap. Nep &amp; Auguſt. l. <hi>20.</hi> de Ciuitate Dei c. <hi>15.</hi> &amp; epiſt. <hi>99.</hi> Cyrill in Iohn l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>36.</hi> Gregorie <hi>the great</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> epiſt. <hi>179.</hi> &amp; Paulinus in Panegerico Colſi. &amp;c.</note> Fathers
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:22753:57"/>
with one conſent out of the Scriptures, and this Article (as<note n="(e)" place="margin">Cal. l. 2. Inſt. c. 16. n. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Caluin</hi> him ſelfe confeſſeth) taught that Chriſt deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hel or Limbus, &amp; freed thence the Patriarkes and Prophets, and other true beleeuers, and after in his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, carried them with him triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phantly into heauen; the Proteſtants wil beleue no ſuch matter; yea they hold it a<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers <hi>vt ſupra.</hi> art. 3. pag. 17.</note> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish errour to affirme, that the Fathers which died vnder the Old Law, were shut vp in any ſuch place, as Limbo, and <note n="(g)" place="margin">That there is a hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt day, I am not yet well aſſured, and that there is a particular place, where now the ſoules of the damned are, as Painters ſet out, and bellie-ſlaues teach, is nought in my opinion. Luther tom. 3. Ien. Ger. fol. 212. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophorus Ireneus alſo in his booke entituled <hi>Speculum infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> cap. 9. affirmeth that the hell of the damned is not yet, but that God will make ſuch a place, at or after the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the Catechiſme of the diuines of Hidelberg. an. 63. &amp; 69. maketh a doubt whether there be any hell or not, or any place appointed for the wicked to be puniſhed in, after this life. See Schluſſelberg in theologia Caluin. art. 27.</note> many of them, and thoſe alſo of the chiefeſt note, make queſtion whether there be any ſuch locall place, as hell is affirmed to be by the Catholike Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, or whether there shall be any hell at all, till after doomes-day at the ſooneſt.</p>
                  <p>Againe, whereas this article expreſly ſaith, that Chriſt roſe from death, and the<note n="(h)" place="margin">I haue power to yeeld my life, and I haue power to take it againe. Ioh 10.18. The Sonne quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth whom he will. Iohn. 5.21. diſſolue this temple, and in three dayes I will raiſe it. Iohn. 2.19. Caluin in cap. 2. Iohn. &amp; in 8. ad Rom.</note> Scriptures adde, that he roſe by
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22753:58"/>
his owne power, as it muſt needes be, he being himſelfe God and equal to his Father, according to his diuine nature; <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, that it is abſurd to hold, that Chriſt did challenge to him ſelfe the glorie of his owne reſurrection, ſince the ſcripture ſaith, that it was the worke of God the Father; and<note n="[i]" place="margin">In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita Daeipa in portis neuſtriae. an. <hi>1564.</hi> teſte Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uardentio in theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machia Caluin. l. <hi>3.</hi> haer. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Franciſcus à San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto Paulo,</hi> a Miniſter at <hi>Deip,</hi> expounding that place of S. Paule (<hi>the God of peace which rayſed from death our great Paſtor. Heb.</hi> 13.20.) affirmed that Chriſt could not raiſe him ſelfe; and therefore it was neceſſarie that his Father should extend the arme of his vertue to that worke.</p>
                  <p>Further, the right beleefe of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, according to expreſſe<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 28. v. 2.</note> Scripture, and the ioynt<note n="(l)" place="margin">Hier. in 28. Mat. &amp; Hilar. l. 6.3. de Trinitate Cyrillus l. 12. in Ioan. ca. 59. &amp; 53. Chryſoſt. hom. 85. in Iohan. &amp; hom. 16. de reſurrectione. &amp; Auguſtine ſermon. 160. de clauſis Ianuis. &amp; alibi paſſim.</note> conſent of all auncient Catholike Doctors, is, that Chriſt in his reſurrection penetrated the ſtone, and arroſe, the ſepulcher, being shutte cloſe, as after he entred into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the doores being shut: but the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino-Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, leaſt hence they might be forced to confeſſe, that Chriſts bodie may as well be in many places at once, as that two bodies may be in one place, vtterly deny<note n="*" place="margin">See Schluſſelberg, artic. 31. p. 163. in Theolog, Caluin. l. 1.</note> this veritie, and ſay that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22753:58"/>
either he tumbled away the ſtone whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he roſe, or that ſome other rolled it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: yea Zwinglius (the Proteſtants ſainted confeſſor and Martir) dareth to ſay that<note n="(m)" place="margin">Zwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold. in Caluino-Turciſ. l. 3. c. 15. pag. 614. Beza A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. 2. ad Claud. de Xantes. p. 385 Confeſſ. Gallica. an. 1560. &amp; Conf. Belgica co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent 37. artic. quibus ſynodus Dordraci an. 1578 praecipit omnes Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtros ſubcribere. See Feuard. in Theolog. Cal. l. 6. cap. 1. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leil againſt D. Smith. fol. 28. 77. &amp; 140.</note> the groſſeſt Sargeant with his redde breeches, might haue gone out of the Monument in that maner as Chriſt did.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Beza is of opinion, that this Article <hi>(he deſcended into hell, and roſe againe the third day)</hi> crept by negligence into the Creed; yea the French &amp; Holland Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in the yeares 1569. and 1578. in the Confeſsion of their faith omitted this article, and <hi>Carliel</hi> in a booke prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at London an. 1582. calleth this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, a a Tale, an Errour, and a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hereſie.</p>
                  <p>From all which premiſes, it will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly follow, that the Proteſtants, eſpecially thoſe of the Caluinian ſect, cannot in any point be ſaid to beleeue a right this fift Article of the Apoſtles Creed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE VI. He aſcended into Heauen, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father Almightie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:22753:59"/>THe ſixt Article is, that Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended vp into heauen, and there ſitteth at the right hand of God; the true meaning of which Article, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the expreſſe word of God in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<note n="(b)" place="margin">See Hebrews 11. v. 13. 39. &amp;c. 9. v. 15. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 4.8. &amp; Pſal. 67. &amp; Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie 9.11. &amp; pſal 107. v. 16. See S. Thomas Aquinas 3. parte, q. 49. art. 5. &amp; q. 52 art. 5.</note> Scripture, &amp; the vniforme conſent of all the auncient<note n="[c]" place="margin">The blood of Chriſt is the Keye of Paradiſe, &amp;c. this is the land of the liuing which before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our Sauiour in fleſh, neither Abraham, nor Iſaac, nor Iacob, nor the Prophets, could obtaine, [according to that of S. Paule Heb. 9.15.] therefore he is the Mediator of the New Teſtament, &amp;c. So S. Hierome Epiſt. ad Dardanum. See alſo in Epiſt. ad Heliodorum, where he ſaith that before Chriſt Abraham was in hell, &amp;c. Reading the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, reading the Law, reading the Pſalmes, I neuer found the kingdome of heauen, but in the New Teſtament, becauſe, before Chriſt opened the gate of that kingdome, all the iuſt were detained in hell. So S. Chryſoſtome hom. 4. in Marcum. And the like is affirmed by the reſt of the Fathers. See Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe in c. 9. ad Hebr. &amp; Auguſtine ſer. 137. de Tempore. See in the former Article in d.</note> doctors, is, that Chriſt aſcending like a Conquerour, ledde with him the Sainctes of the Old Teſtament, who till then were detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in priſon, and firſt opened the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen to all beleeuers, and now ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father, that is to ſay, hath<note n="(d)" place="margin">So S. Athanaſius de confeſſ. eſſent. &amp; orat. 2. contra Arian. &amp; Damaſcene l. 4. de Orthodox fide c. 2. &amp; Cyrillus Hiaroſ. catech. 14.</note> equall power and authoritie with the Father, and that his humanitie in reſpect of his hypoſtatical<note n="(e)" place="margin">See Schluſſel. in theolog. Cal. art. 29. fol. 150. l. 4.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22753:59"/>
is to be adored; and that though he be ſtill locally in heauen, yet by his Omnipotencie, is alſo at the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant locally on<note n="(f)" place="margin">See Feuarde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius l. 6. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. Cal. c. 10.</note> earth, where the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his laſt Supper is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though it be in 10000. places at once: but the Proteſtants beſides that they generally deny, that he freed in his deſcent the Fathers ſoules out of LIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BO, as was before noted, doe alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly teach, that the Fathers were in heauen long before Chriſts Aſcention; and doe ſo incarcerate<note n="(g)" place="margin">See the ſame Feuard. l. 6 c. 6. &amp; Schluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelberg vt ſupra art. 2.</note> Chriſts glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied body (now triumphantly raigning in heauen) in a certaine place, as that by any meanes, he cannot be elſe where preſent, neither in heauen nor earth, contrarie to which the Lutherans as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roniouſly maintaine his Vbiquitarie preſence.</p>
                  <p>Againe the Caluino-proteſtants (for the better maintenance of their figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue preſence in the Euchariſt) teach that in Chriſts Aſcention vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, he did not penetrate but<note n="(h)" place="margin">See Feuardſt. as before cap 7.</note> breake the heauens, or elſe entred in by ſome great chinke or crennie; which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to<note n="(i)" place="margin">See Feuard. as before</note> Scripture, and doth infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly derogate from the power and vertue of Chriſt God and Man; and moſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly take from his glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, all priuiledges, gifts, and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22753:60"/>
and make it in all thinges, like one of ours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Caluin haer in Mat. cap. <hi>22.</hi> v. <hi>44.</hi> &amp; in cap. <hi>26.</hi> v. <hi>64.</hi> &amp; in cap. <hi>16.</hi> v. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note>Laſtly they vtterly denie, as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shewed, that any adoration is to be giuen to Chriſts humanitie; and by the right hand of God, they commonly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that Chriſt hath a place in heauen in dignitie, next his father. <hi>Seſsio ad dextram,</hi> &amp;c. the ſitting at the right hand (ſaith Caluin) is taken for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or next degre,<note place="margin">That all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants make Chriſt inferiour to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as touching his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head was formerly prooued in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</note> which the VICAIR of God doth occupie.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt is ſaid to ſit at the right hand of the Father, becauſe being made the Heigheſt King, he doth obtaine as it were the ſecond ſeate of honour and rule next vnto him, becauſe he is his VICAIR; again to ſitt at the right hand, is all one as to ſay the VICAIR of God. So Caluin Arianizing. And thus you ſee how farre the Proteſtants are from beleeuing a right the ſixt Article of the Apoſtles Creed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE VII. From thence he shall come to Iudge both the quicke and the dead.</head>
                  <p>THe ſeuenth Article is, touching Chriſts comming to Iudgement,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:22753:60"/>
which the doctors of proteſtancie many wayes depraue. For were as the ſacred Scriptures euery where affirme that all men shall be iudged according to their workes, and in particular treating of Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudgment, expreſſely ſay<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25 v. 34. 35. 36. 37. 38. &amp;c.</note> that Chriſt shall pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation againſt the wicked, becauſe they neglected to do the workes of charitie, ſuch as be to <hi>feede the hungrie, cloath the naked,</hi> harbour the harbourles and ſtranger, viſit the ſicke, to goe to men in priſon and the like; &amp; contrariwiſe, shal all the good to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioyes, for performing the ſaid mercifull workes; the Proteſtants gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally teach;<note n="(b)" place="margin">Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin in c. 27. Mat. v. 26. &amp; Beza in confeſſ. puncto 4. art. 12.</note> that it is vnpoſsible, at leaſt Chriſtian men neede not feare, that their works shal come into Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;<note n="(c)" place="margin">Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther l. de captiuit. Babilon. tom. 2. Witt. lat. fol. 78. &amp; Tindal in reuelat. antichriſt apud Fox in Acts p. 1337. and Whitak. de eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia contra Bellarm. controu. 2. 9. 4. and Smoutius in explicat. ſup. dominican oratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. p. 53. 54.</note> that no ſinne can condemne a Chriſtian or baptized man, but only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luther in cap. 3. ad Galath. tom. 1. Lat. Witt. fol. 348.</note> that all the ſinnes we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit are as properlie Chriſts, as if hee himſelfe had committed them;<note n="[e]" place="margin">Caluin. lib. 4. inſt. cap. 17. n. 2.</note> that beleeuing mens ſinnes can no more hurt them then Chriſt himſelfe;<note n="(f)" place="margin">Luther tom 1. in diſ p. f. 400. &amp; tom. 2. de abhominatione miſſae fol. 390. &amp; tom. 1. in fine 50. concluſ. fol. 54.</note> that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:22753:61"/>
Faith only doth ſaue vs,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tom. 1. Lat. Ien fol. 484. &amp; tom. 1. Ger. Wit in 2. Gal fol 47. &amp; 92. See before Chap. 2. pag.</note> &amp; that this Faith muſt be without the leaſt workes.</p>
                  <p>Againe wee finde in<note n="(h)" place="margin">Luke 24.39.40 &amp; Iohn. 20.27.28</note> Scripture, that Chriſt roſe from death with the fiue woundes, which he receiued on the Croſſe; and the ſame<note n="(i)" place="margin">Acts 1.11.</note> Scripture elſe where affirmeth, that he shall ſo come to iudgement, as he aſcended vp into heauen. The Catholike<note n="(k)" place="margin">So S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome Theoptilact. Cyrill. of Alex. comment. in Acts. 1. v. 11. So S. Athanaſius in Epiſt. ad Epitetetum, Ignatius in epiſt. ad Smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſes; Auguſtine tract. 121. in Iohn; Ambroſe l 10. in Lucam. Hilarie l. 3. de Trinitate; Leo Magnus ſer. 1. de aſcens. &amp; Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine ſer. 6. &amp; 7. de aſcenſione &amp; ſer. 49. &amp; 146. de tempore, &amp; li. 2. de ſymbolo. c. 7. &amp; epiſt. 146. See Feuardentius in theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. Cal. l. 6. c. 11. errore 17. Caluin in c. 24. Lucae.</note> Church alſo euer taught and beleeued, that Chriſt shall haue the ſcarres of his woundes appearing in his body, when he commeth to iudgement; but Caluin ſaith that it is a foolish and old wiues dotage, to beleeue that Chriſt shal haue the markes of his woundes when he commeth to iudgement.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, for a Iudge to force a man to do euill, &amp; after to punish him for it, all men muſt needs acknowlegd to be horrible iniuſtice and tyrannie. Now the<note n="*" place="margin">See the firſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</note> Caluino-Proteſtants, generally teaching (as was before shewed in the firſt Article) that God doth not only permitt,<note place="margin">See alſo in the laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> but predeſtinate all our acts whatſoeuer; that the moſt wickedſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22753:61"/>
that euer were, were of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be wicked; and that the ſinnes which men commit through the force of Gods decree, are altogether vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoidable; it muſt needes follow accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their doctrine; that Chriſt (whom they should acknowledge to be God, and conſequently goodnes and Iuſtice it ſelfe) either will not come to Iudge both the quicke and the dead, or that in adiudging any to hell, he is a moſt tyrannicall and vniuſt Iudge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE VIII. I beleeue in the Holie Ghoſt:</head>
                  <p>TO beleeue a right in the holy ghoſt,<note place="margin">Iohn 15.26. &amp; 1. Ioh 5. n. 7</note> according to expreſſe Scripture, and the Nicene Creed, is to maintaine and teach, that he proceedeth from the Father and the Sonne, and is of the ſame eſſence with the Father and the Sonne, of equall Maieſtie, and coeternal; but the chiefe Doctors of Proteſtancie (as was formerly shewed in the ſecond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle) teach that the eſſence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is incommunicable, and that both the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct eſſences fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Father, by which they make them diſtinct Gods, as was there prooued. Yea the Proteſtants are ſo farre from beleeuing aright this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, that <hi>Feuardentius</hi> a Catholike Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22753:62"/>
in his Treatiſe, entituled THEO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MACHIA CALVINISTICA, conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them as guiltie of hereſie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, in at leaſt ſeuen and fiftie points, as you may ſee in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth chapter of the ſaid THEOMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHIA, in the firſt nine Chapters of which he sheweth,<note place="margin">Feuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius theoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. l. 7. per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> how they deny the Holy Ghoſts proceeding from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne; giue him a diſtinct eſſence from the Father; make him vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the Father and the Sonne; deny that he is to be adored together with the Father and the Sonne, &amp;c. and in the reſt of the Chapters that follow, they make him the Author of all ſinnes and wickedneſſe, and blaſphemouſly detract from his goodnes, ſanctitie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and infinite power; take al God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head from him, and transforme him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a meere diuell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE IX. I beleeue the Catholike Church, the Communion of Saints.</head>
                  <p>THe ninth Article is, I beleeue the Holy Catholike Church, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints. Which Article all ſortes of Proteſtants, are farther from beleeuing a right, then any of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
                  <p>For firſt as touching the word Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22753:62"/>
Luther quite blotted it out of the Creed,<note place="margin">See Iur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geinicius in bello quinti euangelij quart. C. 7.</note> and placed inſteed thereof, the word <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> fearing leaſt the word <hi>Catholike</hi> duly conſidered, might diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his Proteſtanticall Church (whoſe foundation he had then newly laide) to be but a new and Antichriſtian Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue.</p>
                  <p>Secondly concerning the Church it ſelfe, whereas Chriſt calleth it the Pillar and firmament of truth, and further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, that the Holy Ghoſt should guide it to all truth, to the end of the world, and that the gates of hell should not preuaile againſt it: the Proteſtants imitating their hereticall Granſires the Donatiſts,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15. &amp; Mat 16.18. &amp; cap. 5. v. 20. &amp; Ioh 14. v. 16. &amp;c. 16 v. 13. &amp; Mat 28. v. 20. Iohn Rainold in his the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies § 9. &amp; in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. § 9. &amp; D. White in his way to the Church § 26. and Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker lib. 2. contra bellarm. de eccleſ. q. 4. p. 322</note> generally teach that the Church both may and hath erred euen in fundamentall points.</p>
                  <p>Againe God ſpeaking of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, ſaith<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſay. c. 2. v. 2. &amp;c. 60. 61. 62. per totum. &amp; pſal. 19. v. 4. &amp; Epheſ 4.11.</note> that he would make her an euerlaſting glorie, and a ioy from generation to generation; that her gates should be continually open; that her watchmen should neuer ceaſe day nor night; that her Sunne should neuer goe downe, nor her Moone be hid; that it should neuer be ſaid of her, forſaken or deſolate; that she should be placed on the hill, and that all nations
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22753:63"/>
should flow vnto her; and that there should be Paſtors in her to the end of the world: but the<note n="*" place="margin">See in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note> Proteſtants, becauſe they cannot shew their owne Church from the Apoſtles time, till Luthers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacie, contend that the Catholike Church may be inuiſible; and that it was <hi>de facto.</hi> INVISIBLE for aboue a thouſand yeares, no true Paſtor (at leaſt of the Proteſtant Religion) being any where to be found.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly (to omit other notes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the true Catholike Church, which the Proteſtants vtterly denie, that thereby they may the better be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſupport their Antichriſtian Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue) whereas the<note n="*" place="margin">Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Tol. 8. cap. 9. &amp; Concil Gangre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe cap. 19. &amp; in praefat. &amp; Concili. generale 6. can. 56. &amp; cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolor. can. 68.</note> Church (vnder paine of ANATHEMA) commandeth all men, whom ſickneſſe and impoſsibilitie of age doe not exempt, to faſt the Lent, the foure Embers, all Fridaies and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdaies, and the Eaues of our B. Ladie and the Apoſtles, from flesh; the doctors of Proteſtancie generally affirme, that faſting is a worke indifferent, and doe ordinarilie eate flesh in Lent and other faſting dayes, yea they commonly make their greateſt feaſts on the ſollemneſt faſts, and hold him a ſuperſtitious fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that maketh a difference of meates on ſuch dayes; which they could not doe if they beleued the Catholike Church,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:22753:63"/>
or credited our Sauiour, where he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that whoſoeuer refuſeth to <hi>heare the Church, should be as a heathen and a publican.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luther tom. 4. de Eccleſia c. 9. &amp; Cal. l. 3. Inſt. c. 20. n. 24. and Muſculus in locis commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ca. de deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo. prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept. 5.</note> and thus you ſee how farre the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants are from beleeuing aright the Catholike Church, which is taught in the firſt part of this ninth article. And as touching the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> which is the ſecond part of this Article, in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that the Saints cannot heare our Prayers, yea that ſuch as be dead, doe ſo ſleepe, that they vnderſtand nothing, and that the liuing haue no fellowship with the dead; they ſufficiently intimate that they cannot communicate with vs in thoſe prayers we make to Almightie God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE X. I beleeue the remiſſion of ſinnes.</head>
                  <p>AL Catholike Doctors from time to time, according to expreſſe <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 1. v. 23. &amp; Acts 3.19. Heb. 9. v. 28. Mich. 7.19. Pſal. 50. v. 9. Ezech. 36 24. &amp; 1. Cor. 6. v. 11. &amp; Acts 22.16. 1. Iohn. 1. v. 7. Apocal. 1.6. Heb. 9.13. Tim. 26. See Iurgenicius in bello quinti Euangelij cap. 7.</note> Scripture and this article, haue taught; that God, through the Paſsion &amp; death of Chriſt, doth truly remitte their ſins, who by Baptiſme, or any other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, lay hold on Chriſts Paſsion, and are truly penitent: but the Caluino-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants following their maiſter Caluin,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:22753:64"/>
doe generally teach;<note place="margin">Sinne truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in vs, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther is it taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by Baptiſme but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the guilt is blotted out by imputation it is nothing. So Caluin. in Antid. Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 5. Againe, now it is manifeſt, how falſe it is which ſome long ſince haue taught, that by Baptiſme we are looſed and freed from Originall ſinne. lib. 4. inſt. cap. 15. n. 10. Againe, let no man flatter him ſelfe, when he heareth that ſinne alway remaineth in vs. ibid. n. 11. See alſo l. 3. inſtit. c. 11. n. 2. &amp; 22. &amp; lib. 2. inſt. c. 1. n. 8. &amp; 9. &amp; l. 3. c. 12. n. 4; neither are we aſhamed to ſay that Iuſtice is the hiding of the offence. So Whitaker ad 8. rat. Camp. Remit our offences, that is, doe not impute them; ſo the Palantine Cathechiſme quaeſt. 126, &amp; 36 Sinnes in vs are not taken away, but in the Iudgement of God; that is, they are not ſmputed. So Paraeus in Theſibns de peccato. See Iurgiewicius in bello 5. Euang. in hoc Articulo.</note> that ſinne truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in vs euen after Baptiſme; and that it is neuer truly remitted, though to the elect it be not imputed.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I cannot ſee, how Proteſtants can ſay this tenth Article of their Creed, at leaſt I cannot but maruel that they doe not alter it, and ſay, <hi>I beleeue then my ſinnes ſhall not be imputed to me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE XI. I beleeue the Reſurrection of the bodie.</head>
                  <p>TOuching the Reſurrection of the dead, which is the Eleuenth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Apoſtles Creed, though I can not generally accuſe the Proteſtants, as not beleeuing the ſame, yet Brentius one of their chiefe Doctors will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22753:64"/>
that the maior part amongſt them, doe not beleeue the ſame; his words be theſe. <hi>Etſi nulla ſit inter nos, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Brentius in Luca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> c. 2. hom. 35. See Caluin-Turciſ. lib. 4. c. 5.</note> although amongſt vs, there be no pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſsion, that the ſoule dieth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the body, and that there is not a reſurrection of the dead; yet that moſt impure and prophane life which the greateſt part follow, doth plainly shew, that they are perſwaded that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life, there is no life, at leaſt they are not certaine of it, yea ſome when they are moſt ſober, as well as when they are drunke; in there familiar talke, caſt forth ſuch ſpeaches, by which they plainly ſignifie, that they do not beleeue the reſurrection of the dead. So <hi>Brentius, Schluſſelberg,</hi> alſo a Lutheran Proteſtant will tell you, that if it be true which the Caluino-Proteſtants affirme, that Chriſt in his Reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>on, reſumed not that blood, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> shedde on the Croſſe, two abſurdities will neceſſarily follow; firſt,<note place="margin">Schluſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg in theolog. Caluin. lib. 1. art. 20. See Iurgiewi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius in bello 5. Euangelij quart. D.</note> that mankind was redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with corruptible and putrifying blood contrarie to that of <hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and ſecondly that Chriſt contrarie to the propheſies of the Holy Ghoſt, ſaw corruption: whence it appeareth (quoth he) that the Caluiniſts albeit they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme in word and writing, yet in their hart they do not beleeue the <hi>Reſurrection
<pb n="08" facs="tcp:22753:65"/>
of the dead.</hi> So <hi>Schluſſelberg.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As touching <hi>Caluin</hi> the father of al English, Scottish, French, and Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian Proteſtants, it plainely appeareth by an epiſtle which his Cymiſt and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brother * <hi>Farellus</hi> wrote vnto him,<note place="margin">Quod res tibi incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibilis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil miru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hac ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne permo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis, ſi cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das nouis corporibus aliquando nos indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endos, hoc à ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na alienu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, &amp;c. <hi>So Farel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long confutation of this errour, concludeth thus.</hi> Atque tibi ſatisfactura ſpero, niſi mentem tuam nimis occupatam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periant, quod à pictate &amp; à modeſtia tua procul abeſt. Sed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men leuiter pro noſtra ámicitia, monendum te cenſui, quia nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cum te audirem, ſubuerebar, ne altiores apud te radices egiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet haec opinio, quam vt facile eam abijceres. <hi>Hetherto Farellus.</hi> in epiſt. ad Caluinum. an. <hi>1549</hi> cuius initium eſt. <hi>Litteras tuas,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; eſt epiſt. <hi>78.</hi> inter epiſt. Caluini. edit per Petum Sanctean dicum. <hi>Geneuae.</hi>
                     </note> that he was far from beleeuing this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead; and the like we may iudge of his followers, for they all deny that Chriſt can make his owne body to be Really preſent in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at once, as Schluſſelberg proueth at large, and they further deny (as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shewed, that Chriſt could, or at leaſt did not, (through the Scriptures and all Antiquitie, ſtand againſt them) goe out of his Mothers wombe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violating her virginitie, or out of the Sepulchre without remoouing the ſtone; or into the chamber where the Apoſtles were a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>bled, the doores being shut, either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> which is a leſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, and the beliefe of it will ſooner ſinke into mens mindes, conſidering
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22753:65"/>
that Chriſt was God and Man; then that mens bodies after ſo manie alterations, mutations, and corruptions should riſe againe (euen in the twinkling of an eye) the verie ſame that they were in this mortall life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="article">
                  <head>ARTICLE XII. And the life euerlaſting.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the life euerlaſting, which the Saints enioy in heauen, and is here treated of in this 12. and laſt Article, the Doctors of Proteſtancie, are as farre from beleeuing a right, as any of the former.<note place="margin">Mat. 10. v. 18. &amp; Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 7. v. 21.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For firſt, whereas the Scripture ſaith, <hi>if you will enter into life euerlaſting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e muſt keepe the Commandements,</hi> and, not that beleefe only but deedes muſt bring vs to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; they generally teach, that faith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth Iuſtifie, and that the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements are impoſsible to be kept, and therefore farre from being neceſſarie to the attainement of heauen.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, whereas the ſacred<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 3.5 &amp; 37. &amp; Titus 3 5. &amp; Rom 5.12. &amp; Epheſ. 2. v. 3. &amp; 1. Cor. 15. v. 22.</note> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and out of it all Catholike Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors<note n="(b)" place="margin">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine l. 3. de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cap. 9. &amp; alij paſſim.</note> teach, that Baptiſme is the only key that openeth vnto vs the Gate of this life euerlaſting: The Proteſtants<note n="(c)" place="margin">Calmin. l. 4. inſt. c. 16. n. 24. &amp;c. 15. n. 10. &amp; 20. &amp; cap. 16. n. 17. &amp; 26. &amp; in antidot. Concil. Trident. ſeſſ. 5. See the former.</note> place thoſe children there who die with
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:22753:66"/>
out it; and further adde, that Baptiſme neither hindereth nor furthereth in the way of ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly whereas all Catholike<note n="(d)" place="margin">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine l. 4. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſt c. 8. &amp; de fide &amp; ſymbolo. &amp; lib. de patientia cap. 26. &amp; lib. de fide ad Petrum. c. 38.</note> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, according to the expreſſe word of God, euer taught and beleued, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pagan, Heretike, nor Schiſmatike, could enter into life euerlaſting; the Proteſtants affirme, that not only He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes and Schiſmatikes, but Heathen alſo and Infidels (ſuch is their wicked) as they tearme it) Charitie) may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; <hi>In vita aeterna,</hi> &amp;c. In the kingdome of heauen (ſaith Zwinglius)<note n="*" place="margin">Vide praefatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Zwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glij tom. 1. lib de prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia cap. 6. &amp; Luther in Geneſ. cap. 47 &amp; Schluſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg. lib. 3. Theolog. Cal. ant. 7. See Caluino Turciſ. lib. 4. cap. 9.</note> We shall ſee Hercules, Theſeus, Socrates, Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Antigonus, &amp;c. yea (ſaith he) if I might haue my choiſe, I would rather chooſe the lotte of Socrates or Seneca, then of any Roman Emperour, King, or Prince addicted to Poperie. So Zwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius, and the like is affirmed by Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therus, Hardenbergius, Toſſanus, Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus, and Bullinger.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, whereas the<note n="*" place="margin">Apocal 21. v. 27.</note> Scripture plainly ſaith, that no ſpotted or defiled thing shall enter into the Holy Citie; the Proteſtants make no queſtion, but that all of their fraternitie, shall goe thither, who yet (as they themſelues
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:22753:66"/>
confeſſe) haue alway their ſoules ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from toppe to toe, and that alſo with mortal ſin; ſin<note n="(h)" place="margin">Caluin in antid. concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 5. &amp; lib. 4 inſt. c. 15. n. 10. 11. &amp; lib 2. c. 1. n. 8.</note> remaineth in vs; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is taken away by baptiſme. So Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin; and againe,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ibid. n. 9.</note> all the parts of our ſoules are poſſeſſed with ſinne;<note n="(k)" place="margin">Lib. 3. Inſt. c. 12. n. 4.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any thing in vs free from a deadly contagion.</p>
                  <p>To all which, if you adde that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaine Doctrine of the Apoſtle of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancie<note n="(l)" place="margin">Luther in collog menſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c. 49. tit. de vita aeterna.</note> affirming that in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen shall be <hi>dogges, sheepe, oxen,</hi> and other like Creatures, for the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants to ſport with all, it will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly appeare, that the Doctors of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancie, are verie farre from beleeuing a right this twelft and laſt Article of the Apoſtles.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:22753:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER IV.</hi> That the god of the Proteſtants, eſpecially thoſe of the Caluino-Puritan ſect, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their chiefe doctrines, and the famous confeſsions of ſome of the ſame fraternitie, is no other but a diuell of Hell.</head>
               <p>THat the Author of euill, is no other then a diuell, no good Chriſtian euer queſtioned, neither doth Caluin deny, but that if God may be ſaid to be the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caluin contra Liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos c. 14.</hi> Si qui dij turpia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt non ſunt dij Euripides. impia &amp; ſcelerata opera dij beati non faciunt. <hi>Homer. Odyſſ.</hi> Pugnandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus modis ne quis in ciuitate quam vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus recte gubernari Deum authorem ſed cauſam eſſe malorum dicere vel audire, quia nec pium eſt ita dicere, nec ipſum dictum ſecum conſiſtit Plato lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Repub.</note> author of euill, it may iuſtly be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that God is a diuell: now that the Proteſtants in generall, eſpeciall thoſe of the Caluinian ſeperation, make God the Author of all ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whatſoeuer, their owne writings will giue ſufficient teſtimonie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mala opera in impijs operatur, quit audet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare, ſe etiam in malis operibus ſaepe coactum aliud facere quam cogitauit.</hi> God doth worke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill workes in euill men, who dareth deny, but that he hath often ben com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled in euill workes to do otherwiſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:22753:67"/>
then he thought. So <hi>Luther</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">Luther in affert. art. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. Witt. an. 1520. art. 36. See the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants apologie tract 2. c. 2. ſect. 10 ſub 14. Fox in his acts and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Willet in his Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſi paſſim Zwingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſerm. de proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia. c. 6. tom. 1. &amp; cap. 5. an 1530. See Schl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelberg in theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. art. 8. p. 77. Melanct. coment. in Rom 8 edit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Caluini l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nn. 23 n. 7.</note> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants Prophet and euangeliſt. When we committ murther or adultrie, it is the worke of God, who is the moouer, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and inforcer of it. ſo <hi>Zwinglius, Fox</hi> and <hi>Willets</hi> true Proteſtant confeſſor and martir: againe; although a bull do bull a whole heard of kine, yet it is no ſinne in him but a greater commendation, becauſe no Law forbiddeth him; yet if the maſter of the bull should lie with more wiues then his owne, he should offend, ſince the Law commaundeth ſaying, <hi>Thou shalt not committ adultry,</hi> euen ſo God hauing no Law prohibiting him he doth not ſinne, though he worke thoſe things which is ſinne in men. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ſay that God doth not only permit or ſuffer his creatures to worke or do any thing, but doth properly do all things him ſelfe, whether thoſe workes be indifferent, as to eat and drinke <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or whether they be euill, as the adultrie of <hi>Dauid.</hi> There is no reaſon why we should allow of this cold gloſſe, <hi>That God doth only permitt, and not alſo cauſe euills,</hi> ſo in effect <hi>Melancton:</hi> Againe; the abulterie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the treaſon of <hi>Iudas,</hi> are as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the workes of God, as the voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the conuerſion of <hi>Paule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a horrible decree I confeſſe (ſaith Caluin) and yet no man can deny but
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:22753:68"/>
that God forſaw, what end man should haue, and he therefore knew it, becauſe by his decree he had ſo ordained it, &amp;c. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Idem. lib. 3. jnſt cap. 21. n. 5.</note> we call Predeſtination, the eternall decree of God, by which he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained with him ſelfe, what he wil haue done with euery man, for all are not created with like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, but to ſome eternall life, to others eternal death is preordained, &amp;c.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid. n. 7.</note> whereſoeuer this pleaſure of God raigneth, no workes come into conſideration;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Lib. 2. Inſt. cap. 23. n. 2. See alſo lib. 3. inſt cap. 24 n. 14. &amp; 14.</note> men by the naked decree of God, without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of their owne, are Predeſtinated to eternall death;<note n="(e)" place="margin">Lib. 1. inſt. cap. 18. n. 1.</note> therefore whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer men doe, or the diuel himſelfe, God holdeth the ſterne, and conuerteth their indemeanours, to the execution of his iudgements; God would haue the perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious king Achab to be deceiued; the diuell doth offer his helpe, to effect that buſines; he is ſent with a certaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, to be a lying Spirit in the mouthes of all the Prophets;<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel is ſaid to blind the hearts of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credilous, but the efficacie of this error, commeth from God himſelfe;<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> man being iuſtly forced by God, doth doe what is not lawfull for him;<note n="(h)" place="margin">Lib. 1 Inſt. cap. 17. n. 5.</note> I farther graunt, that thieues and murtherers, and other malefactors, are the inſtruments of Gods diuine iuſtice;<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ibid. c. 18. n. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Abſolon pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:22753:68"/>
his fathers bed, by inceſtuous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultrie, doth commit a deteſtable wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, yet God pronounceth this worke to be his owne;<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. cap. 14. n. 2. ſee alſo lib. 2. inſt cap. 4. n. 5 l. lib. 3. inſt. cap. 24. n. 13.</hi> Non ita intelligen dum eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>quem vult in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durat,</hi> quaſi De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ipſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quae non eſſet, du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiem cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis opere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare enim dicitur quem mol liri noliri noluerit. Sic etiam execare quem i lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minare noluerit. Auguſt. li. de praed &amp; gratia cap. <hi>4. Caluin. l. 1 inſtit. c 18. n. 1. &amp; 2.</hi>
                  </note> there can be nothing more plaine, then where he ſo often pronounceth, that he blindeth the mindes of men, and ſtriketh them with giddines; that he inebriateth them with the ſpirit of drowſines, that he hardneth their hearts, &amp;c. <hi>(l)</hi> behold he directeth his voice vnto them, but to make them the more deafe, he ſendeth them light, but to make them the more blinde, he giueth them a remedie, but meaneth not to cure them, &amp;c. the impure ſpirit is therefore called Gods ſpirit, becauſe he doth anſwere to his becke and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and is rather an inſtrument in doing, then an author of him ſelfe. Thus and much more Caluin, in which as you ſee like a true childe of darkeneſſe, he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fairely for his Lord and maiſter the diuell, clearing him as much as in him lyeth, from being any principall author of euill (as all good Chriſtians hold him to be) and layeth it wholly on Gods shoulders, he maketh God (I ſay) the only, abſolute, and principal author of all wickedneſſe, neither will he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the word (Permiſsion) <hi>ridiculum eſſet,</hi> &amp;c. It were ridiculous (ſaith he) that a Iudge should only permit, and not alſo
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:22753:69"/>
decree what hee would haue done;<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. c. 14 n. 2.</note> where it is ſaid, that God doth blinde men, and harden their hartes, may put it off, by flying vnto Gods <hi>Permiſsion,</hi> as if God by leauing the Reprobate, did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to be blinded by the diuel; but ſince the ſpirit pronounceth, that mans blindnes and madneſſe,<note place="margin">Caluin. lib. 1 inſt cap 18 n. 3. See alſo lib. 3. inſt c. 23. n 6.</note> is inflicted by Gods iuſt iudgement, that ſolution is ouer-friuolous; againe, now I haue plainely shewed that God is the author of all thoſe things which thoſe <hi>Cenſurers</hi> (meaning Catholikes) would haue to happen by his <hi>idle permiſsion</hi> only.<note place="margin">Bucer in enarrat in epiſt. ad Rom. p. 394. &amp; 239 an. 1536.</note> So <hi>Caluin</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pharao (ſaith Bucer) did what God would haue him, neither could he doe otherwiſe; when God put into the hart of Dauid to number the people, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God was willing to haue him to doe it, and wrought it in him;<note n="*" place="margin">Idem in cap. 1. ad Rom p. 7 2. &amp; in cap 9. pag. 459. Beza in appotiſ. 8</note> ſince God <hi>ſeduceth, hardeneth, deliuereth into a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſence, ſendeth a powerful errour to make men doe ſuch a thing,</hi> it approoueth that he doth not onely permit them to fall into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour by forſaking them, but alſo by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining their hearts.</p>
               <p>God (ſaith Beza) doth worke al things without exception, whether they be good or badde, vertuous or vicious, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he should liue in idleneſſe;<note n="(g)" place="margin">Idem contra Caſtalion apud Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium in theomac. Cal.</note> if God did only <hi>permit</hi> ſinnes to be done, he were not Omnipotent, but an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:22753:69"/>
God, idle, ſlouthful, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident;<note n="(h]" place="margin">Idem contra Sycoph. apud Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeum lib. contra Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. rat. 8. p. 218.</note> humaine reaſon telleth vs, that he is no leſſe in fault, who is able to ſaue one from deſtruction, &amp; yet ſaueth him not, then if he himſelfe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him;<note n="(k)" place="margin">Idem in volum theol. 1. pag. 417</note> we acknowledge that God hath not only Predeſtinated men to damnation, but alſo to the cauſes of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. Now the cauſes of damnation being ſinnes, it muſt needs follow, that God Predeſtinateth men vnto ſinne, &amp; conſequently is the Author of ſinne.</p>
               <p>God doth not onely <hi>permit men</hi> to fall into ſinne (ſaith Marlorat) but he will haue it ſo, and doth ſo ordaine,<note place="margin">Marlorat in cap. 1. ad Rom. v. 24. &amp; cap. 9 v. 18.</note> and by his commandement, Sathan the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of hell, doth riſe vp againſt vs, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully working what him liſteth, in the hearts of the wicked.</p>
               <p>Many men hold a ſtale opinion (ſaith Whitaker) that what ſinnes ſoeuer are committed by any one,<note place="margin">Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker apud Duraeum rat. 8. p. 217. See alſo pag. 214. Se in Caluin. aut Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorat, &amp;c.</note> are done onely by Gods permiſsion, and not his will, &amp; this <hi>permiſsion,</hi> they wholly ſeuer from Gods will, whereas God doth not only <hi>permit,</hi> but by his powerful will, would haue all things done which the wicked doe.</p>
               <p>God (ſaith Willet) an other English Doctor) hath deſtined ſome to be the veſſels of his wrath,<note place="margin">Willet in ſynopſi. pag. 554.</note> without any reſpect to their workes, whether good or bad.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="206" facs="tcp:22753:70"/>
                  <note place="margin">Crowly in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollogie, for the Engleſh writers.</note>I confeſſe (ſaith <hi>Crowly</hi>) theſe are my words, that Gods Predeſtinaito<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was the only cauſe of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, but not conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of al ſinne; for ſuch as haue eyes to ſee doe ſee; that <hi>Adams</hi> fall was good <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the only cauſe why <hi>Adam</hi> was aſſaulted and ouerthrowne by Sathan was the Predeſtination of God; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I haue ſaid that Gods Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the only cauſe of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and of the murther of <hi>Cain</hi> againſt his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abell,</hi> yea that the moſt wiked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that euer were, of God appointed to be wicked eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they were, ſo <hi>Crowly</hi> in a booke entituled, <hi>The apologie or defence of English writers</hi> and Preachers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, <hi>ſcene</hi> and <hi>alowed,</hi> according to the order appointed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts make god the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er of all ſinne; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd they ſay that though the elect runne into Adulterie, muttherer, luſt, and the like ſines, yet they are neuer the more the ſonnes of the diuel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, no not for a moments ſpace. See Schluſſelberg in theolog. Caluin. art. 7. pag. 70.</note>It being euident then that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in generall eſpecially the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian, Zwinglian, &amp; English faction, make God the principall cauſe of all ſins and wickedneſſes, and repute the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill but as his <hi>Agent or inſtrument,</hi> and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo confeſſed by <hi>Caluin, Whitaker,</hi> and others, that the author of ſinne, is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the <hi>Diuill.</hi> I will cloſe vp this
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:22753:70"/>
chapter with the words of <hi>Philippus Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> a Lutheran Proteſtant, only applying that in generall to Proteſtants, which he affirmeth of the Caluiniſts in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deum quem colunt, inuocant, adorant, &amp;c.</hi> We ſay that the God whom the Caluiniſts (and all other Proteſtants) worship, inuocate, and adore, is a deſperate Arch-knaue, Arch-thiefe, Arch-tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, Arch-lyer, Arch-hangman, &amp;c. ſince there is no murther, no theift, no heinous offence, no deceipt, no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, no wickedneſſe, no lewdneſſe, in in the whole world to be thought or deuiſed ſo great, ſo horred, ſo groſſe, ſo abominable, which the God of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts (and other Proteſtantt) by his eſſentiall malice, doth not a hundred millions of times exceed and ſurpaſſe; vnder-firmiter, irrefragablliter, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſequitur, &amp;c.</hi> whence it followeth firmely, vnreſiſtably, &amp; without contradiction, that the Caluiniſts (and other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) in attributing ſuch properties and power to their God, are blinde, madde, and poſſeſſed by the diuel, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping and inuocating a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible diuell, inſteed of the All-potent, Eternall, and Euer-liuing God; Againe,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:22753:71"/>
                  <hi>Deus Caluiniſtarum eſt leuis, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The like affirme Heſſuſius &amp; Schluſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lelberg, two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therean miniſters and alſo Caſtalio (Caluins good bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther) in their notable Treatiſes, againſt this blaſphemous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of abſolute Predeſtination, from which moſt of the chiefe doctrines of Proteſtant Religion, take their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</note> The God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Caluiniſts (and other Proteſtants) is light, laſciuious, impure, variable, craftie, deceiptfull, bloody, the <hi>Molo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> deſcribed in holy writte, the roaring Lyon, the olde enemie, the accurſed Leuiathan, &amp;c. From which accurſed and euer execrable god, or rather di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, the good God of heauen deliuer vs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22753:71"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
